Business Secrets with Rajiv Gupta Sir.
राजीव गुप्ता सर के साथ बिज़नेस सीक्रेट्स।
hello. Loosely you can explain that
नमस्ते। लूजली आप यह समझा सकते हो कि
What did Dhirubhai Ambani tell Mukesh Ambani
धीरूभाई अंबानी ने मुकेश अंबानी को क्या
Said. Don't enjoy the things I created.
कहा। मेरी बनाई हुई चीज के ऊपर ऐश मत करो।
Earn your stripes. But today I
अर्न योर स्ट्र्राइप्स। लेकिन मैं आज
I am confessing. I also stand
कन्फेस कर रहा हूं। मैं भी स्टैंड
I am corrected. When that investment of Jio
करेक्टेड हूं। जब वो Jio की इन्वेस्टमेंट
Was doing. I was working for Reliance.
कर रहे थे। आई वास वर्किंग फॉर Reliance।
I said brother where are you going in telecom
मैंने कहा भाई कहां टेलीकॉम में घुस रहे
yes? what happen? today they are ruling even
हो? व्हाट हैपें? टुडे दे आर रूलिंग इवन
There. under what conditions should you stay out
देयर। अंडर व्हाट कंडीशन शुड यू स्टे आउट
of business?" If you choke, your
ऑफ़ बिज़नेस?" अगर आपका दम घुटता है, आपका
I don't feel like it, better to stay in the business.
मन नहीं होता, बेटर टू स्टे ऑफ द बिज़नेस।
You will live a life of suffocation and mortification. you are not
घुट-घुट के मरमर के जिओगे। यू आर नॉट
Doing any favor to anything. lots of
डूइंग एनी फेवर टू एनीथिंग। बहुत सारे
Fuzzies need a little reality check
फजीस को एक छोटी सी रियलिटी चेक की जरूरत
is also there. Failure will happen many times. Yours
भी है। फेलियर होगा बहुत बार होगा। आपका
which is a so called world changing idea
जो सो कॉल्ड वर्ल्ड चेंजिंग आईडिया है हो
It might change four times and be something else
सकता है वो चार बार चेंज हो और कुछ और ही
It should be done. whoever is telling you that quick
बन जाए। जो भी आपको बोल रहा है कि क्विक
He is Mani, he is misleading you. personal
मनी है वो आपको गुमराह कर रहा है। पर्सनल
How should the game of finance be played? ₹1 Lakh
फाइनेंस की गेम कैसी खेलनी चाहिए? ₹1 लाख
vs ₹1 Lakh vs ₹1 Crore. that's a
वर्सेस ₹1 लाख वर्सेस 1 करोड़। दैट्स अ
Very good way to really increase your wealth.
वेरी गुड वे टू रियली इंक्रीस योर वेल्थ।
Great Marriages Can Lead to Great Businesses.
ग्रेट मैरिजेस कैन लीड टू ग्रेट बिज़नेसेस।
If your life partner is someone with you
इफ योर लाइफ पार्टनर इज समवन विथ हुूम यू
Can share your pain and she can add value in
कैन शेयर योर पेन एंड शी कैन वैल्यू ऐड इन
Giving Your Perspective. this is one of the
गिविंग योर पर्सपेक्टिव। दिस इज़ वन ऑफ़ द
Secrets of Gujarati Business One Being So
सीक्रेट्स ऑफ़ गुजराती बिज़नेस वन बीइंग सो
Successful. 50% off the next scene doesn't
सक्सेसफुल। 50% ऑफ़ द नेक्स्ट सीन डजंट
Want to join the family business. Why? Over
वांट टू जॉइन द फैमिली बिज़नेस। क्यों? ओवर
Bearing seniors in the family. their thinking
बियरिंग सीनियर्स इन द फॅमिली। इनकी सोच
What is? that this is an incarnation of God. But
क्या है? कि भगवान का ये अवतार है। बट
because of humility they are calling
बिकॉज़ ऑफ़ ह्यूमिलिटी दे आर कॉलिंग
Themselves asking. Breathe the Kids Yard
देमसेल्व एस्किंग। बच्चों को यार सांस
Let me take it. they can't take so much of crap
लेने दो। दे कैन नॉट टेक सो मच ऑफ़ क्रैप
And above all they need respect.
एंड अबव ऑल दे नीड रिस्पेक्ट।
This is what we tried to do throughout this podcast
इस पूरे पॉडकास्ट में हमारी यह कोशिश रही
that any student, any young person
है कि कोई भी स्टूडेंट, कोई भी यंग
Professional, any person knows about business
प्रोफेशनल, कोई भी इंसान बिजनेस के बारे
Learn A to Z in. in india if you
में ए टू जेड सीखे। इंडिया में अगर आपको
Any business has to scale,
किसी भी बिजनेस को स्केल करना है,
If you want to start your startup journey, then
स्टार्टअप की जर्नी स्टार्ट करनी है, तो
This is a must watch podcast episode
ऐसा पॉडकास्ट एपिसोड देखना बहुत जरूरी है
Taking notes. remember this is for people
नोट्स लेते हुए। याद रखिए दिस इज फॉर पीपल
who are not from business family but also
हु आर नॉट फ्रॉम बिजनेस फैमिली बट आल्सो
Verily
वेरीेंटली
If you are from a business family then you must
अगर आप एक बिजनेस फैमिली से हो आपको इस
Episodes are more useful than episodes on YouTube
एपिसोड से ज्यादा यूज़फुल एपिसोड YouTube
Will not be available in India. remember this even today
इंडिया पर नहीं मिलेगा। याद रखिए आज भी
Most Indian family businesses run on Jugaad
ज्यादातर इंडियन फैमिली बिनेसेस जुगाड़ पे
We are going on. There is no system, no
चल रहे हैं। ना कोई सिस्टम है, ना
No governance, no succession plan. just papa
गवर्नेंस, ना सक्सेशन का प्लान। बस पापा
Are you taking care of it or will your brother see it? and similar
संभाल रहे हैं या भाई देख लेगा। और इसी
Like this the legacy of many businesses ends
तरह बहुत सारे बिजनेसेस की लेगसी खत्म
This happens because chaos is a result of ego and structure
होती है क्योंकि केओस ईगो और स्ट्रक्चर की
Lack brings everything down. Therefore, today's
कमी सब कुछ गिरा देती है। इसलिए आज के
Professor Rajeev is the guest of the podcast
पॉडकास्ट के गेस्ट है प्रोफेसर राजीव
Gupta XVP Reliance first CEO a 60
गुप्ता एक्सवीपी Reliance पहले सीईओ एक 60
years old family business and now chair
साल पुरानी फैमिली बिनेस के और अब चेयर
Family Business of Person Masters Union
पर्सन मास्टर्स यूनियन के फैमिली बिनेस
Every type of family business is covered under the program
प्रोग्राम में हर टाइप की फैमिली बिज़नेस
He has experience of it from within.
का उनको अंदर से एक्सपीरियंस है।
Knowledge of practical corporate structure
प्रैक्टिकल कॉर्पोरेट स्ट्रक्चर की नॉलेज
Is. Generally speaking, the startup world
है। जनरली स्पीकिंग स्टार्टअप दुनिया की
I have knowledge. Why do businesses fail?
नॉलेज है। बिनेसेस क्यों फेल होते हैं?
How can we save our businesses? this business
बिनेसेस को बचा कैसे सकते हैं? इस बिजनेस
The coach doesn't know everything. rajeev sir has help
कोच को सब पता नहीं। राजीव सर हैज़ हेल्प
Multiple Entrepreneurs and Business Family
मल्टीपल एंटरप्रेन्यर्स एंड बिजनेस फैमिली
Through their own journeys. remember this one
थ्रू देर ओन जर्नीज़। याद रखिए यह एक
Practice theme podcast. rajeev sir
प्रैक्टिकिटी थीम पडकास्ट है। राजीव सर
He himself is very famous because he is the only
खुद बहुत मशहूर है इस वजह से कि वो सिर्फ
They do not give knowledge. He has written a book of his own
ज्ञान नहीं देते। उन्होंने खुद की एक बुक
Also written: The Lala Company which was brutally
भी लिखी है द लाला कंपनी जो ब्रूटली
In the most honest, comedic and no filter way
ऑनेस्ट कॉमडिक और नो फिल्टर तरीके से
Exposing Indian family businesses
इंडियन फैमिली बिनेसेस को एक्सपोज करती
Is. If you are also from a business family or if
है। अगर आप भी बिजनेस फैमिली से हो या अगर
If you are a young entrepreneur then this episode
आप एक यंग एंटरप्रेन्योर हो तो यह एपिसोड
You will feel that your own story is
देख के आपको लगेगा कि आप की खुद की कहानी
It is going on. Rajeev Sir in Masters Union
चल रही है। मास्टर्स यूनियन में राजीव सर
teaches how to start a family run business
सिखाते हैं कि कैसे एक फैमिली रन बिजनेस
be transformed into a future ready business
को एक फ्यूचर रेडी बिजनेस में बदला जा
Can. And yes you will get a full scholarship too
सकता है। और हां एक फुल स्कॉलरशिप भी मिल
Those who take their family seriously
रही है उनको जो सीरियसली अपना फैमिली
Want to transform business. all the
बिजनेस ट्रांसफॉर्म करना चाहते हैं। ऑल द
Details are given below. more than this
डिटेल्स आर गिवन डाउन बिलो। इससे ज्यादा
We did not create the Useful Business Podcast
यूज़फुल बिजनेस पॉडकास्ट हमने नहीं क्रिएट
This is the responsibility of TRS. so please watch it till the
करा है टीआरएस पर। तो प्लीज वॉच इट टिल द
End. Tech Notes. Whether you are a young
एंड। टेक नोट्स। चाहे आप एक यंग
You are an entrepreneur, you are an aspiring
एंटरप्रेन्योर हो, आप एक एस्पायरिंग
Are you an entrepreneur or if you have your own family
एंटरप्रेन्योर हो या अगर आप खुद के फैमिली
Want to scale your business, this is the
बिज़नेस को स्केल करना चाहते हो, दिस इज द
Podcast for you. enjoy but get set
पडकास्ट फॉर यू। एंजॉय बट गेट सेट
[music]
[संगीत]
Another notebook and pen podcast by Rajeev
एक और नोटबुक और पेन वाला पडकास्ट राजीव
With Gupta Sir. Sir there is a craze going on these days
गुप्ता सर के साथ। सर आजकल ना एक क्रेज चल
is online that people make money
रहा है ऑनलाइन कि लोगों को पैसे बनाने
Are. People need career guidance. people
हैं। लोगों को करियर गाइडेंस चाहिए। लोगों
Needs business guidance. we have behind you
को बिजनेस गाइडेंस चाहिए। आपके पीछे हमने
A blue colour light is on, which means time
ऑन करी है एक नीली कलर की लाइट मतलब टाइम
for Electricity MBA
फॉर बिजली एमबीए
Interesting welcome to TR S Sir podcast
इंटरेस्टिंग वेलकम टू टीआर एस सर पडकास्ट
we will quickly teach people at the beginning of
की शुरुआत में हम झट से लोगों को सिखाएंगे
that you can start your own business career for the long term
कि लॉन्ग टर्म के लिए खुद का बिजनेस करियर
How to plan AKA Guju Business
कैसे प्लान करते हैं ए केए गुजू बिनेस
secrets and madu business secrets and
सीक्रेट्स एंड माडू बिनेस सीक्रेट्स एंड
sindhi business secrets
सिंधी बिनेस सीक्रेट्स
hello sir ok hello are you ready for
नमस्ते सर ओके नमस्कार आर यू रेडी फॉर
Electricity MBA Absolutely OK Electricity MBA
बिजली एमबीए अब्सोलुटली ओके बिजली एमबीए
The first question of. What are the three biggest tips?
का पहला सवाल। तीन सबसे बड़े टिप्स क्या
Are they there? for young people so that they can live life
होते हैं? यंग लोगों के लिए ताकि वो लाइफ
I can set up a business. The very first tip
में बिजनेस खड़ा कर सकें। सबसे पहला टिप
This is where to go brother? What is direction?
ये है कहां जाना है भाई? दिशा क्या है?
Because direction will set the condition. We
क्योंकि दिशा ही दशा को सेट करेगी। हम
Why do you need to go? What is the purpose? How else
क्यों जाना है? पर्पस क्या है? और कैसे
Want to go? What is our path? These three things
जाना है? हम रास्ता क्या है? ये तीन चीजें
There should be crystal clear documentation
एकदम क्रिस्टल क्लियर डॉक्यूमेंटेड होनी
Needed We are ok. That's all. That's it. Ok.
चाहिए। हम ओके। दैट्स ऑल। दैट्स इट। ओके।
break down all these questions further
इन सारे क्वेश्चंस को और ज्यादा ब्रेक
Will download it during the podcast. Sure.
डाउन करेंगे पडकास्ट के दौरान। श्योर।
Ok. next question. There are a lot of such businesses
ओके। अगला सवाल। अ बहुत सारे ऐसे बिनेसेस
that fade away overtime
होते हैं जो ओवरटाइम फेड अवे हो जाते हैं
Or they have a downfall. so the most common
या उनका डाउनफॉल हो जाता है। तो सबसे कॉमन
What is a mistake? any long term
मिस्टेक क्या होती है? किसी लॉन्ग टर्म
Of successful business? what happens many times
सक्सेसफुल बिनेस की? कई बार क्या होता है
that when a man gets success then we
कि जब आदमी को सक्सेस मिलती है ना हम तो
She climbs on top of his head. He thinks of me
वह सर पर चढ़ जाती है। वो सोचता है मेरे
All the answers come on . and when he says
को सारे आंसर्स आते हैं। और जब वो कहता है
that I get all the answers, then I get intoxicated with that
कि मेरे को सारे आंसर्स आते हैं तो उस नशे
He takes such a hazardous risk
में वो कोई ऐसा हज़ार्डस रिस्क ले लेता है
which is not driven by data and the
व्हिच इज नॉट ड्रिवन बाय डेटा और द
Reality it is driven by the ego. and in that
रियलिटी इट इज ड्रिवन बाय ह ईगो। और उसमें
What happens is that he takes a gamble. It
क्या होता है कि एक वो जुआ खेलता है। इट
It is very different from a business risk. And
इज़ वेरी डिफरेंट फ्रॉम अ बिज़नेस रिस्क। और
That gambling is often driven by ego. End
वो जुआ अक्सर ड्रिवन बाय ईगो होता है। एंड
it ain't back by numbers and then whatever
इट इज नॉट बैक बाय नंबर्स एंड देन जो भी
built it falls flat on the face and
बिल्ड किया इट फॉल्स फ्लैट ऑन द फेस एंड
Off the story. Ok? Because this is a scaling
ऑफ द स्टोरी। ओके? क्योंकि ये एक स्केलिंग
The business is special. Family Business Special
बिजनेस स्पेशल है। फैमिली बिजनेस स्पेशल
Is. So the question to you is, what
है। इसलिए आपसे सवाल यह है कि जो
Successful businesses are in the long term
सक्सेसफुल बिनेसेस है इन द लॉन्ग टर्म
Their owners give their children three main tips
उनके ओनर्स अपने बच्चों को तीन मेन टिप्स
What do you usually give? look at the kids
क्या देते हैं अक्सर? देखो बच्चों को
One thing parents say is work hard.
पेरेंट्स का एक ये होता है मेहनत करो।
They always think that it is about our time, friend
उनको सब हमेशा ही लगता है यार हमारे टाइम
I used to work very hard. First is hard work
में बड़ी मेहनत होती थी। फर्स्ट इज मेहनत
do it. Second is blindly trusting someone
करो। सेकंड इज ब्लाइंडली किसी को ट्रस्ट
Do not do it. Make friends wisely too.
मत करो। दोस्तों को भी सोच समझ के बनाओ।
And the third thing is that friend, this is something I made
और तीसरा यह है कि यार मेरे बनाई हुई चीज
Don't be lazy over it. standing on your feet
के ऊपर ऐश मत करो। अपने पांव पर खड़े होकर
show. Earn your stripes. he always
दिखाओ। अर्न योर स्ट्र्राइप्स। वो हमेशा
They want that okay I will make it for you
ये चाहते हैं कि ठीक है मैं तो बना के दे
I have been. But I worked so hard
रहा हूं। लेकिन मैंने इतनी मेहनत से
Made. What did you do for yourself? you have
बनाया। तुमने अपने लिए क्या किया? तुमने
What did you do differently? So their always
अलग से क्या किया? तो उनका हमेशा यह
There is advice and there is concern as well
एडवाइस भी होती है और यह कंसर्न भी होता
that is until he gets on his own feet
है कि जब तक ये खुद अपने पांव पे नहीं
If they stand up, then what I'm going to give them
खड़े होंगे तो मैं जो इनको देने वाला हूं
They won't be able to handle even that. We are ok.
ये उसको भी नहीं संभाल पाएंगे। हम ओके।
Just expanding this question, one
अभी इसी सवाल को एक्सपैंड करते हुए एक
I will ask practical questions. a business
प्रैक्टिकल सवाल पूछूंगा। अ बिजनेस
It is said in the circles that Ambani
सर्कल्स में कहा जाता है कि जो अंबानी
He is the third generation of the family and is very capable
फैमिली की थर्ड जनरेशन है वो बहुत कैपेबल
This is an age compared to other business families. it
है एज कंपेयर टू अदर बिनेस फैमिलीज़। यह
Why is it being said? See, that is why it is said
क्यों कहा जा रहा है? देखिए, इसलिए कहा जा
It is happening because the results are coming. if you
रहा है बिकॉज़ रिजल्ट्स आ रहे हैं। अगर आप
Look at this, divide the business so intelligently
देखो इतना इंटेलिजेंटली बिजनेस को डिवाइड
to be done. it's not easy to divide
किया गया। इट्स नॉट इजी टू डिवाइड
Reliance empire but its DNA of the
Reliance एंपायर बट उसको डीएनए ऑफ द
Divide the child according to their DNA
बच्चों के डीएनए के हिसाब से उसको डिवाइड
to be done. Governance mechanisms were put in place.
किया गया। गवर्नेंस मैकेनिज्म्स लगाए गए।
and the potential of the business and potential
एंड पोटेंशियल ऑफ द बिनेस एंड पोटेंशियल
Off to the next jan was matched. that is
ऑफ द नेक्स्ट जन को मैच किया गया। दैट इज
Forest. The second thing is the scale of Reliance
वन। सेकंड चीज यह है Reliance जिस स्केल
I am sitting on it you know I use the term escape
पर बैठा है यू नो आई यूज द टर्म एस्केप
velocity that is almost escape velocity
वेलोसिटी वो ऑलमोस्ट एस्केप वेलोसिटी पे
Is. people process system governance it's a
है। पीपल प्रोसेस सिस्टम गवर्नेंस इट्स अ
Well oiled machine. So if the children are not capable
वेल ऑइल्ड मशीन। तो अगर बच्चे कैपेबल नहीं
Even if it were there it would be very difficult to destroy
होते तब भी बड़ा मुश्किल होता डिस्ट्रॉय
to do. But kids are capable. Our
करना। बट बच्चे कैपेबल हैं। अपने
I have seen grandfather. saw your father
ग्रैंडफादर को देखा है। अपने फादर को देखा
Is. I have seen him working hard. so what would have happened
है। मेहनत करते हुए देखा है। तो क्या होता
Is? When you watch kids learn from you,
है? जब आप बच्चे देखने से सीखते हैं,
We don't learn by speaking. So that DNA, that
बोलने से नहीं सीखते। तो वो डीएनए, वो
Hard work, that self-sacrifice comes into it.
मेहनत, वो सेल्फ सैक्रिफाइस आ जाता है।
That's the reason everybody is very sure that
दैट्स द रीज़न एवरीबॉडी इज वेरी श्योर दैट
This generation is going to do well. We are ok.
दिस जनरेशन इज गोइंग टू डू वेल। हम ओके।
No sir during this entire podcast I am a
इस पूरे पडकास्ट के दौरान ना सर मैं एक
First generation entrepreneur
फर्स्ट जनरेशन एंटरप्रेन्योर के
I will also talk to Perspective. Absolutely. And
पर्सेक्टिव से भी बात करूंगा। बिल्कुल। और
People who are going to inherit the business
जो लोग बिनेसेस इन्हहेरिट करने वाले हैं
From your parents and also from their perspective
अपने पेरेंट्स से उनके पर्सेक्टिव से भी
I will ask questions as we move forward. Ok. A
सवाल पूछूंगा एज वी मूव फॉरवर्ड। ओके। अ
The next question is asked in India that most
अगला सवाल भारत में कहा जाता है कि सबसे
There is more money in boring businesses.
ज्यादा पैसे बोरिंग बिनेसेस में होते हैं।
Which is not glamorous. Why? Look boring
जो ग्लैमरस नहीं है। क्यों? देखिए बोरिंग
What is business? For the children of today.
बिज़नेस क्या है? आजकल के बच्चों के लिए।
Its name is manufacturing.
उसका नाम है मैन्युफैक्चरिंग।
Manufacturing means in a factory
मैन्युफैक्चरिंग का मतलब फैक्ट्री में
to go, to the shop floor, to have a fight with the labour
जाना, शॉप फ्लोर पर जाना, लेबर से मगजमारी
doing, looking after the machines, quality
करना, मशीनंस को देखना, क्वालिटी को
Look And it is repetitive. But if we
देखना। एंड इट इज रेपिटेटिव। बट अगर हम
View MSMEs There are total MSMEs
एमएसएमईस को देखें जितने भी एमएसएमईस हैं
you know almost 60% of them are in the
यू नो ऑलमोस्ट 60% ऑफ देम आर इन द
Manufacturing sector. so that's why it said
मैन्युफैक्चरिंग सेक्टर। तो इसीलिए यह कहा
It seems that the dude is boring. But if we
जाता है कि यार बोरिंग है। लेकिन अगर हम
Think carefully, which country?
जरा ध्यान से सोचें कौन सा देश
Grew up without manufacturing? We
मैन्युफैक्चरिंग के बिना बड़ा हुआ है? हम
Who has become big on the strength of trading?
ट्रेडिंग के दम पे कौन सा बड़ा हो गया है?
So manufacturing is needed but there is fun in it
तो मैन्युफैक्चरिंग चाहिए लेकिन उसमें मजा
It does not come because there is repetition in it. so this
नहीं आता क्योंकि उसमें रेपटीशन है। सो ये
The saying is true. but the next generation
कहावत सही है। लेकिन नेक्स्ट जनरेशन के
So I want to say this brother, it is like this.
लिए मैं यह कहना चाहता हूं भाई ऐसा है।
Have patience. It is feeding your bills. It
पेशेंस रखो। इट इज फीडिंग योर बिल्स। इट
is feeding you know all yours which is good for you right now
इज फीडिंग यू नो ऑल योर जो अभी आप अच्छा
If you are living a lifestyle then go with it
लाइफस्टाइल जी रहे हो तो उसके साथ भी चलना
Learn. Behind glamorous things all the time
सीखो। हर हर वक्त ग्लैमरस चीजों के पीछे
There is no need to run away. Yes sir. My
भागने की जरूरत नहीं होती। हां जी। मेरा
I also have my own business. it's a talent
खुद का भी एक बिज़नेस है। इट्स अ टैलेंट
Management company. is a media agency. Very
मैनेजमेंट कंपनी। मीडिया एजेंसी है। बहुत
Monk is considered a glamorous company
ग्लैमरस कंपनी मानी जाती है मंक
Entertainment. Ok? but we have built it
एंटरटेनमेंट। ठीक है? बट वी हैव बिल्ट इट
Over Seven Years. and we've seen the wear and tear,
ओवर सेवन इयर्स। और हमने घिसाई देखी है,
I have seen struggles and challenges. and at this
स्ट्रगल्स, चैलेंजेस देखे हैं। एंड एट दिस
Point being, young business professionals are
पॉइंट ना एज यंग बिज़नेस प्रोफेशनल्स यह
I have found out that at some point there is no such person
पता चला है कि यार एट सम पॉइंट ना कोई ऐसा
Business should be started where repeatability is important
बिजनेस खोलना चाहिए जहां रिपीटेबिलिटी
Factor it in the product. where you can
फैक्टर हो प्रोडक्ट में। वेयर यू कैन
Design a Product Once and Keep It Growing
डिजाइन अ प्रोडक्ट वंस एंड कीप ग्रोइंग इट
For ever. You have said this very well.
फॉर एवर। ये आपने बहुत ही अच्छा बोला है।
because if we're doing customized things
क्योंकि अगर हम कस्टमाइज चीजें कर रहे हैं
not as many times as in manufacturing
ना जितनी बार मैन्युफैक्चरिंग में क्या
Is? Your dis became yours if it is a mass
है? आपका डिज़ बन गया आपका इफ इट इज़ अ मास
produced manufacturing than you are
प्रोड्यूस्ड मैन्युफैक्चरिंग देन यू आर
Absolutely right, you worked hard, then you
अब्सोलुटली राइट कि आपने मेहनत करी देन यू
Can reap the benefits for some point of time
कैन रीप द बेनिफिट्स फॉर सम पॉइंट ऑफ़ टाइम
The business you mentioned brother is digging a well every day
जो बिज़नेस आपने बताया भैया रोज कुआं खोदना
and drink water everyday and come to a well the next day
है और रोज पानी पीना है और अगले दिन कुएं
should be excavated more thoroughly because
की खुदाई और अच्छी तरह होनी चाहिए क्योंकि
A lot of people have come. so you absolutely
बहुत सारे लोग आ गए हैं। सो यू अब्सोलुटली
Right. ah you know sir i think the audience
राइट। अ पता है सर मुझे लगता है कि ऑडियंस
also by now it has been understood that the businesses which
भी अब तक ये समझ गई है कि जो बिनेसेस
Only those businesses which are profitable are cool businesses. Today's
प्रॉफिटेबल है वही कूल बिनेसेस हैं। आज के
That face of the world has gone where the coolness of business
जमाने में वो फेस गया जहां बिजनेस का कूल
To be or not to be depends on their raise capital
होना या ना होना उनके रेज कैपिटल पर
Was dependent. at this point people
डिपेंडेंट था। एट दिस पॉइंट पीपल
Appreciate Businesses That Make Money. And me
अप्रिशिएट बिज़नेसेस दैट मेक मनी। और मैं
I believe that in modern day India
मानता हूं कि भारत में मॉडर्न डे भारत में
99% of the profitable businesses are
99% ऑफ़ द प्रॉफिटेबल बिज़नेसेस आर
Repeatability based. It's absolutely fine. One
रिपीटेबिलिटी बेस्ड। बिल्कुल ठीक है। एक
Something you can repeat every day
ऐसी चीज जो आप दोहरा सकते हो राइट हर दिन
Every year and then learn to scale it. yes
हर साल एंड देन लर्न टू स्केल इट। यस
Absolutely. Fair to perfectly fine.
अब्सोलुटली। फेयर टू से बिल्कुल ठीक है।
I will give him coaching today. Ok. Moving on.
उसकी कोचिंग देंगे आज। ओके। मूविंग ऑन।
Name of the most iconic group of our country
हमारे देश के सबसे आइकॉनिक ग्रुप का नाम
It is Tata Group. for 160 years
है टाटा ग्रुप। 160 सालों के लिए वो
Have been profitable. they grew there overall
प्रॉफिटेबल रहे हैं। दे ग्रोन देयर ओवरऑल
Group of Businesses. So his three businesses
ग्रुप ऑफ़ बिनेसेस। तो उनकी तीन बिजनेस
I would like to know the secrets. Ok. I think
सीक्रेट्स जानना चाहूंगा। ठीक है। आई थिंक
Great question. The first thing is that Tata
ग्रेट क्वेश्चन। पहली चीज यह है कि टाटा
that the whole family has been right from
की जो पूरी फैमिली रही है राइट फ्रॉम
Founder Till Ratan Tata never owned
फाउंडर टिल रतन टाटा कभी भी मालकियत वाली
There was no feeling at all. Custodianship
फीलिंग ही नहीं थी। कस्टोडियनशिप
Brother, I am the custodian of the next generation.
भैया मैं कस्टोडियन हूं अगली जनरेशन का।
I am not the master of what I want to enjoy
मैं मालिक नहीं हूं इसका कि मेरे को ऐश
Have to do it. First. Second Thing Joe Society
करनी है। फर्स्ट। सेकंड थिंग जो सोसाइटी
It's a give back thing. Now we are the people
के लिए गिव बैक वाली चीज है। अब हम लोग यू
No CSR has come, give me 2%. there was no rule at that time
नो सीएसआर आ गया 2% दे दो। उस समय कोई रूल
It was not there. but you know the way back 70 years back you
नहीं था। बट यू नो वे बैक 70 इयर्स बैक यू
no there was a crush in the factory for
नो देयर वास अ क्रश इन द फैक्ट्री फॉर
women we you know there were benefits that did
वुमेन हम यू नो देयर वर बेनिफिट्स दैट डिड
not exist in corporate India which is Tata
नॉट एकिस्ट इन कॉर्पोरेट इंडिया जो टाटा
used to give so concern for society give back to
देते थे सो कंसर्न फॉर सोसाइटी गिव बैक टू
Society and take care of your employees
सोसाइटी एंड टेक केयर ऑफ योर एम्प्लाइज ये
The three building blocks that remained came butt
जो तीन बिल्डिंग ब्लॉक्स रहे उनके बट आई
Will add a fourth one wherever the business goes
विल ऐड अ फोर्थ वन बिजनेस कहीं भी जाए
Zero compromise with value system
वैल्यू सिस्टम से जीरो कॉम्प्रोमाइज एंड
I can tell you from my friends who work
आई कैन टेल यू फ्रॉम माय फ्रेंड्स हु वर्क
V Tata, many times he says friend speed money
वि टाटा कई बार वो कहते हैं यार स्पीड मनी
you understand what is speed money they call it
यू अंडरस्टैंड व्हाट इज स्पीड मनी वो कहते
yes brother its no big deal we will do it slow
हैं भाई ऐसा कोई बात नहीं स्लो कर लेंगे
I will not give you money so you have to be able to stand
पैसा नहीं देंगे सो टू बी एबल टू स्टैंड
The ground is fine friend, there will be loss of business
ग्राउंड कि ठीक है यार बिज़नेस का लॉस होगा
Never mind, I will stay Value Systems
कोई बात नहीं मैं रहूंगा वैल्यू सिस्टम्स
So of these three, you said three and I said the fourth one too
तो ये तीन के आपने तीन बोले मैंने चौथा भी
I added I think that is very rare and
ऐड कर दिया आई थिंक दैट इज वेरी रेयर और
If these value systems were maintained
अगर यह वैल्यू सिस्टम्स मेंटेन हो जाते
you know i think this company is there for
यू नो आई थिंक दिस कंपनी इज देयर फॉर
Eternity and this lesson everyone should learn
इटरर्निटी और ये लेसन सबको सीखना चाहिए
Patience and Thank You Patience and Thank You
सब्र और शुक्र सब्र और शुक्र
Nice or OK Another Hypothetical Practical
नाइस या ओके एक और हाइपोथेटिकल प्रैक्टिकल
Question
सवाल
According to you our country's superstar
आपके अनुसार हमारे देश के सुपरस्टार
What does Shahrukh Khan tell his son Aryan
शाहरुख खान अपने बेटे आर्यन को क्या
will say about business because said
कहेंगे बिजनेस के बारे में क्योंकि कहा
It is said that Shahrukh Khan is the most popular actor in Bollywood
जाता है कि शाहरुख खान बॉलीवुड के सबसे
He is the best businessman. Absolutely. aryan khan
बेस्ट बिजनेसमैन है। बिल्कुल। आर्यन खान
What will you call it? You will tell them this, son
को क्या कहेंगे? उनको यह कहेंगे बेटा तूने
Have you seen me? What time do I sleep?
मेरे को देखा है ना मैं कितने बजे सोता
I get up at what time and I
हूं, कितने बजे उठता हूं और मैंने अपनी
What condition have you become in? he is exactly of
क्या हालत कर ली है? ही इज एक्जेक्टली ऑफ़
My Age. Ok? he has to first tell son
माय एज। ओके? ही हैज़ टू फर्स्ट टेल बेटा
One doesn't become Shahrukh just like that. To become Shahrukh
ऐसे ही शाहरुख नहीं बन जाता। शाहरुख बनने
Working 14, 16, 18, 20, 22 hours for
के लिए 14, 16, 18, 20, 22 घंटे काम करना
Does matter. And with so much wealth and fame
पड़ता है। और इतनी वेल्थ, इतनी शोहरत आने
Even after I'm Not Singing on My Laurels.
के बाद भी आई एम नॉट सिंग ऑन माय लॉरल्स।
Now I have become one. So first of all he
अब तो मैं बन गया। तो सबसे पहले वो
will teach you what I asked you at the beginning
सिखाएगा जो मैंने शुरू में आपने पूछा
Hard work is non-negotiable. The second Shahrukh
मेहनत वो नॉन नेगोशिएबल है। दूसरा शाहरुख
A very important thing is that everyone
का एक बहुत इंपॉर्टेंट चीज यह है कि सबको
take along with you respect he knows how to
साथ लेकर चलो रिस्पेक्ट ही नोस हाउ टू
Respect people wether it is a fan wether it
रिस्पेक्ट पीपल वेदर इट इज अ फैन वेदर इट
is an extended family and friends only
इज़ एन एक्सटेंडेड फैमिली और फ्रेंड्स ही
Nos How to Respect People. i think that
नोस हाउ टू रिस्पेक्ट पीपल। आई थिंक दैट
Is the second tip he is going to give him.
इज द सेकंड टिप ही इज़ गोइंग टू गिव हिम।
and thirdly he will tell I am sure to Aryan
एंड थर्ड ही विल टेल आई एम श्योर टू आर्यन
that son look at your father and grandfather
कि बेटा अपने फादर और ग्रैंडफादर को देखो
Where have we come from and all this
हम कहां से उठ के आए हैं और इतना सब कुछ
Even after it happened, it did not come to my mind
होने के बाद भी दिमाग में नहीं चढ़ा मैं
I am still grounded, my son is grounded
अभी भी ग्राउंडेड हूं तो बेटा ग्राउंडेड
stay in the air don't float because in the air
रहना हवा में मत तैरना क्योंकि हवा में
If you swim then your path will be somewhere above
तैरोगे ना तो ऊपर वाला रास्ता आपका कहीं
Nor does it let you fall anywhere. i think these are the
ना कहीं आपको गिराता है। आई थिंक दीज़ आर द
Three things I'm sure he would be telling me
थ्री थिंग आई एम श्योर ही वुड बी टेलिंग
Aryan Hum from Personal Finance Perspective
आर्यन हम पर्सनल फाइनेंस पर्सपेक्टिव से
what will you say? From personal finance, this is
क्या कहेंगे? पर्सनल फाइनेंस से वो ये
they will say that look friend it is like this if there was one
कहेंगे कि देखो दोस्त ऐसा है कि एक होती
This is personal wealth. Ok? insulate it
है पर्सनल वेल्थ। ठीक है? उसको इंसुलेट कर
Take it from business. We are making sure that the business grows
लो बिजनेस से। हम जिससे कि बिजनेस ऊपर
It may continue going down. So whichever one of yours
नीचे होता भी रहे। तो आपका जो एक
You have become accustomed to the lifestyle. So
लाइफस्टाइल की आपको एक आदत पड़ गई है। सो
May it continue for you. so I'm sure he will
वो आपकी चलती रहे। सो आई एम श्योर ही विल
Create those iron walls which anyone is smart
क्रिएट दोज़ आयरन वॉल्स व्हिच एनी स्मार्ट
Business family dude this is my personal
बिज़नेस फैमिली डस कि यार यह मेरी पर्सनल
For well being, you know we are your bread and butter
वेल बीइंग के लिए यू नो हम रोजी रोटी आप
Understand those cars that end lifestyle
समझ जाओ दोज़ कार्स दैट लाइफस्टाइल एंड
separate that from the business i think that
सेपरेट दैट फ्रॉम द बिज़नेस आई थिंक दैट
would be his great advice because business
वुड बी हि वेरीेंट एडवाइस बिकॉज़ बिज़नेस
Despite being a good leader, anything can
डिस्पाइट बीइंग अ गुड लीडर एनीथिंग कैन
Happens. Business means risk. it can be
हैपन। बिज़नेस का मतलब रिस्क है। इट कैन बी
because of you it can be insight of your
बिकॉज़ ऑफ़ यू इट कैन बी इनस्पाइट ऑफ़ योर
Best efforts. i think that's what he
बेस्ट एफर्ट्स। आई थिंक दैट्स व्हाट ही
Will definitely tell him. because shahrukh is
विल डेफिनेटली टेल हिम। बिकॉज़ शाहरुख हैज़
Also Come from Ambal Beginning and Jo Ambal
आल्सो कम फ्रॉम अंबल बिगिनिंग और जो अंबल
There is a beginning somewhere or the other
बिगिनिंग होती है ना वो कहीं ना कहीं
leaves an imprint of insecurity and
इनसिक्योरिटी की छाप छोड़ देती है और
It lasts for two-three generations. so i am
दो-तीन जनरेशंस तक वो रहती है। सो आई एम
Surely this thing will be secure, boss
श्योर ही विल से बॉस ये चीज तो सिक्योर
Do it and go. Akshay Kumar sir came on the show.
करके चलो। अक्षय कुमार सर आए थे शो पर।
I also asked him whether
उनसे भी मैंने ये पूछा कि कहीं ना कहीं
There is a middle class boy inside you right now
आपके अंदर एक मिडिल क्लास का लड़का है अभी
Too. He said yes absolutely. He Said
भी। उन्होंने कहा हां बिल्कुल। ही सेड
That. Because of that, hard work is being done. Absolutely
दैट। उस वजह से मेहनत हो रही है। बिल्कुल
Correct. So it's a super power almost came. Yes.
ठीक। तो इट्स अ सुपर पावर ऑलमोस्ट आई। यस।
So here we have talked about Tatas, Ambanis
तो हमने यहां टाटा की बात करी है, अंबानीज
I have talked about it, I have talked about Shahrukh Khan.
की बात करी है, शाहरुख खान की बात करी है।
I want to ask you a little googly question,
आपसे थोड़ा एक गुगली सवाल पूछना है कि ये
Those who are the top of the top people in India
जो टॉप ऑफ द टॉप लोग होते हैं भारत में
What is their personal finance strategy often?
इनकी पर्सनल फाइनेंस स्ट्रेटजी अक्सर क्या
it occurs? See what they do? To all
होती है? देखो ये क्या करते हैं? सबसे
This is their important strategy.
इंपॉर्टेंट स्ट्रेटजी इनकी ये होती है।
Don't put your eggs in one basket. We are the first
डोंट पुट योर एग्स इन वन बास्केट। हम पहली
The thing is this diversified portfolio. Second
चीज ये है डवर्सिफाइड पोर्टफोलियो। दूसरा
Don't Trust One Wealth Manager.
डोंट ट्रस्ट वन वेल्थ मैनेजर।
Have multiple wealth managers. third
हैव मल्टीपल वेल्थ मैनेजर्स। तीसरा
take a mix of people you know who are managing
टेक अ मिक्स ऑफ पीपल यू नो हु आर मैनेजिंग
Your Wealth. take a mix of people you don't
योर वेल्थ। टेक अ मिक्स ऑफ़ पीपल यू डोंट
No Pure Professional. i think anyone
नो प्योर प्रोफेशनल। आई थिंक कोई भी
A smart guy works with these three things.
स्मार्ट बंदा इन तीनों चीजों से चलता है।
Hum because this is the only way to diversify
हम बिकॉज़ दिस इज द ओनली वे टू डवर्सिफाई
And mitigate your risk. We don't know all the eggs
एंड मिटिगेट योर रिस्क। हम सारे अंडे ना
So, you have to put an asset with a person
तो एक बंदे के पास डालने हैं ना एक एसेट
Do you want to put him in class? This is my friend
क्लास में डालने हैं ना यह मेरा दोस्त है
This has to be given to him. A friend as well as a professional
इसको देने हैं। दोस्त भी है और प्रोफेशनल
is also there. I think this is what they follow and
भी है। आई थिंक दिस इज व्हाट दे फॉलो एंड
No wonder they do well. I mean if you see me last
नो वंडर दे डू वेल। आई मीन इफ यू सी लास्ट
Three Four Years and That's What If You See
थ्री फोर इयर्स एंड दैट्स व्हाट इफ यू सी
Any studies I mean the wealth of the richest
एनी स्टडीज आई मीन द वेल्थ ऑफ़ द रिचेस्ट
People in the country in three years would have
पीपल इन द कंट्री इन थ्री इयर्स वुड हैव
More than doubled may be B may be 2.5x. We
मोर देन डबल्ड मे बी मे बी 2.5 एक्स। हम
Or is this what the middle class of our country has to learn?
या यही सीखना है हमारे देश के मिडिल क्लास
To. absolutely how to get there
को। बिल्कुल अब्सोलुटली कि वहां तक कैसे
arrived and after reaching there further
पहुंचे और वहां पहुंचने के बाद और आगे
how to go?
कैसे जाएं?
to further that questions and are considered
टू फर्दर दैट क्वेश्चंस ओर माना जाता है
that the richest people in our country
कि हमारे देश के जो सबसे अमीर लोग हैं
His maximum money is in real estate
उनका मैक्सिमम पैसा रियलस्टेट में
specifically land it's true this is absolutely correct
स्पेसिफिकली लैंड सच है ये बिल्कुल सही
Is. okay because look what that land's
है। ओके क्योंकि देखो क्या है कि लैंड के
Our faith is firm in us that brother
साथ ना एक हमारी आस्था जमी हुई है कि भाई
land, land, property, gold, so land comes first
जमीन जमीन जायदाद सोना सो जमीन सबसे पहले
It comes. but again it depends on whom you
आती है। बट अगेन इट डिपेंड्स आप किस
You are talking about net worth. if you are
नेटवर्थ की बात कर रहे हो। इफ यू आर
talking somebody with multimillionaire crore you know
टॉकिंग समबडी विद मल्टीाउजेंड करोड़ यू नो
sort of asset base than he would have been
सॉर्ट ऑफ़ एसेट बेस देन ही वुड हैव मे बी
25 30% In The Land's End Among Others. you get
25 30% इन द लैंड एंड इन अदर्स। यू गेट
My point? But whose net worth is slightly less.
माय पॉइंट? बट जिसकी नेटवर्थ थोड़ी कम है।
may be the proportion of land may be higher in
मे बी द प्रोपोर्शन ऑफ़ लैंड मे बी हायर इन
That. because it entered the human mind
दैट। क्योंकि इंसान के दिमाग में ये घुसा
It has happened. Why is it in the ground? This big
हुआ है। क्यों जमीन में है? यह बड़ा
It is important. Firstly by selling the land
इंपॉर्टेंट है। एक तो जमीन को बेच बेच के
Can't eat it. I spent my money today so you
नहीं खा सकते। हम आज मेरा खर्चा आया तो यू
R. Force. It's a force locking. Second
आर फोर्स। इट्स अ फोर्स लॉकिंग। दूसरा
Everybody knows that God has stopped making
सबको पता है कि गॉड हैज़ स्टॉप मेकिंग
Land.
लैंड।
It will increase further. Wow!
और बढ़ेगी बढ़ेगी। वाह!
So brother, plant it in the ground, better late than never
तो भैया जमीन में लगाओ देर आए दुरुस्त आए
But it is a good investment so
लेकिन चौखी इन्वेस्टमेंट है तो इसलिए
but as I said once you reach a very
डालते हैं बट एज आई सेड वंस यू रीच अ वेरी
High level because then you also get wealth
हाई लेवल बिकॉज़ देन यू आल्सो गेट वेल्थ
advisors who will explain you that sir land
एडवाइर्स हु विल एक्सप्लेन यू कि सर लैंड
Apart from this there are other asset classes also. Butt Up
के अलावा भी अदर एसेट क्लासेस हैं। बट अप
To A Certain Networth I'm Saying
टू अ सर्टन नेटवर्थ आई एम आई एम सेइंग से
about 50% and may be closer to 50% would be
अबाउट 50% और मे बी क्लोजर टू 50% वुड बी
In Land. We are a
इन लैंड। हम अ
I hope the audience understands how much value it has
आई होप कि ऑडियंस ये समझे कि कितना वैल्यू
You are getting this short power from MBA
मिल रहा है इस शॉर्ट बिजली एमबीए में से
yes. And just 10 minutes have passed off
ही। एंड अभी 10 मिनट खत्म हुए हैं ऑफ
Recording. Still, I am saying this. Sir
रिकॉर्डिंग। फिर भी मैं ये कह रहा हूं। सर
The question is that in those business families
सवाल ये है कि जिन बिनेस फैमिलीज में
There are only daughters in today's era 2025
सिर्फ बेटियां हैं आज के जमाने में 2025
In. There is a family patriarchal mentality
में। वहां फैमिली पेट्रियाक की मेंटालिटी
It is different. What is happening? Reality
अलग होती है। क्या हो रहा है? रियलिटी
What is there in India? The look is totally different.
क्या है भारत में? देखो बिल्कुल अलग है।
If you have a son and a daughter, compare them
अगर आपका एक बेटा एक बेटी है उससे कंपेयर
If they do it then it is very clear. daughter's wedding
करते हैं तो बड़ा क्लियर है। बेटी की शादी
I invested all my business in my son
में लगा दिया सारा कुछ बिजनेस बेटे को
Will go. This still happens today. it is the same today
जाएगा। यह आज भी होता है। आज भी ऐसा ही
Is. That's why I always say that you
है। इसीलिए मैं हमेशा बोलता हूं आपने तो
I thought that whatever my friend gives to my daughter in marriage
यह सोच लिया कि यार बेटी को शादी में जो
I gave what I had to give. He came back after 5 years
देना था दे दिया। 5 साल बाद वो उठ के आ
Went. The law says it is 50%. So the fight
गई। लॉ तो कहता है उसका 50% है। तो लड़ाई
If you are getting it installed then please clarify. But
आप लगवा रहे हो तो क्लेरिफाई कर दो। लेकिन
Your question is different. If there are two daughters
आपका क्वेश्चन अलग है। अगर दो बेटियां हैं
There are two ways in which business owners win
उसमें दो तरीके की जो बिजनेस ओनर्स जितो
I talk to him. one says brother
से मैं बात करता हूं। एक बोलते हैं भाई
It is like that. Both are daughters. A daughter
ऐसा है। दोनों बेटियां हैं। एक बेटी
I am interested in business but not one.
बिजनेस में इंटरेस्टेड है एक नहीं है।
But both get equal share of the business
लेकिन शेयर ऑफ द बिनेस दोनों को बराबर
Give. The second one is a musician. Second
दूंगा। दूसरी वाली इज अ म्यूजिशियन। दूसरी
Wali is a teacher. the second one is doing
वाली इज अ टीचर। दूसरी वाली इज डूइंग
Research in America. Equal shares for both
रिसर्च इन अमेरिका। शेयर दोनों को बराबर
will get. Now comes the time to talk. Some?
मिलेगा। अब आ जाती है बात चलाने की। कुछ
People say that I involve my son in law
लोग कहते हैं मैं सन इन लॉ को इनवॉल्व कर
I will take it. I have no problem. Butt enough
लूंगा। आई हैव नो प्रॉब्लम। बट काफी
business family especially of our community
बिजनेस फैमिली खासकर हमारी कम्युनिटी की
She says brother son in law does his work
वो कहती है ना भाई सन इन लॉ अपना काम
Will do it. The daughter will do her own thing. Governance
करेगा। बेटी अपना करेगी। गवर्नेंस
I will install the mechanism. No to these losses
मैकेनिज्म लगा दूंगा। इन लॉस को नहीं
I will let you enter into the business. It is very clear.
घुसने दूंगा बिज़नेस में। बड़ा क्लियर है।
So his view is very clear that if
सो व्यू बड़ा क्लियर है उनका कि अगर
if there are daughters, they will be given shares and they
बेटियां हैं उनको शेयर दिया जाएगा और वो
Run a business, whether one or two
बिजनेस को चलाएं चाहे एक चलाए चाहे दो
Run it and both daughters will get equal share.
चलाएं और दोनों बेटियों को बराबर मिलेगा।
Our ethical and legal angle is that
हम तो एथिकल और लीगल एंगल ये है कि
There should be an exact correct division. whether
एग्जैक्ट करेक्ट बंटवारा होना चाहिए। चाहे
boy girl if there are two boys and one girl
लड़के लड़की अगर दो लड़के हैं और एक लड़की
So 1/3 is 1/3 . we are one boy one girl
है तो 1/3 1/3 है। हम एक लड़का एक लड़की
If it is then it is 50-50. and if you don't do that
है तो 50-50 है। और अगर नहीं करना ऐसा
Look, I am saying that the law says something.
देखिए मैं ये कह रहा हूं लॉ कुछ कहता है
But some norms remain in our culture
लेकिन कुछ नॉर्म बने हुए हैं हमारे कल्चर
In. There is one thing in culture that now a friend lives in a house
में। कल्चर में एक है कि यार अब एक घर में
For example, my father has a whole house
जैसे एग्जांपल है मेरे फादर का एक पूरा घर
Is. There is a whole building. now it's commercial
है। पूरी बिल्डिंग है। अब वो कमर्शियल हो
Went. My parents are living with me now.
गई। अब मां-बाप तो मेरे साथ ही रह रहे हैं
No. So where will the daughter come from? give it to him
ना। तो बेटी कहां से आएगी? उसको तो दे
I gave it. So it will be in my name only.
दिया मैंने। तो मेरे नाम पे ही होगी ना।
I am giving an example of a house. This way
एक मैं एक घर का एग्जांपल दे रहा हूं। ऐसे
He's son is taking care of the business, isn't he?
ही बिजनेस का बेटा संभाल रहा है ना उसकी
So the marriage took place. But I am saying this law
तो शादी हो गई। पर मैं यह कह रहा हूं लॉ
Ever since the change has happened and I am doing every business
जब से चेंज हुआ है और मैं हर एक बिजनेस
Because of family, this course is also different
फैमिली से बिकॉज़ इस कोर्स में भी अदरवाइज
Consulting is the first thing I ask you
कंसल्टिंग मेरे से सबसे पहले मैं पूछता
Yes brother, did you think of this or not? No
हूं भाई ऐसा है विचार बनाया कि नहीं? नहीं
Didn't think about it. Why didn't you think
सोचा नहीं इसके बारे में। क्यों नहीं सोचा
Brother? Think, Discuss, Document and
भाई? सोचो, डिस्कस करो, डॉक्यूमेंट करो और
Tell me this is the plan. not to daughter
कन्व करो कि यह प्लान है। बेटी को नहीं
I will give it or I will not give 50%. I will give you 25%
दूंगा या 50% नहीं दूंगा। 25% दे दूंगा
Because the son is driving. it has to be
क्योंकि बेटा चला रहा है। इट हैस टू बी
Fair and Equitable.
फेयर एंड इक्विटेबल।
Look, there is a word called equal and equitable.
देखिए एक वर्ड है इक्वल और इक्विटेबल।
There is no talk of equal. it has to
इक्वल की बात नहीं हो रही है। इट हैज़ टू
B. Equitable. Means it has to be fair. It
बी इक्विटेबल। मींस इट हैज़ टू बी फेयर। इट
has to be based on some formula and some
हैज़ टू बी बेस्ड ऑन सम फार्मूला और सम
Method. It can't be arbitrary. It is very
मेथड। इट कांट बी आर्बिट्रेरी। यह बहुत
Clarity is necessary in the case of girls
जरूरी है लड़कियों के मामले में क्लेरिटी
Should be. If children, if by chance your
होनी चाहिए। अगर बच्चों अगर बाय चांस आपके
It is like this in the mind, in the subconscious mind that
मन में ऐसा है सबकॉन्शियस माइंड में कि
If you do not give 50% to your daughter then it should be clear
बेटी को 50% नहीं देना तो ये क्लियर होना
Why should I not give it? I wonder that such
चाहिए क्यों नहीं देना। आई वंडर कि ऐसी
What are the girls thinking? I'm Dead
लड़कियां क्या सोच रही है? आई एम डेड
sure that according to them it's a no
श्योर दैट अकॉर्डिंग टू देम इट्स अ नो
brainer that i am 50%
ब्रेनर कि मेरे हैं 50%
It's a no-brainer. Today's generation JX
इट्स अ नो ब्रेनर। आज की जनरेशन जेएक्स की
You talk to Jane and they know the law and
आप बात करो जेन व दे नो द लॉ एंड
you know i have you know i like in my house
यू नो लाइक इन माय हाउस यू नो आई हैव
Daughters We Can't Even Talk About Equality
डॉटर्स वी कांट इवन टॉक अबाउट इक्वलिटी
meaning you are saying why are you saying that
मतलब दे आर सेइंग वो बात क्यों कर रहे हो
means is there something in your mind that it is not equal
मतलब कुछ मन में है क्या कि इक्वल नहीं है
do you get the drift why is this question even
डू यू गेट द ड्रिफ्ट ये क्वेश्चन ही क्यों
that is equal of course it is equal so I am
है कि बराबर है ऑफकोर्स बराबर है सो आई एम
sure so this is a very nice thing ranveer ki
श्योर सो दिस इज़ अ वेरीेंट थिंग रणवीर कि
Parents are probably thinking, oh no brainer
पेरेंट्स शायद सोच रहे हैं अरे नो ब्रेनर
It belongs to the son and what is the daughter thinking
बेटे का है और बेटी क्या सोच रही है नो
Brainer is 50% mine how big is the rift
ब्रेनर है 50% मेरा है कितना बड़ा रिफ्ट
and you are sowing the seeds of what chaos will happen
है और आप बीज बो रहे हो किसके बवाल होने
This happens in every business family
के जो हर बिजनेस फैमिली में होता है सो
Sorting this out and fixing it is a lot of work
इसको सॉर्ट आउट करना फिक्स करना बहुत
It is important what happens in America and Europe
जरूरी है अमेरिका यूरोप में क्या होता है
it's exactly like this is no difference is
इट्स एक्सक्टली लाइक दिस इज़ नो डिफरेंस इज़
no difference the inheritance is same for the
नो डिफरेंस द इनेरिटेंस इज सेम फॉर द
children but it's driven by a will its
चिल्ड्रन बट इट्स ड्रिवन बाय अ विल इट्स
Driven by If There Is No Will So For
ड्रिवन बाय इफ देयर इज़ नो विल सो फॉर
Example: I can choose to know if you give me an ex
एग्जांपल आई आई कैन चूज टू यू नो गिव एक्स
and that percentage but this discrimination
और व परसेंटेज बट दिस डिस्क्रिमिनेशन
Against the female children is far more
अगेंस्ट द फीमेल चिल्ड्रन इज फार मोर
rampant in india as compared to the
रैंपेंट इन इंडिया एस कंपेयर टू द
western countries hum
वेस्टर्न कंट्रीज हम
This will change, the next business will definitely change
बदलेगा ये बिल्कुल बदलेगा नेक्स्ट बिनेस
Look at the owner I'm talking to now
ओनर से जिनसे मैं बात करता हूं देखो अब
What is happening Ranveer, this is also a reality check
क्या हो रहा है रणवीर ये भी एक रियलिटी आई
Sad Reality But Lots of Separations from Kant
कांट से सैड रियलिटी बट लॉट ऑफ सेपरेशंस
Divorces are happening a lot
आर हैपनिंग डिवोर्सेस बहुत हो रहे
So what does the business owner think that my friend
तो बिजनेस ओनर क्या सोचता है कि यार मेरी
It may not happen in lifetime
लाइफ टाइम में हो सकता है नहीं हुआ
Because divorces are still happening even after 20 years
डिवोर्स क्योंकि 20 साल बाद भी हो रहे हैं
It's still happening even after 15 years. one is this and the other
15 साल बाद भी हो रहे हैं। एक तो ये दूसरा
They say this is my daughter in many cases
वो ये कहते हैं मेरी बेटी इन मेनी केसेस
They are not working financially for every father
दे आर नॉट वर्किंग फाइनशियली हर एक बाप की
There is a wish. I also wish that
एक इच्छा होती है। मेरी भी ये इच्छा है कि
friend, my daughters are financially
यार मेरी डॉटर्स जो है ना फाइनशियली
Be independent. If in a family he
इंडिपेंडेंट हो। अगर किसी फैमिली में वह
she is staying not because her
रह रही हैं इसलिए नहीं रह रही कि उनका
She is earning her livelihood by choice. of love
रोजीरोटी वो चॉइस से रह रही हैं। प्यार के
I am living for it. living for family
लिए रह रही हैं। फैमिली के लिए रह रही
Are. so that's why to answer your question
हैं। सो इसीलिए टू आंसर योर क्वेश्चन
Increasingly I am seeing the fathers also
इंक्रीजिंगली आई एम सीइंग द फादर्स आल्सो
I am not thinking, friend. Like it was zero before
थिंकिंग नहीं यार। जैसे पहले तो जीरो था
If you don't get married then 100% I will take care of my son
ना शादी कर दी तो सब बेटे का 100% आई विल
Not Say the Mindset Has Become 50-50 But In
नॉट से द माइंडसेट हैज़ बिकम 50-50 बट इन
there mind it is that the son has a little
देयर माइंड इट इज कि बेटे को थोड़ा सा
I should get more or I am driving but
ज्यादा मिलना चाहिए कि चला रहा है लेकिन
There should be something bigger in the daughter's name
बेटी के नाम पे होना चाहिए कुछ और ये बड़ा
There is at least one positive change in India
पॉजिटिव चेंज है इंडिया में एटलीस्ट द
the needle has moved okay next question especially if
नीडल हैज़ मूव्ड ओके अगला सवाल स्पेशली अगर
If we talk about us, there are many such businesses
हमक की बात करें तो बहुत सारे ऐसे बिज़नेस
There are families who have been doing this for five to six generations
फैमिलीज़ हैं जो पांच छह जनरेशन से अपने
We are growing our businesses. Absolutely. Wool
बिनेसेस को ग्रो कर रहे हैं। बिलकुल। उन
What is common among all families? So
सारी फैमिलीज़ में कॉमनैलिटी क्या है? तो
Look what people have done in it.
देखो क्या है उसमें क्या किया लोगों ने।
Either stay together or separate. don't interrupt
या तो साथ रहो या अलग हो जाओ। बीच में मत
Hang on. So, let me give you an example.
लटके रहो। सो मैं एग्जांपल देता हूं।
The brothers are getting along well. It's love.
भाइयों की जम रही है। प्यार है।
You will sacrifice your life and stay with me. having a fight
सैक्रिफाइस कर दोगे साथ रहो। झगड़ा हो रहा
Is. Father will say, son, go away. means every
है। फादर कहेगा बेटा अलग हो जाओ। मतलब हर
It is different with every generation.
जनरेशन के साथ ये हर जनरेशन के साथ अलग।
so if you see the same brand name of mine
सो इफ यू सी सेम ब्रांड नेम के मेरे
This brand is also owned by grandfather's brother's sons
दादाजी के भाई के बेटों का भी यह ब्रांड
Is. My grandfather's faction also belonged to that
है। मेरे दादाजी के उस वाले फैक्शन का भी
This is the brand. so they may not have changed the
यह ब्रांड है। सो दे मे नॉट हैव चेंज द
Brand name. but they have divided the business
ब्रांड नेम। बट दे हैव डिवाइडेड द बिनेस
Over such a period of time. We think he is
ओवर सच अ पीरियड ऑफ़ टाइम। हमको लगता है वो
There is a family. but there are various factions
एक फैमिली है। बट देयर आर वेरियस फैक्शंस
of the family because they understood they had the
ऑफ़ द फैमिली बिकॉज़ दे अंडरस्टुड दे हैड द
If you stay with the vision, utensils will ring. So
विज़न कि साथ रहोगे तो बर्तन बजेंगे। तो
Brother, separate them out. no fight
भैया इनको सेपरेट आउट कर दो। कोई लड़ाई
No it is not so. Option One Option Two in Rare
नहीं हो। ऑप्शन वन ऑप्शन टू इन रेयर
Cases. so suppose there are four facets of the
केसेस। सो सपोज देयर आर फोर फैश ऑफ द
Family. So maybe there won't be four parts.
फैमिली। तो हो सकता है चार पार्ट नहीं हो।
Two people who are in love are together and
दो इकट्ठे जिनमें प्यार है वो साथ हैं और
The two factions are different. so the trick is this
दो फैक्शन अलग हैं। सो इसका ट्रिक यह है
visualize that you can live together
विजुअलाइज करना कि साथ रह सकते हो कि
No? I can't stay. Divide it. Separate
नहीं? नहीं रह सकते। डिवाइड कर दो। सेपरेट
Get it done. Otherwise, drive with love.
हो जाओ। नहीं तो प्यार के साथ चलाओ।
what is a problem? will stay with me with love
दिक्कत क्या है? प्यार से रहेंगे मेरे
Children. This is your thinking and you are thirsty for blood
बच्चे। यह आपकी सोच है और खून के प्यासे
It has happened. that is the problem but lots of
हुए हुए हैं। दैट इज द प्रॉब्लम बट लॉट ऑफ
The Kolkata Businessman You Know
द कोलकाता बिज़नेसमैन आर फ्रॉम यू नो
marwar the shekhawati region and gents you know who
मारवाड़ द शेखावट रीजन और जेंट्स यू नो हु
Gone from there, they have this intelligence
गॉन फ्रॉम देयर उनमें है ये वाली बुद्धि
that's not my friend it's foresight that's where they are
कि यार नहीं फोरसाइट है दैट्स वेयर दे आर
Survived Across Generations Futuristic
सर्वाइव्ड अक्रॉस जनरेशंस फ्यूचरिस्टिक
Futuristic is the potential problem
फ्यूचरिस्टिक है पोटेंशियल प्रॉब्लम को
see, understand, do not deny, look
देख लेना समझ लेना डिनाई नहीं करना देखो
What happens is that a man lies the most
क्या होता है ना कि झूठ आदमी सबसे ज्यादा
He tells himself lies
अपने आप से बोलता है वो अपने आप से झूठ
I don't say anything, they know it won't work brother
नहीं बोलता उनको पता है भाई नहीं जमेगी
We have to run our brothers' business separately
भाइयों की बिनेस को तो चलाना है ना तो अलग
do it friend hum hum
करो यार हम हम
Now, I also want to say something
वैसे तो मैं भी कुछ कहना चाहता हूं अब
But I have a question for you regarding the next question.
नेक्स्ट सवाल के बारे में बट आपसे एक सवाल
I will ask you so many business families
पूछूंगा आपने इतने सारे बिजनेस फैमिलीज को
If you have studied then you belong to Marwari business family and
स्टडी करा है तो मारवाड़ी बिनेस फैमिली और
What is the difference in a Gujarati business family?
गुजराती बिनेस फैमिली में फर्क क्या होता
yes ok people look alike from a distance
है ओके लोगों को दूर से लगता है एक जैसे
Are from. This is commonality in accounting
से हैं। कॉमनैलिटी ये है हिसाब किताब में
He is topper in Mathematics. We
मैथमेटिक्स में अव्वल दर्जे के हैं। हम
Are financially prudent. Lifestyle
फाइनशियली प्रूडेंट हैं। लाइफस्टाइल
It is exactly like beans. Looks like a bean.
बिल्कुल सेम जैसी है। देखने में सेम है।
But there are big differences. so i will say
लेकिन बड़े डिफरेंसेस हैं। सो आई विल से
That Marwari businessmen are more methodical.
दैट मारवाड़ी बिजनेसमैन आर मोर मेथोडिकल।
As is the system. That was taken out by Birlaz
जैसे पड़ता सिस्टम है। वो बिरलाज़ ने निकाला
Is. It means brother when he goes home in the evening
है। पड़ता मतलब भैया शाम को घर जाते वक्त
Tell me what came in. Auntie is in
बता देना क्या अंदर आया। आंटी में है
My. Ok? so they are much more methodical,
मेरी। ठीक है? सो दे आर मच मोर मेथोडिकल,
Much more systematic. Gujaratis on the other
मच मोर सिस्टमैटिक। गुजरातीज ऑन द अदर
Hands are I think more liberal more acceptable.
हैंड आर आई थिंक मोर लिबरल मोर अप्टेबल।
The second difference is Marwaris are very very
सेकंड डिफरेंस इज मारवाड़ीज आर वेरी वेरी
Traditional, Very Hierarchical Gujarati Eye
ट्रेडिशनल, वेरी हायरार्कियल गुजरातीज़ आई
Find a slightly more liberal one and I think
फाइंड अ स्लाइटली मोर लिबरल एंड आई थिंक
this is my guess because when i see almost
दिस इज़ माय गेस बिकॉज़ व्हेन आई सी ऑलमोस्ट
every gujarati family has somebody in
एव्री गुजराती फैमिली हैज़ समबडी इन
Atlanta and That Region of America. so there
अटलांटा और दैट रीजन ऑफ़ अमेरिका। सो देयर
is there a lot of westernization
इज़ लॉट ऑफ़ वेस्टर्नाइजेशन
Were s Marwari people it is not like that
वेयर एस मारवाड़ी लोगों के ऐसा नहीं है कि
The kids are not out but they have a lot of business
बच्चे बाहर नहीं है बट उनका काफी बिजनेस
It is limited to India only. so this is these are
इंडिया में ही सीमित है। सो दिस इज़ दीज़ आर
sum of the differences gujarati i find more
सम ऑफ़ द डिफरेंसेस गुजरातीज़ आई फाइंड मोर
Liberals Have a More Broad Minded Risk Appetite
लिबरल मोर ब्रॉड माइंडेड रिस्क एपिटाइट
It is in both. and methodical I think
दोनों में है। एंड मेथोडिकल मेरे को लगता
Yes, there are a few more Marwari people. Hmm
है मारवाड़ी लोग थोड़े ज्यादा है। हम्म
Hmm. A is a super power which I have learnt in Gujarat
हम्म। अ एक सुपर पावर है जो मैंने गुजराती
Notice has been made in business families and
बिनेस फैमिलीज में नोटिस करा है और
Notice in honestly every Gujarati household
ऑनेस्टली हर गुजराती हाउसहोल्ड में नोटिस
I have done it. My mother is also Gujarati. I slept
करा है। मेरी मम्मी भी गुजराती है। सो आई
Seen it up close. Ok. the super power is
सीन इट अप क्लोज। ओके। सुपर पावर ये है कि
Gujarati women are fantastic at running
गुजराती वुमेन आर फैंटास्टिक एट रनिंग
Families are as well as running businesses. and this
फैमिलीज़ एज वेल एज रनिंग बिज़नेसेस। एंड यह
I have always noticed that even if there are
मैंने हमेशा नोटिस करा है कि इवन इफ दे आर
Not actively taking part in the business.
नॉट एक्टिवली टेकिंग पार्ट इन द बिज़नेस।
They guide their husbands in detail
वो अपने हस्बैंड्स को डिटेल में गाइड करते
Are. If the marriage is lasting. that's the
हैं। इफ द मैरिज आर लास्टिंग। दैट्स दी
Another angle. but i think at least in my eyes
अदर एंगल। बट आई थिंक एटलीस्ट इन माय आईज
When it comes to Gujarati business families
व्हेन इट कम्स टू गुजराती बिनेस फैमिलीज
The female head who is the matriarch of the family
जो फैमिली की मैट्रियाार्क है फीमेल हेड
they always have a role to play a little bit in
दे ऑलवेज हैव अ रोल टू प्ले लिटल बिट इन
I have noticed this business. I don't know
बिज़नेस ये मैंने नोटिस करा है। आई डोंट नो
about this is amazing thing and there for
अबाउट दिस इज़ अमेजिंग थिंग एंड देयर फॉर
my hypothesis this is just from
माई हाइपोथेसिस दिस इज़ जस्ट फ्रॉम
Observations that Gujaratis I find more
ऑब्जरवेशन दैट गुजरातीज़ आई फाइंड मोर
liberal more broad minded may be it is
लिबरल मोर ब्रॉड माइंडेड मे बी इट इज
coming from there that women have a role to
कमिंग फ्रॉम देयर कि वीमेन हैव अ रोल टू
Play and I personally think it's a good thing
प्ले एंड आई पर्सनली थिंक इट्स अ गुड थिंग
because you see this they say lonely at the
बिकॉज़ आप ये देखो बोलते हैं ना लोनली एट द
Top
टॉप
To whom can a business owner go to narrate his complaint?
एक बिजनेस ओनर अपना रोना किसके पास जाकर
Cried? Whom should I tell my pain to? To the Employee
रोए? अपना दर्द किसको बताएं? एम्प्लई को
He will manipulate it. so if your life
वो तो मैनपुलेट कर देगा। सो इफ योर लाइफ
partner is someone with whom you can share your
पार्टनर इज समवन विथ हुूम यू कैन शेयर योर
Pen and She Can Add Value in Giving Your
पेन एंड शी कैन वैल्यू ऐड इन गिविंग योर
Perspective like you talked about your mother.
पर्सेक्टिव लाइक यू टॉक्ड अबाउट योर मदर।
and i think may be this is one of the
एंड आई थिंक मे बी दिस इज़ वन ऑफ़ द
Secrets of Being a Gujarati Business Woman
सीक्रेट्स ऑफ़ गुजराती बिज़नेस वुमेन बीइंग
So successful. Hmm.
सो सक्सेसफुल। हम्म।
A honestly sir right now my business career is
अ ऑनेस्टली सर अभी मेरे बिजनेस करियर के
Almost 10 years have passed. a if i
ऑलमोस्ट 10 साल खत्म हो चुके हैं। अ इफ आई
want to get romantically involved with
वांट टू गेट रोमांटिकली इन्वॉल्व विद
Anyway this is one of my conditions. i should
एनीवन ये मेरी एक कंडीशन होती है। आई शुड
Be able to talk work with the person. Very
बी एबल टू टॉक वर्क विथ द पर्सन। बहुत
This is necessary. ok amazing. Either and I
जरूरी है ये। ओके अमेजिंग। या तो एंड आई
genuinely feel that
जेनुइनली फील कि
Women around the world have a very strong strategy
दुनिया भर की औरतें स्ट्रेटजी बहुत तगड़ी
Makes it. The Great Strategies. I slept
बनाती है। दे ग्रेट स्ट्रेटजीस। सो आई
Also agree with that. So So The Culture Which
आल्सो एग्री विथ दैट। सो सो द कल्चर व्हिच
I Come From Not From My Family Side But
आई कम फ्रॉम नॉट फ्रॉम माय फैमिली साइड बट
from my the corporation i work for office
फ्रॉम माय द कॉरपोरेशन आई वर्क फॉर ऑफिस
That nothing will happen at home. Ok? But
की कोई बात घर पे नहीं होगी। ठीक है? बट
Recently when this covid came work from home
रिसेंटली जब ये कोविड आया वर्क फ्रॉम होम
So obviously I told you a few things
हुआ सो ऑब्वियसली थोड़ी बहुत बातें सुनाई
She gives it to me. You know but I agree with you.
दे देती हैं। यू नो बट आई एग्री विद यू।
I think there is a sense of people
आई थिंक देयर सेंस ऑफ़ पीपल
It is very sharp. and sometimes there is no
इज वेरी शार्प। एंड समटाइम देयर इज़ नो
Logic it's just pure intuition. If
लॉजिक इट जस्ट प्योर इंट्यूशन। अगर
He said that the guy is not well
उन्होंने बोल दिया बंदा ठीक नहीं है ना तो
You will get to know about it somewhere after 5-7 years.
वो कहीं ना कहीं आपको 5 सात साल बाद पता
Let's go or after 20 years that he was not right. So
चले या 20 साल बाद कि वो ठीक नहीं था। सो
I agree with the one is intuition and I
आई एग्री विद दी वन इज इंट्यूशन एंड आई
also think the way they look at things and the
आल्सो थिंक द वे दे लुक एट थिंग्स एंड द
Those guys look at things that are very, very scary
वे गाइस लुक एट थिंग्स आर वेरी वेरीरी
Different. Our parameters are different. So
डिफरेंट। हमारे पैरामीटर्स ही अलग हैं। सो
I think it's a good strategy that you are
आई थिंक इट्स अ गुड स्ट्रेटजी दैट यू आर
having that both may be you bring them both
हैविंग कि दोनों मे बी यू ब्रिंग दे बोथ
Bring complementary things to the table.
ब्रिंग कम्प्लीमेंट्री थिंग्स टू द टेबल।
And it's wonderful. Hmm.
एंड इट्स वंडरफुल। हम्म।
Do You Think Great Marriages Can Lead To
डू यू थिंक ग्रेट मैरिजेस कैन लीड टू
Great businesses? I think so. but but
ग्रेट बिजनेसेस? आई थिंक सो। पर लेकिन
Ranveer, I always say this in my life
रणवीर मैं हमेशा ये कहता हूं अपने लाइफ
If you want to bring a partner into the business then
पार्टनर को अगर बिजनेस में लाना है ना तो
This is walking on the razor’s edge. Ok. Failure
ये वॉकिंग ऑन द रेजर्स एज है। ओके। फेलियर
The chances are high. We are my own
के चांसेस ज्यादा हैं। हम मेरा ये अपना
There is a view. I have a lot of data. if you say it
व्यू है। डाटा मेरे पास बहुत है। कहोगे तो
I will tell you as well. If there is success then it will be super
मैं बता भी दूंगा। सक्सेस होगी तो सुपर
It will be successful. But it's walking on the razors
सक्सेस होगी। बट इट्स वॉकिंग ऑन द रेजर्स
Edge. Don't ever think that we have so much
एज। ये मत सोचना कभी कि हमारे में इतना
If there is love and understanding then in business
प्यार और अंडरस्टैंडिंग है तो बिजनेस में
It will work. Chances of conflict are high. But
चलेगी। चांसेस ऑफ कॉन्फ्लिक्ट आर हाई। बट
If You Can Crack the Code and Set Some
इफ यू कैन क्रैक द कोड एंड सेट सम
Protocols I think it can be a great
प्रोटोकॉल्स आई थिंक इट कैन बी अ ग्रेट
Combination. we know you let's take
कॉम्बिनेशन। हम यू नो लेट लेट्स टेक
The case of biotech. Is it okay? let's take the
बायोटेक का केस। ठीक है ना? लेट्स टेक द
Piramal Family. you know nandini piramal and
पिरामल फैमिली। यू नो नंदिनी पिरामल एंड
Peter. you know so there are so many cases that
पीटर। यू नो सो बहुत सारे केसेस हैं कि
In which husband wife combination have really
जिसमें हस्बैंड वाइफ कॉम्बिनेशन हैव रियली
Work but it is a bit difficult according to me
वर्क बट थोड़ा मुश्किल है मेरे हिसाब से
I think so flatization flatization is necessary
आई थिंक सो ट्लेटाइजेशन ट्लेटाइजेशन जरूरी
First you must understand what I am saying
है पहले ये समझ लो जो मैं बोल रहा हूं आई
I'm putting a big disclaimer like this
एम पुटिंग अ बड़ा वाला डिस्क्लेमर ऐसा
There is no disclaimer which I haven't read
वाला डिस्क्लेमर नहीं है जो पढ़ा नहीं
This is a little bit bold and high that
जाता ये थोड़ा सा बोल्ड एंड हाई में है कि
should husband and wife work together
शुड हस्बैंड एंड वाइफ वर्क टुगेदर मेरा
This is my view, if there is synergy then let us give it
अपना व्यू यह है अगर सिनर्जी है देस दे
can work but assume that
कैन वर्क बट यह मान कर चलो दैट
Conflict zones will come which can even
कॉन्फ्लिक्ट ज़ों्स आएंगे व्हिच कैन इवन
Destroy your personal relationship. so if you
डिस्ट्रॉय योर पर्सनल रिलेशनशिप। सो इफ यू
Call it out at the beginning and tell me friend
कॉल इट आउट शुरू में ही और बता दो यार
will come and for that you have already become proactive
आएंगे और उसके लिए आप पहले ही प्रोएक्टिव
If you take action then the chances are mitigated.
एक्शन ले लो तो चांसेस आर मिटिगेटेड।
But on which assumption are you working
लेकिन अगर आप कौन सी एजम्पशन पे चल रहे
yes? Like I said earlier, kids
हो? जैसे मैंने पहले बोला बच्चों में तो
Love will remain. our love will be forever.
प्यार रहेगा। हमारा प्यार हमेशा रहेगा।
No. So then it can work. Ok. next question
नहीं। सो देन इट कैन वर्क। ओके। अगला सवाल
It is interesting. Are spoiled kids too
इंटरेस्टिंग है। क्या बिगड़े हुए बच्चे भी
Businesses can grow. of the spoilt
बिज़नेसेस ग्रो कर सकते हैं। बिगड़े हुए की
The definition depends on this. if you
परिभाषा इस पे डिपेंड करता है। अगर आप
You can come to the office, board meeting
ऑफिस में आ जा सकते हो, बोर्ड मीटिंग
You can attend without giving it away then
अटेंड कर सकते हो विदाउट गिविंग इट अवे तो
You can drive it.
चला सकते हो।
or i'm saying that if you're spoiled and
या आई एम सेइंग कि अगर आप बिगड़े हुए हो और
As I looked at that spoilt thing,
वो बिगड़े वाली चीज को जैसे-जैसे मैंने
He said it is an iron wall. Brother whatever i do
बोला आयरन वॉल है। भाई मैं जो भी करूं
In my personal time I drive Tanu's car
मेरे पर्सनल टाइम में तनु की मैं गाड़ी
I drive, I do this, I do that.
चलाता हूं, मैं ये करता हूं, वो करता हूं।
But if I show up in a board meeting and I
बट इफ आई शो अप इन अ बोर्ड मीटिंग एंड आई
Sleep off. and if i'm distracted or
स्लीप ऑफ। और इफ आई एम डिस्ट्रैक्टेड या
Topic A is happening, B is happening. like this also
टॉपिक ए हो रहा है, बी हो रहा है। ऐसे भी
I have seen the cases. than better to stay
केसेस मैंने देखे हैं। देन बेटर टू स्टे
Professionalize the business. does that
ऑफ द बिजनेस प्रोफेशनलाइज कर दो। डस दैट
Answer the question? Or another question. Under
आंसर द क्वेश्चन? या एक और सवाल है। अंडर
What conditions should you stay out of business?
व्हाट कंडीशंस शुड यू स्टे आउट ऑफ बिनेस?
If you are not interested, you feel suffocated
अगर आपका इंटरेस्ट नहीं है, आपका दम घुटता
it is, you don't feel like it and there is something else in you
है, आपका मन नहीं होता और आप में कुछ और
You have the fire to do it, don't get into business at all.
करने की आग है, बिजनेस में बिल्कुल मत आओ।
Professionalize it. System, process
प्रोफेशनललाइज कर दो। सिस्टम, प्रोसेस
There are plenty of good templates available. and enough
अच्छे खासे टेंपलेट्स अवेलेबल हैं। और इनफ
and more examples are that only blood
एंड मोर एग्जांपल्स हैं कि सिर्फ खून ही
I can't drive it. Someone else can also drive it.
नहीं चला सकता। दूसरा भी चला सकता है।
Don't come at all. You will live a life of suffocation and mortification.
बिल्कुल मत आओ। घुट-घुट के मरमर के जिओगे।
You are ruining your business as well.
अपना भी बर्बाद कर रहे हो बिजनेस को भी।
You are not doing any favor to anybody.
यू आर नॉट डूइंग एनी फेवर टू एनीबॉडी।
Ok. So that more Indians know the truth about India.
ओके। ताकि और भारतीय भारत का सच जाने।
So I would ask you this question: What is the problem in Delhi?
इसलिए मैं आपसे यह पूछूंगा कि दिल्ली के
What is the difference between the rich and the rich of Mumbai
अमीरों और मुंबई के अमीरों में फर्क क्या
It happens?
होता है?
This is a touchy question. So the rich in Delhi are not that rich
टची सवाल है। तो दिल्ली के अमीर अमीर थोड़े
Will be loud. There will be some carts, some
लाउड होंगे। वड्डी गड़ियां होंगी, थोड़े
There will be some show off, show off to the girls,
शोशेबाजी होगी, थोड़ा लड़कियों को दिखाना,
To impress, Bombay's Rise is a little sale
इंप्रेस करना, बॉम्बे के राइज़ थोड़े सेल
Will be. They will also have a long car. but the
होंगे। दे विल आल्सो हैव लॉन्ग कार। बट द
Music will not be blaring with the you know
म्यूजिक विल नॉट बी ब्लेयरिंग विथ द यू नो
Mirrors down. If they go to a high end
मिरर्स डाउन। इफ दे गो टू अ हाई एंड
Restaurants, they won't be bosses.
रेस्टोरेंट, दे वों वोंट बी बोस्ट्रेस।
and i have seen in mumbai you no like there
एंड आई हैव सीन इन मुंबई यू नो लाइक देयर
are some places you would also know where
आर सम प्लेसेस यू वुड आल्सो नो जहां पे
Leave the table, you don't get a seat during the weekend
टेबल छोड़ो सीट नहीं मिलती वीकेंड में एंड
they look this section is reserved for me that's
दे लुक दिस सेक्शन इज़ रिर्व फॉर मी दैट्स
They have to show off but they will not make a ruckus
दे वे टू शो ऑफ बट दे विल नॉट मेक अ हल्ला
Gulla so the rich of Delhi will exploit and
गुल्ला सो दिल्ली के अमीर शोषा करेंगे और
Let's see brother, did I see this or not
देखेंगे भाई देखा कि नहीं मैंने इतना
I shouted that I came in such a big car
हल्ला किया मैंने इतनी बड़ी गाड़ी में आया
Bombay wala is self contained in himself you
बॉम्बे वाला अपने में सेल्फ कंटेंड है यू
no theek hai and he will not be so loud and
नो ठीक है एंड ही विल नॉट बी सो लाउड एंड
he is not you know peeping that someone saw
ही इज़ नॉट यू नो पीपिंग कि किसी ने देखी
Or no, it's my car, so that's the difference.
कि नहीं मेरी गाड़ी सो ये डिफरेंस है।
It's a big cultural difference between Delhi
इट्स अ बिग कल्चरल डिफरेंस बिटवीन दिल्ली
And Mumbai. But no business oriented
एंड मुंबई। पर कोई बिनेस ओरिएंटेड
Are there differences? There is a lot of difference. Very
डिफरेंसेस है? बहुत डिफरेंस है। बहुत
There is a difference. I think Bombay is
डिफरेंस है। मैं ये सोचता हूं कि बॉम्बे
There is more truth in it. I am sorry. Delhi
में सच ज्यादा है। आई एम सॉरी। दिल्ली
Height Working in Delhi. Truth in Bombay
हाइट वर्किंग इन दिल्ली। बॉम्बे में सच
Is too much. Bombay has a simple and straightforward language.
ज्यादा है। बॉम्बे में सीधी सपाट भाषा है।
Seth, this won't be possible. A little in Delhi
सेठ ये नहीं हो पाएगा। दिल्ली में थोड़ा
Over promise and under delivery. Bombay
सा ओवर प्रॉमिस अंडर डिलीवर है। बॉम्बे
I Will Not Say Under Promise and Over
में आई विल नॉट से अंडर प्रॉमिस एंड ओवर
It is delivered. What is delivered is what is promised
डिलीवर है। जो डिलीवर है वही प्रॉमिस जो
It appears to be the same. so i think its ethical
दिखता है वही है। सो आई थिंक एथिकल इट्स
much easier to do business in bombay because
मच इज़ियर टू डू बिनेस इन बॉम्बे बिकॉज़
What you see is what you get. so i think
व्हाट यू सी इज़ व्हाट यू गेट। सो आई थिंक
It's a very big difference. Sir another India
इट्स वेरी बिग डिफरेंस। सर एक और भारत
This is a centric question. And I did not start this discussion
सेंट्रिक सवाल है। और ये डिस्कशन ना मैंने
Heard it in Mumbai. Often. a discussion this
मुंबई में सुनी है। अक्सर। अ डिस्कशन यह
that's it man it feels like tie to cities
है कि यार ऐसा लगता है कि टिए टू सिटीज
There is high money potential in it. and very
में मनी पोटेंशियल ज्यादा है। और बहुत
Everybody says there is a lot of money
सारे लोग कहते हैं कि बहुत सारा पैसा भरा
It is in tier two because spending
पड़ा है टिएर टू में क्योंकि स्पेंडिंग
Tie to Tie Three becomes slightly less. is
हल्के से कम होती है टिए टू टिए थ्री। इज
is this true? that earning potential has higher
दिस ट्रू? कि अर्निंग पोटेंशियल हैज़ हायर
In the Interiors of India. So look at this
इन द इंटीरियर्स ऑफ़ इंडिया। सो देखो इसका
Do you know what the answer is? that of the man who
आंसर पता है क्या है? कि आदमी का जो
experience hai na it is based on
एक्सपीरियंस है ना इट इज बेस्ड ऑन
Expectation versus reality. now tier two
एक्सपेक्टेशन वर्सेस रियलिटी। अब टियर टू
you expect so little from there
से आप एक्सपेक्ट इतना कम करते हो वहां
Even a little bit starts making bigger noises
थोड़ा बहुत भी ज्यादा बड़े हल्ले करने लग
Let's go. You get my point? Butt Carts
जाते हैं। यू गेट माय पॉइंट? बट गाड़ियां
Where are they sold the most? tie to or tie
ज्यादा कहां बिकती हैं? टिए टू में या टिए
In the forest? Where do luxury cars sell the most?
वन में? लग्जरी कार्स ज्यादा कहां बिकती
Are? If 200 units are sold in Delhi, a
हैं? अगर दिल्ली में 200 यूनिट बिकेंगे एक
of car and if 20 are sold in Indore then
कार के और अगर इंदौर में 20 बिकेंगे तो
We'll see 20 more of those. Because I
हमें वो 20 ज्यादा दिखेंगे। क्योंकि मैं
I am expecting 10 from there. so that
एक्सपेक्ट वहां से 10 कर रहा हूं। सो दैट
is one thing tier one still has more money but
इज वन थिंग टियर वन स्टिल हैज़ मोर मनी बट
Yes the wealth is percolating down. so five
यस द वेल्थ इज परकुलेटिंग डाउन। सो फाइव
Years 10 Years Back If You See The One You Know
इयर्स 10 इयर्स बैक इफ यू सी द यू नो
Luxury Car Network and Dealership Consumers
लग्जरी कार नेटवर्क और डीलरशिप कंज्यूमर
Durable Network and Luxury Brands
ड्यूरेबल नेटवर्क और लग्जरी ब्रांड्स
Network It Wasn't There So Much. so fancy
नेटवर्क इट वाज़ंट देयर सो मच। इतने फैंसी
Showrooms were not in Tier 2 and Tier 3. Today
शोरूम्स टिए टू टिए थ्री में नहीं थे। आज
They are becoming viable. but to se ki tie to me
वायबल हो रहे हैं। बट टू से कि टिए टू में
More potential of growth naturally
ज्यादा पोटेंशियल ऑफ ग्रोथ नेचुरली ज्यादा
because the denominator is less. If we are a
है क्योंकि डिनोमिनेटर कम है। हम अगर एक
The lower the denominator of the thing the lower the saturation
चीज का डिनोमिनेटर कम होगा सैचुरेशन कम
If it happens then the potential is high. But Age Of
होगी तो पोटेंशियल ज्यादा है। बट एज ऑफ
today tie one is definitely larger and a
टुडे टिए वन डेफिनेटली इज़ लार्जर एंड अ
Bigger market than tier two and tier three. Ok
बिग मार्केट देन टियर टू टियर थ्री। ओके
Sir. One last question from Electricity MBA. Question
सर। बिजली एमबीए का एक आखिरी सवाल। सवाल
that a lot of judges get multi million
यह है कि बहुत सारे जेजीस को मल्टी मिलियन
Dollar careers needed. Butt a little
डॉलर करियर्स चाहिए। बट एक छोटी सी
A reality check is also needed. a please shed
रियलिटी चेक की जरूरत भी है। अ प्लीज शेड
Light on the time required and please tell
लाइट ऑन द टाइम रिक्वायर्ड एंड प्लीज टेल
What things need to be sacrificed
अस कि किन चीजों का बलिदान देना पड़ता है
In the pursuit of making multi-millions
इन द पर्स्यूट ऑफ़ मेकिंग मल्टी मिलियन
Dollar Businesses. so only one is mine
डॉलर बिज़नेसेस। सो सिर्फ एक ही मेरी
This is the advice to JG because I also say in some
एडवाइस है जेजी को बिकॉज़ आई आल्सो स इन सम
of the startup contests that they
ऑफ द स्टार्टअप का्टेस्ट्स कि उनको ऐसा
It seems that this is how things happen because
लगता है कि ऐसे ही हो जाती है चीजें बिकॉज़
The media is probably not trying to tell you
मीडिया इज प्रोबब्ली यू नो ट्राइंग टू टेल
them this so one i want to tell them hard work
देम दिस सो वन आई वांट टू टेल देम मेहनत
number one has to be done, number two will be a failure
करनी पड़ती है नंबर वन नंबर टू फेलियर होगा
number three will have to be pivoted many times
बहुत बार होगा नंबर थ्री पिवेट करना पड़ेगा
Your so called world changing idea
आपका जो सो कॉल्ड वर्ल्ड चेंजिंग आईडिया
it may be that it changes four times and some
है हो सकता है वो चार बार चेंज हो और कुछ
And it becomes number four, whatever you say
और ही बन जाए नंबर फोर फोर जो भी आपको बोल
I am saying that there is quick money, become a billionaire quickly
रहा है कि क्विक मनी है जल्दी बिलेनियर बन
You will go, he is misleading you. there can
जाओगे वो आपको गुमराह कर रहा है। देयर कैन
B C An exception cannot be the rule
बी सी एन एक्सेप्शन कैन नॉट बी द रूल
One gets a salary of Rs 1 crore in IIT.
आईआईटी में 1 करोड़ की सैलरी मिलती है।
again
अगेन
Statistics are fooling us. so i want
स्टैटिस्टिक्स आर फुलिंग अस। सो आई वांट
To tell them you will have to be patient, even if you lose
टू टेल देम पेशेंस रखनी पड़ेगी, हार भी
It will happen, blood will come out, injury will happen, hurt
होगी, खून भी निकलेगा, चोट भी लगेगी, हर्ट
There will be challenges, your self concept will also be challenged.
भी होगे, सेल्फ कांसेप्ट भी चैलेंज होगा।
That's part of the journey. us and that's
दैट इज द पार्ट ऑफ द जर्नी। हम एंड दैट्स
what i see you know whatever genji i
व्हाट आई सी यू नो व्हाटएवर जेंजी आई
interact with three or four failures
इंटरेक्ट विद तीन या चार फेलियर होते हैं
Neither do they become big and they tell anyone
ना तो बड़ा लो हो जाते हैं और वो किसी को
I am unable to even express my pain. you know i can
बता भी नहीं पाते अपना दर्द। यू नो आई कैन
See that they are feeling lost inside. give and take
सी कि दे आर फीलिंग लॉस्ट इनसाइड। दे आर
Not feeling confident. wherever i went
नॉट फीलिंग कॉन्फिडेंट। वेयरवर आई गूव्ड
Up. He became a multi-millionaire. How many buns
अप। वो तो मल्टी मिलिनियर बन गए। कितने बन
Are you gone brother? We should have patience. no hurry up work
गए भाई? हम पेशेंस रखो। जल्दी का काम कोई
Not there. And remove the fear from your mind and heart
नहीं है। और अपने दिमाग दिल से फियर ऑफ़
Remove the judgement. be absolutely shameless
जजमेंट हटाओ। अबब्सोलुटली बेशर्म बनो थोड़े
what's the hurry what's the hurry
से और जल्दी क्या है जल्दी काहे की है
Dear, we must become 30 multi
प्यारे हम बन जाना 30 जरूरी है मल्टी
You have to make a million in 30 years, you can make it in 40 years
मिलियन 30 में ही बनना है 40 में बन जाना
Hum you know I mean there is so much pressure
हम यू नो आई मीन ये जो इतना प्रेशर
Unnecessary has been created and Ranveer
अननेसेसरी क्रिएट किया हुआ है एंड रणवीर
I think through your this forum I want to say
आई थिंक थ्रू योर दिस फोरम आई वांट टू से
That I used to think that in our generation
दैट मैं ये सोचता था कि हमारी जनरेशन में
There is a big competition but I think Judge's
बड़ा कंपटीशन है बट आई थिंक जजी का जो
There is pressure and it's not merely because of
प्रेशर है एंड इट्स नॉट मेयरली बिकॉज़ ऑफ़
Instagram pictures you know that's one piece but
Instagram पिक्चर्स यू नो दैट्स वन पीस बट
it's also about and it's not about
इट्स इट्स आल्सो अबाउट एंड इट्स नॉट अबाउट
jealousy it's about what did i do wrong
जेलसी इट्स अबाउट मैंने क्या गलती कर दी
that other person did right so I want to tell
दैट अदर पर्सन डिड राइट सो आई वांट टू टेल
Let them do what you said, don't be judgemental
देम ये जो आपने बोला है कि जजमेंटल मत हो
Everyone's journey is different, everyone's path is different
हर एक की जर्नी अलग है हर एक का रास्ता
It is different, apply all the factors friend, only then
अलग है सारे फैक्टर्स को लगाओ ना यार तभी
Like to like apple to apple only then compare
लाइक टू लाइक एप्पल टू एप्पल तभी कंपेयर
hoga na may be you are not building in all the
होगा ना मे बी यू आर नॉट बिल्डिंग इन ऑल द
Factors and Just Destroying Yourself
फैक्टर्स एंड जस्ट डिस्ट्रइंग योर सेल्फ
self concept self respect self
सेल्फ कॉन्सेप्ट सेल्फ रिस्पेक्ट सेल्फ
Confidence is not like that, we know this
कॉन्फिडेंस ऐसा नहीं है हम पता है ये आपने
Have you heard about short attention spans?
सुना है ना कि शॉर्ट अटेंशन इंजन स्पैन्स
Everyone is done with the reels of shots
हो गए हैं सबके रील्स की वजह से शॉट्स की
Because of. i think it applies havely on jsg
वजह से। आई थिंक इट अप्लाई हेवली ऑन ज्सजी
Careers also. Ah this is the skill difference
करियर्स आल्सो। अ ये स्किल डिफरेंस है
Foresight in Your Generation Among Millennials
मिलेनियल्स में आपकी जनरेशन में फोरसाइट
It used to be like, okay let me visualize what 20
होती थी कि ओके लेट मी विजुअलाइज व्हाट 20
Years from now will look like what 40
इयर्स फ्रॉम नाउ विल लुक लाइक, व्हाट 40
Years from now will look like this. A
इयर्स विल नाउ फ्रॉम लुक लाइक। अ
That combined with all this fear of judgment. Ahhh
दैट कंबाइंड विद यह सब फियर ऑफ़ जजमेंट। अह
Getting over well by the pressures around you. Or
गेटिंग ओवरवेल बाय द प्रेशर्स अराउंड। या
Some strength is needed. a which is there
थोड़ी मजबूती की जरूरत है। अ व्हिच इज देयर
in a fussiness but it needs to be there
इन अ फ्यू जेंसी बट इट नीड्स टू बी देयर
On a larger scale. Anyways sir now electricity
ऑन अ लार्जर स्केल। एनीवेज सर अब बिजली
MBA finished. a we will start the sukoon
एमबीए खत्म। अ वी विल स्टार्ट द सुकून
Oriented business podcast.
ओरिएंटेड बिज़नेस पडकास्ट।
Details
डिटेल्स
We will move forward with the templates
के साथ टेंपलेट्स के साथ हम आगे बढ़ेंगे
So that people can start their life with a notebook and pen
ताकि लोग नोटबुक और पेन लेकर अपनी लाइफ
Change. Through this episode. Let's begin.
बदलें। थ्रू दिस एपिसोड। लेट्स बिगिन।
perfect. Ok. actually practical
परफेक्ट। ओके। एक्चुअली प्रैक्टिकल
Beginning of chapters. a again this has to be
चैप्टर्स की शुरुआत। अ अगेन दिस हैज़ टू बी
The Most Value Adding Podcast of the Year.
द मोस्ट वैल्यू एडिंग पडकास्ट ऑफ द ईयर।
Sir. So in chapter one we'll talk about
सर। इसलिए चैप्टर वन में हम बात करेंगे
Personalized Personal Finance Strategies
पर्सनलाइज्ड पर्सनल फाइनेंस स्ट्रेटजीज़ के
about. These are two perspectives. First
बारे में। यह दो पर्सपेक्टिव्स हैं। पहला
Perspective for Someone Completely Self
पर्सपेक्टिव फॉर समवन कंप्लीटली सेल्फ
Med. A person whose family doesn't have money,
मेड। अ जिनके फैमिली के पास पैसे नहीं है,
What should be done? Second Perspective Joe
क्या करना चाहिए? सेकंड पर्सपेक्टिव जो
people are inheriting a little bit of their
लोग थोड़ा बहुत इनहेरिट कर रहे हैं अपने
From the family. Explain this also. Look at what exactly
फैमिली से। यह भी समझाइए। देखो जो बिल्कुल
There is no family backing. And I Assume
ही फैमिली बैकिंग नहीं है। एंड मैं अस्यूम
I am talking about your business family
कर रहा हूं आप बिजनेस फैमिली की बात कर
Are you staying with someone or working?
रहे हो या नौकरी वाले की?
in the first case or job of a job holder
इन द फर्स्ट केस या नौकरी वाले की नौकरी
of that one. So what I am saying is that the most
वाले की जी। तो मैं यह कह रहा हूं कि सबसे
Firstly, the job holder has to see to it that
पहले यह जो नौकरी वाले को यह देखना है कि
If even before AI comes in today’s time
अगर आज के टाइम में इवन बिफोर एआई हैड कम
Such a time will surely come when six to eight months or
इन ऐसा समय जरूर आएगा जब छ आठ महीने या
year if both of you are working if you are
साल इफ बोथ ऑफ यू आर वर्किंग इफ यू आर
Married you know one person will not have a job and such
मैरिड यू नो एक की जॉब नहीं होगी और ऐसा
It is also possible that it may not be for two. so start
भी हो सकता है दो की नहीं हो। सो स्टार्ट
Saving for the Rainy Day. thats point number
सेविंग फॉर द रेनी डे। दैट्स पॉइंट नंबर
Forest. Point number two is that we have a
वन। पॉइंट नंबर टू ये है कि हमारे यहां एक
It has become a tradition. There must be a home. Home
ट्रेडिशन बन गया है। घर होना चाहिए। घर
Buy it quickly. so the people who have been
जल्दी खरीदो। सो द पीपल हु हैव बीन
Be successful in their jobs you know one
सक्सेसफुल इन देयर जॉब्स यू नो एक
There is a resolution that the house should be ready for retirement
रेजोल्यूशन होता है कि घर रिटायरमेंट के
I will make it later. Throw me to Kolkata
बाद बनाऊंगा। मुझे कोलकाता फेंक दो
Throw it to Aurangabad and I will go. so build a house
औरंगाबाद फेंक दो मैं जाऊंगा। सो घर बनाने
That you should not hurry so much. If you have to make
की इतनी जल्दी नहीं करनी। अगर आपको बनाना
yes you should be flexible to live in a
है भी यू शुड बी फ्लेक्सिबल टू लिव इन अ
Rented Accommodation. The third thing is that
रेंटेड अकोमोडेशन। थर्ड थिंग ये है दैट
Diversify Your Portfolio. if somebody is
डवर्सिफाई योर पोर्टफोलियो। इफ समबडी इस
Telling You Take a Portfolio PMS
टेलिंग यू पोर्टफोलियो पीएमएस ले लो ले लो
But use mutual fund, use PMS
बट यूज़ म्यूच्यूल फंड यूज़ पीएमएस यूज़
Various Things to Keep on Growing Your You
वेरियस थिंग्स टू कीप ऑन ग्रोइंग योर यू
no portfolio and the most important thing is this
नो पोर्टफोलियो एंड मोस्टेंट चीज यह है
Have a target in mind and get it somewhere
अपने मन में एक टारगेट रखो और वो कहीं
Document it because it is a moving goal
डॉक्यूमेंट कर दो क्योंकि वो मूविंग गोल
post that dude this is my net worth
पोस्ट है कि यार यह मेरे पास मेरी नेटवर्थ
If this happens then I will feel secure in
हो जाती है तो मैं आई विल फील सिक्योर इन
Life hum hmm. it is a continual
लाइफ हम हम्म। इट इज अ कंटीन्यूअसली
Moving goal posts. How Ever Build Inflation
मूविंग गोल पोस्ट। हाउ एवर बिल्ड इनफ्लेशन
Into it. Because what happens when Ranveer
इंटू इट। बिकॉज़ व्हाट हैपेंस रणवीर कि जब
He keeps moving, so you keep yourself moving
वो मूव करता रहता है ना तो आप अपने आप को
Then you are harsh on yourself. because dude
फिर यू आर हारश ऑन योरसेल्फ। क्योंकि यार
My net worth is this much, his is this much. So
मेरी नेटवर्थ इतनी है उसकी इतनी है। सो
these are the things i think very well for
दीज़ आर द थिंग्स आई थिंक वेरीेंट फॉर
Personal Finance Point of View. We are ok.
पर्सनल फाइनेंस पॉइंट ऑफ व्यू। हम ओके।
I would like to add a couple of points. the point
मैं एक दो पॉइंट ऐड करना चाहूंगा। द पॉइंट
I don't want to add what you already added
आई डोंट वांट टू ऐड व्हिच यू ऑलरेडी ऐडेड
Is PMS firms. Nobody tells us this
इज़ पीएमएस फर्म्स। यह कोई हमें बताता नहीं
that a portfolio management service is called
कि पोर्टफोलियो मैनेजमेंट सर्विस नाम की
There is one thing. Everybody thinks so, friend
एक चीज होती है। हर किसी को लगता है यार
How do I do personal finance? I
कि मैं पर्सनल फाइनेंस कैसे करूंगा। आई
Don't even know it. my suggestion is pms
डोंट इवन नो इट। माय स्यूशन इज़ पीएमएस
Find firms and work with them and targets
फर्म्स ढूंढो एंड वर्क विथ देम एंड टारगेट
Working with them early. The different PMS
वर्किंग विथ देम अर्ली। अलग-अलग पीएमएस
Lower thresholds vary across firms
फर्म्स में अलग-अलग लोअर थ्रेशहोल्ड्स
There are. That is, how much money is the minimum
होते हैं। यानी कि मिनिमम कितने पैसे
Have to invest. So find a good one
इन्वेस्ट करने हैं। तो फाइंड अ गुड वन
Which you can fit into. and this data is
व्हिच यू कैन फिट इंटू। एंड दिस डेटा इज
Easily available. It's published data. We are you
इजीली अवेलेबल। इट्स पब्लिश्ड डेटा। हम यू
Can these be PMS providers?
कैन सी कि ये पीएमएस प्रोवाइडर्स हैं।
What is the last three years Cager? Five
लास्ट थ्री इयर्स कैगर क्या है? फाइव
What is Ears Cagger? 10 years, seven years
इयर्स कैगर क्या है? 10 इयर्स, से इयर्स
What are the kinds of risk capital you know
व्हाट आर द काइंड ऑफ रिस्क कैपिट यू नो
What type of portfolio do they do? So
किस टाइप का पोर्टफोलियो वो करते हैं? तो
PMS is very important. Butt PMS
पीएमएस बहुत जरूरी है। बट पीएमएस
Requires a Certain Minimum Capital You Know
रिक्वायर्स अ सर्टेन मिनिमम कैपिटल यू नो
it's 50 lax before you can get into one
इट्स 50 लैक्स बिफोर यू कैन गेट इंटू अ
PMS. I think something like new age PMS
पीएमएस। आई थिंक कुछ-कुछ न्यू एज पीएमएस
Firms where threshold is Rs 10 lakh
फर्म्स है जहां 10 लाख का थ्रेशहोल्ड होता
Is. Fine. So I am not aware of that. But
है। फाइन। सो आई एम नॉट अवेयर ऑफ़ दैट। बट
if you have it I'm saying this if you have it
अगर है तो मैं यह कह रहा हूं अगर आपके पास
There is a good PMS, that's a very good way
एक अच्छा पीएमएस है दैट्स अ वेरी गुड वे
to really increase your wealth because of the way
टू रियली इंक्रीस योर वेल्थ बिकॉज़ द वे द
The Market Has Been in the Last Few Years
मार्केट हैज़ बीन इन द लास्ट फ्यू इयर्स
and is likely to be in the fourth coming
एंड इज़ लाइकली टू बी इन द फोर्थ कमिंग
Time you know apart from your salaried income
टाइम यू नो अपार्ट फ्रॉम योर सैलरीड इनकम
If you do it right then this can really
अगर ये आप ठीक करते हो तो दिस कैन रियली
Be a good wealth creation engine for you
बी अ गुड वेल्थ क्रिएशन इंजन हम फॉर यू
because it is important for the one who did not inherit
बिकॉज़ जरूरी है जिसने इन्हहेरिट नहीं किया
Isn't it true that we are talking about insecurity?
है ना जो हम इनसिक्योरिटी की बात कर रहे
That fear is always there, so make a target
थे वो डर हमेशा रहता है तो एक टारगेट बनाओ
And achieve it. It took 5 years, it took 10 years.
और उसको अचीव करो। 5 साल लगे, 10 साल लगे।
But consciously you have to make it happen. We
बट कॉन्शियसली यू हैव टू मेक इट हैपन। हम
we second point i would like to add is yaar
हम सेकंड पॉइंट आई वुड लाइक टू ऐड इज यार
Live within your means.
लिव अंडर योर मीन्स।
Especially in your 20s, the Instagram affair
एस्पेशली इन योर 20ज Instagram के चक्कर
I do not spend money on YouTube
में YouTube के चक्कर में डू नॉट स्पेंड
More than you need to spend. infact
मोर देन यू नीड टू स्पेंड। इनफैक्ट
Savings are cool and it will make your life
सेविंग्स आर कूल एंड इट विल मेक योर लाइफ
Much cool on your 30s. So live a little under
मच कूल ऑन योर 30ज। तो थोड़ा सा लिव अंडर
Your meals. so i am very simple about it
योर मील्स। सो मैं इसका बिल्कुल सिंपल है
That you know it's a crude way of saying it. You
कि यू नो इट्स अ क्रूड वे ऑफ़ सेइंग इट। आप
On whose strength are you dancing? You are spending,
किसके दम पर नाच रहे हो? खर्चा कर रहे हो,
Mummy and Daddy are giving it and it is limitless
मम्मी पापा दे रहे हैं और बेइंतहा है तो
do it. Brother you are wasting your own money and
करो। भैया अपना ही पैसा फूंक रहे हो और
If you are not saving then why are you
सेविंग नहीं कर रहे हो तो व्हाई आर यू
Shooting Yourself in the Foot. and you don't
शूटिंग योरसेल्फ इन द फुट। एंड यू डोंट
Have a security net. means that you to another
हैव अ सिक्योरिटी नेट। मतलब आप दूसरे को
Bleak your own future to show
दिखाने के लिए अपना अपना फ्यूचर ब्लीक कर
had been. So security net is variant.
रहे हो। तो सिक्योरिटी नेट इज वेरीेंट।
hmm so as you would no lot of people go and
हम्म सो एज यू वुड नो लॉट ऑफ पीपल गो एंड
Work in Africa, some people go to the Middle East
वर्क इन अफ्रीका सम पीपल गो टू मिडिल ईस्ट
But now you know in the Middle East the cost of
बट नाउ यू नो इन मिडिल ईस्ट कॉस्ट ऑफ
Living has gone up so I see a lot of my
लिविंग हैज़ गॉन अप तो आई सी लॉट ऑफ़ माय
friends they go to you know they have a
फ्रेंड्स दे गो टू यू नो दे हैव अ
The Hardship They Go Without to Create a Family
हार्डशिप दे गो विदाउट फैमिली टू क्रिएट
that safety net we're talking about that
दैट सेफ्टी नेट हम उसकी बात कर रहे हैं जो
If I am not inheriting then brother safety net
इनहेरिट नहीं कर रहा तो भैया सेफ्टी नेट
do what you have to do for it is very important
के लिए जो करना है करो बहुत जरूरी है वो
We have a final point I would like to add is one
हम अ फाइनल पॉइंट आई वुड लाइक टू ऐड इज़ एक
There is another thing which I think to some degree
और चीज है जो आई थिंक टू तो सम डिग्री
You are taught this in school. Butt often
आपको स्कूल में सिखाई जाती है। बट अक्सर
I have observed that finance strategy
मैंने ये देखा है कि फाइनेंस स्ट्रेटजी
The YouTube channels do not teach that
वाले YouTube चैनल्स ये नहीं सिखाते कि
Also focus on attacking game. That means the income
अटैकिंग गेम पर भी फोकस करो। यानी कि इनकम
Focus a little on increasing it. now weather you
बढ़ाने पर थोड़ा सा फोकस करो। नाउ वेदर यू
Are you doing it in one job and through multiple
आर डूइंग इट इन वन जॉब और थ्रू मल्टीपल
There should be some aggression in income sources
इनकम सोर्सेस वो थोड़ी सी अग्रेशन रहनी
Needed You should think about your own career
चाहिए। सोच डालनी चाहिए खुद के करियर में
How do I multiply this? do i get
कि हाउ डू आई मल्टीप्लाई दिस? डू आई गेट
Promoted to the next degree. how do i
प्रमोटेड टू द नेक्स्ट डिग्री। हाउ डू आई
Get promoted in that case? so i am fully
गेट प्रमोटेड इन दैट केस? सो आई फुल्ली
agree with sea today what has happened is
एग्री विद सी टुडे व्हाट हैज़ हैपेंड इज़
That's there two types of jobs. Some Jobs
दैट देयर टू टाइप्स ऑफ़ जॉब्स। कुछ जॉब्स
There are some things which can extract you so much.
ऐसी होती हैं जो आपको इतना एक्सट्रैक्ट कर
They take it. At least the kind of companies are
लेती हैं। एटलीस्ट द काइंड ऑफ़ कंपनीज़ आर
Work for Even to Go and Give a Guest
वर्क फॉर इवन टू गो एंड गिव अ गेस्ट
Lecture wasn't possible. but i think now
लेक्चर वाज़ंट पॉसिबल। बट आई थिंक नाउ
Companies are realizing this work life
कंपनीज़ आर रियलाइजिंग दिस वर्क लाइफ
Balance piece. so if we have a passion we end
बैलेंस पीस। सो इफ वी हैव अ पैशन हम एंड
you can slowly go without conflict
यू कैन स्लोली विदाउट कॉन्फ्लिक्ट ऑफ
Interest with your company. we are not moon
इंटरेस्ट विद योर कंपनी। वी आर नॉट मून
Lighting. I started my company in 45 hours
लाइटिंग। हम मैंने अपनी कंपनी को 45 आवर्स
But it was weak. after that whatever time I have
पर वीक दिया। उसके बाद जो मेरे पास टाइम
Bacha I fully agree with you that out of that
बचा आई फुल्ली एग्री विद यू कि उसमें से
also you should you should be aggressive too
आल्सो यू शुड यू शुड बी अग्रेसिव टू
INCREASE YOUR TOP LINE We ​​want that and that
इंक्रीस योर टॉप लाइन हम वो चाहिए और वो
When will the target be achieved? I have to achieve it bhaiya
कब होगा टारगेट ये मुझे अचीव करना है भैया
and for this I will do everything put in the
और इसके लिए मैं सब कुछ करूंगा पुट इन द
Extra House Exactly Exactly That
एक्स्ट्रा हाउस एक्सक्ट्ली एक्सक्ट्ली वो
Do you want or need this whole YouTube career?
चाहिए या मतलब ये पूरा YouTube करियर
I am self made, I did not take money from anyone
सेल्फ मेड है किसी से पैसे नहीं लिए
Parents also did not provide funds for age 22 to 24
पेरेंट्स ने भी फंड नहीं करा एज 22 से 24
Tak a I worked as a trainer and specially
तक अ आई वर्क्ड एज अ ट्रेनर एंड स्पेशली
On weekends. When the weekends were free I
ऑन वीकेंड्स। वीकेंड फ्री होता था तो मैं
He used to fill all the slots. and i would
सारे स्लॉट्स फिल कर देता था। एंड आई वुड
earn that extra money but it gave me a
अर्न दैट एक्स्ट्रा मनी बट इट गव मी अ
Cushion for my YouTube channel. so that at least
कुशन फॉर माय YouTube चैनल। तो वो एटलीस्ट
Between 22 and 27-28 that aggression will happen
बिटवीन 22 एंड 27 28 वो अग्रेशन होनी
I need a little. so you know this is very good
चाहिए थोड़ी सी। सो यू नो ये बहुत अच्छा
You stated the point. one of me
आपने पॉइंट बोला। मेरे से एक किसी ने
Took an interview a few days ago. Asked
थोड़े दिन पहले एक इंटरव्यू लिया। पूछा
Dude work life balance. I said I did
यार वर्क लाइफ बैलेंस। मैंने कहा मैंने तो
I never thought about it. If you work life
कभी सोचा ही नहीं। अगर आप वर्क लाइफ
Balance you are thinking that I will stay longer than this
बैलेंस सोच रहे हो कि मैं इससे ज्यादा समय
If I don't give it then change your job. That means that you
नहीं दूंगा तो चेंज योर जॉब। यानी कि यू
I am not in the right job. second thing if you
आर नॉट इन द राइट जॉब। सेकंड चीज़ अगर आपको
I am not getting juice in my job, I am not getting juice
जॉब में जूस नहीं मिल रहा है, रस नहीं मिल
it is, juice is the right word you know which is ours
रहा है, रस इस द राइट वर्ड यू नो जो हमारा
If I am not getting Rasa then Bhaiya I have a day job
रसा हम नहीं मिल रहा है तो भैया डे जॉब तो
then do something else on the weekend but this
है ना तो वीकेंड में कुछ और करो बट ये
It is absolutely correct that you should increase your income
बिल्कुल सही बात है कि इनकम यू नो बढ़ानी
It is very important when I was growing up.
बहुत जरूरी है व्हेन आई वास ग्रोइंग अप आई
don't know if it is right or wrong so they
डोंट नो इफ इट इज़ राइट और रोंग सो दे
What is the difference between Told me Bunny and Punjabi
टोल्ड मी बनी और पंजाबी में क्या फर्क है
Punjabis believe that God has increased my expenses
पंजाबी मानते हैं रब मेरे खर्चे बढ़ा हम
If you increase your expenses then you will automatically generate income
खर्चे बढ़ाएगा तो इनकम के लिए अपने आप
I will run but I don't know if it is true or not
भागूंगा बट आई डोंट नो इफ इट ट्रू ऑर नॉट
But I 100% agree with this, do it a little
बट 100% आई एग्री विथ दिस कि थोड़ी सी करो
Friend, bring passion and do it, you know we
यार मतलब जुनून लाओ और करो यू नो हम
swing the bat really hard wali r young yes
स्विंग द बैट रियली हार्ड वाली आर यंग यस
Absolutely okay right now I think we've wrapped
अब्सोलुटली ओके अभी आई थिंक वी हैव रैप्ड
Up the Topic About Personal Finance for Someone
अप द टॉपिक अबाउट पर्सनल फाइनेंस फॉर समवन
Who is self-made? Those who inherit money
हु इज़ सेल्फ मेड जो लोग पैसे इन्हहेरिट कर
are inheriting the property
रहे हैं प्रॉपर्टी इन्हहेरिट कर रहे हैं
I would like to bracket these separately.
मैं इन्हें ब्रैकेट करना चाहूंगा अलग-अलग
In the layers of A capital, suppose that someone
अ कैपिटल के लेयर्स में तो मान लो कि किसी
has a capital of Rs 1 lakh. Someone has
के पास 1 लाख का कैपिटल है। किसी के पास
One person has a capital of Rs 10 lakh. Any
वन किसी के पास 10 लाख का कैपिटल है। किसी
has a capital of Rs 1 crore. Someone has
के पास 1 करोड़ का कैपिटल है। किसी के पास
There is a capital of Rs 10 crore. Now tell me Sir Four
10 करोड़ का कैपिटल है। अब बताइए सर फोर
Categories: How is the game of personal finance now?
कैटेगरीज़ अब पर्सनल फाइनेंस की गेम कैसी
should I play? so when we say this
खेलनी चाहिए? सो व्हेन वी से ये हमने
inherited it i.e. my father
इन्हहेरिट किया यानी कि मेरे फादर ने
He gave me the cheque. That would never happen
मुझको चेक दे दिया। ऐसा तो कभी नहीं होता
because he is giving you a gift or he
क्योंकि वह आपको गिफ्ट कर रहे हैं या वह
Giving you money for investment
आपको इन्वेस्टमेंट के लिए पैसा दे रहे
Are. Both things are different. you get my
हैं। दोनों बातें अलग हैं। यू गेट माय
Point? this inheritance
पॉइंट? दिस इनहेरिटेंस
is a seed money for you to make a business and
इज अ सीड मनी फॉर यू टू मेक अ बिजनेस और
This is seed money to grow the wealth. if it is
दिस इज सीड मनी टू ग्रो द वेल्थ। इफ इट इज़
Seed Money to Grow the Wealth. That means a gift
सीड मनी टू ग्रो द वेल्थ। यानी कि गिफ्ट
Did. I gave my child ₹1 on his birthday
किया। बर्थडे पे मैंने अपने बच्चे को ₹1
Gave Rs 10 crore. in most cases
करोड़ 10 लाख दे दिया। इन मोस्ट केसेस
Only the parents will decide. but if it is
पेरेंट्स ही डिसाइड करेंगे। बट इफ इट इज
As a seed money for your business for your
एज अ सीड मनी फॉर योर बिजनेस फॉर योर
passionate idea so I will say this to him
पैशनेट आईडिया तो मैं यह बोलूंगा उसी
taking capital and doing what you want
कैपिटल को लेते हुए और जो आप करना चाहते
Make a three year business plan. so i
हो एक थ्री ईयर बिजनेस प्लान बनाओ। सो मैं
I am saying that
कह रहा हूं कि
Whatever I learnt in business, I also learnt it in Reliance
बिजनेस में जो मैंने सीखा Reliance में भी
And many other brothers are from Gujarati community
और बाकी काफी गुजराती कम्युनिटी से भाई
There are 300 days in a year. Ok? They
300 दिन एक साल में होते हैं। ठीक है? वो
It is said that 1000 days are also calculated as 365 days.
बोलते हैं 1000 दिन 365 के हिसाब से भी
Invest ₹1 in this for 1000 days
लगाओ 1000 दिन तक ₹1 मैं इसमें से
I will not take it out
निकालूंगा नहीं
1000, if you have to deposit ₹1 in one day then it will be closed
1000 वे एक दिन अगर ₹1 डालना पड़े तो बंद
are you getting the drift so I have ₹1
आर यू गेटिंग द ड्रिफ्ट सो मेरे पास ₹1
There are lakhs. I made a business plan and
लाख हैं। मैंने एक बिजनेस प्लान बनाया और
I have ₹1 crore and I have a business plan
मेरे पास ₹1 करोड़ मैंने बिजनेस प्लान
Made. The principal is same in both. This
बनाया। दोनों में प्रिंसिपल सेम है। इसी
I won't ask for ₹1 extra within the range
दायरे में ₹1 एक्स्ट्रा मांगूंगा नहीं
From mom and dad. In this the business
मम्मी पापा से। इसी में बिजनेस को
I will drive it. From this, for your household expenses
चलाऊंगा। इसमें से अपने घर खर्च के लिए
I will not take out anything. with in 1000 days it
कुछ नहीं निकालूंगा। विद इन 1000 डेज इट
Should generate cash it should be cash positive. We
शुड जनरेट कैश इट शुड बी कैश पॉजिटिव। हम
If After 1000 Days I Still Need to If I
इफ आफ्टर 1000 डेज आई स्टिल नीड टू इफ आई
I'm in a negative cash flow and this is to me
एम इन अ नेगेटिव कैश फ्लो और ये मेरे को
If you want more money, close the business. We
और पैसा चाहिए बिनेस को बंद कर दो। हम
It's a very simple funda. This is not 1 lakh today
बड़ा सिंपल फंडा है। ये नहीं है आज 1 लाख
Is. Papa, give me 10,000 more. Give me 20,000 more
है। पापा 10,000 और दे देना। 20,000 और दे
Give. There is no such business because we
देना। ऐसे कोई बिनेस नहीं होता हम बिकॉज़
you should know that i have got capital
यू शुड नो कि जो मेरे को कैपिटल मिला है
I have to walk in that only. Basically 3 years
मेरे को उसी में चलना है। बेसिकली 3 साल
This is the timeline of. Ok? and that initial
की टाइमलाइन है। ठीक है? और वो इनिशियल
by doing something with the capital initially
कैपिटल के साथ कुछ ना कुछ करके इनिशियली
Maybe by spending 10,000 maybe 1 lakh
शायद 10,000 स्पेंड करके शायद 1 लाख
If you have Rs 1 crore by spending.
स्पेंड करके अगर आपके पास 1 करोड़ है।
Basically a percentage of that income. Maybe
बेसिकली अ परसेंटेज ऑफ़ दैट इनकम। मे बी
Between 1 to 10% Play with it and try
बिटवीन वन टू 10% उसके साथ खेलो एंड ट्राई
Figuring out how to make it profitable
फिगरिंग आउट कि उसको प्रॉफिटेबल कैसे
Make it. gives a practical example
बनाए। एक प्रैक्टिकल एग्जांपल दे देता
Am. A lot of people are very upset that
हूं। काफी लोगों को बड़ा टशन है कि
Let's open a restaurant. Are we okay? We
रेस्टोरेंट खोल लेते हैं। हम ठीक है? हम
So I ask brother in the restaurant
तो मैं पूछता हूं भाई रेस्टोरेंट में
How much money will it cost? let's say i'm taking
कितना पैसा लगेगा? लेट्स से आई एम टेकिंग
Some Arbitrary Number Interior Vitreous All
सम आर्बिट्रेरी नंबर इंटीरियर विटीरियर सब
Invested crores of rupees. how much is the rent?
लगा के ₹ करोड़ लगा दिए। किराया कितना है?
₹5 Lakh per month. Ok. I am so much my friend
₹5 लाख महीना। ठीक है। हम सर इतना तो मेरे
It is nearby, I will do it. So, the one who earns ₹5 lakh per month
पास है मैं कर लूंगा। तो जो ₹5 लाख महीने
Rent is Rs. 50,000 plus up to ₹ 50,000 lakh
का किराया है प्लस ऊपर से ₹ लाख के
There are overheads. Plus whatever sale you will get
ओवरहेड्स हैं। प्लस आपका जो सेल आएगी क्या
Will there be no cash losses initially? We
शुरू में कैश लॉसेस नहीं होंगे? हम
What is your expenditure and what is your income
क्या आपका जो खर्चा है और जो आपकी इनकम है
will it reach the break even point from
विल इट रीच द ब्रेक इवन पॉइंट फ्रॉम
First Month Know It Might Take Six Months 8
फर्स्ट मंथ नो इट माइट टेक सिक्स मंथ्स 8
Months to reach break even who will fund that
मंथ्स टू रीच ब्रेक इवन हु विल फंड दैट
Apart from Money Hundred Crore, it can be your ₹
मनी सो करोड़ के अलावा हो सकता है आपका ₹
Negative cash flow of Rs. lakh per month is over
लाख पर मंथ का नेगेटिव कैश फ्लो है एंड
it's you budget it for six months then you
इट्स यू बजटे इट फॉर सिक्स मंथ्स देन यू
need ₹ crore and 18 lakhs waiting out there
नीड ₹ करोड़ एंड 18 लैक्स वेटिंग आउट देयर
This is the math which many youngsters don't
दिस इज द मैथ व्हिच मेनी यंगस्टर्स डोंट
Understand now that by pausing slightly
अंडरस्टैंड अभी कि हल्के से पॉज करके
Jugaad thinking that okay for me is food business
जुगाड़ थिंकिंग कि ठीक है मुझे फूड बिनेस
I have to get in. and my definition of getting
में घुसना है। एंड माय डेफिनेशन ऑफ गेटिंग
I want to open this food business or a restaurant.
इंटू फूड बिज़नेस इज रेस्टोरेंट खोलना है।
Start a Cloud Kitchen Business Instead
उसके बदले क्लाउड किचन बिज़नेस स्टार्ट
do it. Absolutely. If instead of that you really need to grind
करो। बिल्कुल। उसके बदले अगर सच में घिसाई
If you want to do it then start street food business
करनी है तो स्ट्रीट फूड बिज़नेस स्टार्ट
do it. Go sell your food on the street. master
करो। गो सेल योर फूड ऑन द स्ट्रीट। मास्टर
The Art of Food. Or once you had food
दी आर्ट ऑफ़ फूड। या एक बार आपने फूड
Once you have completed your Masters, you can run a restaurant.
मास्टर कर लिया फिर रेस्टोरेंट चला लोगे।
Exactly. and my point in this was
एक्सैक्टली। एंड मेरा इसमें पॉइंट ये था
Which is yours worth Rs 1 lakh, 10 lakh, one crore
जो 1 लाख, 10 लाख, एक करोड़ का आपका
There was an example. it's again link to that
एग्जांपल था। इट्स अगेन लिंक टू दैट
Personal Finance vs Business Finance.
पर्सनल फाइनेंस वर्सेस बिजनेस फाइनेंस।
This is the basic funda of business finance. Yours
बिजनेस फाइनेंस का बेसिक फंडा यह है। आपका
What is the capital expenditure? Capex
कैपिटल एक्सपेंडिचर कितना है? कैपेक्स
How much is it? How much is the OPEX? Monthly Expenses
कितना है? ओपेक्स कितना है? मंथली खर्चा
How much is it? What is the break even point? And
कितना है? ब्रेक इवन पॉइंट कितना है? और
to reach that break even point
उस ब्रेक इवन पॉइंट तक पहुंचने के लिए
How much total fund do I need? So upfront
मेरे को टोटल फंड कितना चाहिए? तो अपफ्रंट
Investment Plus the Negative Cash Flows
इन्वेस्टमेंट प्लस द नेगेटिव कैश फ्लोस
Till you reach break even point is the money that
टिल यू रीच ब्रेक इवन पॉइंट इज द मनी दैट
You should have. We should have this funda. No
यू शुड हैव। हम यह फंडा होना चाहिए। नहीं
Then after a few days you will take the bowl again
तो थोड़े दिन बाद फिर कटोरा लेके जाओगे
You will come to your father after getting scolded and this
पिताजी के पास और डांट खा के आओगे और ये
No, what you are saying is very common.
ना बहुत कॉमन है जो आप कह रहे हो ये
Overspending the Capital Etcetera
ओवरस्पेंडिंग द कैपिटल एटसेट्रा
But why does this overspending happen?
पर ये ओवरस्पेंडिंग होती क्यों है
Overspending on an actual human level
एक्चुअली एक ह्यूमन लेवल पर ओवरस्पेंडिंग
Why does it happen? Look, you have two things.
होती क्यों है देखो दो चीजें हैं आपकी
The forecasting was wrong because and it of course
फोरकास्टिंग गलत थी बिकॉज़ एंड इट ऑफन
happens because you have never worked hard with it
हैपेंस बिकॉज़ यू हैव नेवर वर्क विद टफ
Bosses, the type of bosses we worked with
बॉसेस जिस तरीके के बॉसेस से हमने काम
Did you give the forecast? If you gave it then
किया ना फोरकास्ट अगर आपने ने दे दी तो
Firstly 20 questions will be asked. what is the basis
पहले तो 20 सवाल पूछे जाएंगे। बेसिस क्या
Is? What is an Assumption Sheet? What is a term sheet?
है? एजमशन शीट क्या है? टर्म शीट क्या है?
What have you assumed interest rate?
व्हाट हैव यू अस्यूम्ड इंटरेस्ट रेट?
what have you assumed about you know
व्हाट हैव यू अस्यूम्ड अबाउट यू नो
Inflation rate? so there is an assumption sheet
इनफ्लेशन रेट? सो देयर इज़ एन एजम्पशन शीट
Based on which you make a forecast and then
बेस्ड ऑन व्हिच यू मेक अ फोरकास्ट एंड देन
This will happen to you. Not like this one day I
यू से ऐसा होगा। ऐसे नहीं एक दिन मैंने
I did it while sitting. so this is one
बैठे-बैठे करके कर लिया। सो दिस इज वन
The reason why it's going wrong is one thing that's wrong
थिंग रीज़न ऑफ इट गोइंग रोंग इज़ वन रोंग
Forecast. it is not necessary
फॉरकास्ट। इट इज़ नॉट नेसेसरीली
Overspending. it is you have to forecast
ओवरस्पेंडिंग। इट इज आपको फॉरकास्ट करनी
I don't know it because I haven't learnt it from anyone
ही नहीं आती क्योंकि सीखी नहीं है ना किसी
has taught so first of all we
ने सिखाई है तो हम सबसे पहले अपने कोर्स
I will teach forecasting. without him anything
में फॉरकास्टिंग सिखाएंगे। उसके बिना कुछ
Cannot be done. the second point is if you
नहीं हो सकता। सेकंड पॉइंट ये है अगर आप
You are going over budget, how are you going brother?
ओवर बजट जा रहे हो जा कैसे रहे हो भाई?
Was there no month wise budget? who is authorized
बजट नहीं था क्या मंथ वाइज? हु ऑथराइज्ड
You too go over the budget. hum if you are going
यू टू गो ओवर द बजट। हम इफ यू आर गोइंग
Over the budget. this there has to be a
ओवर द बजट। ये देयर हैज़ टू बी अ
Justification.
जस्टिफिकेशन।
Like I was handling x amount of late
लाइक आई वास हैंडलिंग एक्स अमाउंट ऑफ लेट
to Rs 850 crore from advertising and sales
से 850 करोड़ ऑफ एडवरटाइजिंग एंड सेल्स
Promotion Budget in a Year If I Divide it Month Wise
प्रमोशन बजट इन अ ईयर अगर मैं मंथ वाइज
I have broken it, if mine this month
उसको मैंने तोड़ा हुआ है अगर मेरा इस महीने
I have 20 crores and I am doing 22, so I
का 20 करोड़ है मैं 22 कर रहा हूं तो मुझे
I will have to tell my boss sir 2 crores
अपने बॉस को बताना पड़ेगा ना सर 2 करोड़
That's why I'm spending extra and this is me
इसलिए एक्स्ट्रा खर्च रहा हूं और ये मैं
This is how I will recover. Are you getting the point?
ऐसे रिकवरी करूंगा। आर यू गेटिंग द पॉइंट?
This is the sense that's why I am just jumping
ये जो सेंस है ना दैट्स व्हाई जस्ट जंपिंग
Getting into business is fine but understanding this
इंटू बिज़नेस इज़ फाइन बट अंडरस्टैंडिंग दीज़
Very Basic Principles of Cash Management
वेरी बेसिक प्रिंसिपल्स ऑफ रोकड़ा हम
Management is very important. We are overspending
मैनेजमेंट बहुत जरूरी है। हम ओवरस्पेंडिंग
How did it happen brother? There was no budget system. We
कैसे हो गई भाई? बजट सिस्टम नहीं था। हम
Why a system of plan vs actual
कोई प्लान वर्सेस एक्चुअल का सिस्टम क्यों
Wasn't it? So why start a business?
नहीं था? तो क्यों करा बिज़नेस स्टार्ट?
which is why i think its very important that
व्हिच इज़ व्हाई आई थिंक इट्स वेरीेंट कि
At the beginning of a business person's career
करियर के शुरुआत में किसी बिजनेस पर्सन के
Working together is essential. Absolutely. Learn
साथ काम करना जरूरी है। अब्सोलुटली। सीखो
Understand how organizations are run.
समझो कि ऑर्गेनाइजेशनंस कैसे रन होते हैं।
And if business is from a family then from childhood
और अगर बिजनेस फैमिली से हो तो बचपन से
You must have learnt it. But it can also be like this
सीख ही लिया होगा। बट ऐसा भी हो सकता है
That your parents are not in business. they have
कि आपके पेरेंट्स बिनेस में ना हो। दे हैव
Been in the job and you're starting out but
बीन इन द जॉब एंड यू आर स्टार्टिंग आउट बट
The Fundamental Building Blocks What I
दी फंडामेंटल बिल्डिंग ब्लॉक्स व्हाट आई
Mentioned few things break even point cash
मेंशंड फ्यू थिंग्स ब्रेक इवन पॉइंट कैश
Flow management is very important. otherwise
फ्लो मैनेजमेंट ये बहुत जरूरी है। अदरवाइज
What will happen?
क्या होगा?
What is its consequence? again we go back
इसका कॉन्सक्वेंस क्या है? अगेन वी गो बैक
To the Psychological Thing We Worry About
टू द साइकोलॉजिकल थिंग वि आई वरी अबाउट
We should not lose our self confidence
सेल्फ कॉन्फिडेंस नहीं टूटना चाहिए हम हम
because when you go back to ask for money
क्योंकि वो जब पैसा मांगने आप वापस जाओगे
neither does it make you feel ashamed
ना तो जो आपके अंदर एक जलालत फील होती है
Nor does it destroy the man. J
ना वो आदमी को डिस्ट्रॉय कर देती है। ज
It happens a lot in me. very emotional
में तो बहुत होता है। बहुत इमोशनली
He is sensitive. A little scolding in our time
सेंसिटिव है। हमारे टाइम में थोड़ी डांट
It would get a scratch. We sand it. Now
डूट पड़ जाती थी। हम सैंड कर लेते हैं। अब
You can't say anything. I think parents are here
नहीं बोल सकते आप। आई थिंक यहां पेरेंट्स
The role needs to be a bit hand holding
का रोल थोड़ा सा हैंड होल्डिंग वाला होना
Needed Absolutely. mild to very important
चाहिए। अब्सोलुटली। हल्के से बहुत जरूरी
Is. This is the specialty of India, that here
है। ये भारत की खासियत है कि यहां
Parents get a little involved in career
पेरेंट्स थोड़े इन्वॉल्व हो जाते हैं करियर
In. At least for guidance early teaching
में। एटलीस्ट फॉर गाइडेंस अर्ली टीचिंग
etc. A ok. So I asked you 1 lakh and
वगैरह। अ ओके। तो मैंने आपसे पूछा 1 लाख व
10 la vs 1 crore vs 10 crore.
10 लै वर्सेस 1 करोड़ वर्सेस 10 करोड़।
The principal is the same. Yes sir. Principal Beans
प्रिंसिपल सेम है। हां जी। प्रिंसिपल सेम
Is. Ok. Ok. For now you have to do this
है। ओके। ठीक है। अभी के लिए आपको इसी
I will ask questions associated with chapter A that
चैप्टर अ से एसोसिएटेड सवाल पूछूंगा कि
Suppose your parents didn't give you seed capital
मान लो पेरेंट्स ने आपको सीड कैपिटल नहीं
has given it. Directly into your bank account
दिया है। डायरेक्टली आपके बैंक अकाउंट में
They put in the money and gave us independence
पैसे डाल दिए और इंडिपेंडेंस भी दे दी
Son, do anything. Yes. Ok. 1 lakh and 10
बेटा कुछ भी करो। हां। ठीक है। 1 लाख व 10
Lakh versus 1 crore and 10 crore. so if i
लाख वर्सेस 1 करोड़ व 10 करोड़। सो इफ आई
I have only 1 lakh I will go and put it in the
हैव ओनली 1 लाख आई विल गो एंड पुट इट इन द
Best mutual funds. We are very simple. We
बेस्ट म्यूचुअल फंड। हम वेरी सिंपल। हम
I will not look left or right here and there. Yes
मैं इधर उधर बाएं दाएं नहीं देखूंगा। जी
if i have 10 la i will divide it between
इफ आई हैव 10 लै आई विल डिवाइड इट बिटवीन
Mutual funds may be some other asset class
म्यूचुअल फंड्स मे बी सम अदर एसेट क्लास
it could be gold or something else but I will
इट कुड बी गोल्ड और समथिंग एल्स बट आई विल
do that if i have 1 crore right after 10
डू दैट इफ आई हैव 1 करोड़ राइट आफ्टर 10
lax is 1 crore then i will take a pms
लैक्स इज़ 1 करोड़ देन आई विल टेक अ पीएमएस
I will take a mutual fund you know I might
आई विल टेक अ म्यूचुअल फंड यू नो आई माइट
take some little bit of gold and I might
टेक सम लिटिल बिट ऑफ़ गोल्ड एंड आई माइट
also you know invest little bit in a
आल्सो यू नो इन्वेस्ट लिटिल बिट इन अ
Property which is under construction
प्रॉपर्टी व्हिच इज़ अंडर कंस्ट्रक्शन
which i know comes from a sound you know
व्हिच आई नो कम्स फ्रॉम अ साउंड यू नो
builder house i don't want to loose my shirt
बिल्डर हाउस आई डोंट वांट टू लूज माय शर्ट
ok and i would do that as well so that you
ओके एंड आई वुड डू दैट एस वेल सो दैट यू
no i make some you no appreciation for me
नो आई मेक सम यू नो एप्रिसिएशन मेरे को
If I get it then I will give him three or four assets
मिले तो मैं उसको फिर तीन या चार एसेट
I will put you in class, I will not cry hey
क्लास में डालूंगा मैं रोऊंगा नहीं अरे
The stock market has fallen brother, the shares will fall
शेयर मार्केट गिर गई भाई शेयर गिरेगी तो
Gold will rise
गोल्ड उठेगा
It is the reverse, we have war, gold is up
उल्टा इनवर्स है ना हम वॉर हुई गोल्ड ऊपर
We reached the spot, so the stock fell down so hedging
पहुंच गया हम शेयर नीचे गिरा तो हैेजिंग
aren't they like us who you know
है ना हम जैसे जो यू नो
It's you have to hedge at your own risk.
इट्स इट्स यू हैव टू हैेज योर रिस्क।
That's what I will do. I will divide it
दैट्स व्हाट आई विल डू। आई विल डिवाइड इट
into multiple asset classes which i am
इंटू मल्टीपल एसेट क्लासेस व्हिच आई एम
Comfortable with it but one thing is very clear.
कंफर्टेबल विद बट वन थिंग इज वेरी क्लियर।
I will talk to three experts and use
आई विल टॉक टू थ्री एक्सपर्ट्स एंड यूज़
My own intelligence. Blind trust on someone
माय ओन बुद्धि। किसी पे ब्लाइंड ट्रस्ट
I will not do it. and i'm assuming that 10
नहीं करूंगा। एंड आई एम अस्यूमिंग कि 10
1 Crore Strategy for Crore Bracket
करोड़ के ब्रैकेट के लिए 1 करोड़ स्ट्रेटजी
into 10. That is absolutely correct. 1 Crore
इंटू 10। बिल्कुल ठीक बात है। 1 करोड़
Strategy into 10. Ok. Ok. Moving
स्ट्रेटजी इंटू 10। ओके। ठीक है। मूविंग
On to the next chapter. Now we will talk about 2025
ऑन नेक्स्ट चैप्टर। अब हम बात करेंगे 2025
About the relevant industries of India
के इंडिया के रेलेवेंट इंडस्ट्रीज के बारे
Where there is high potential growth. then respect
में जहां हाई पोटेंशियल ग्रोथ है। तो मान
You have seed capital to start your business here
लो आपके पास सीड कैपिटल है यहां बिजनेस
What do you definitely want to do in your life?
डेफिनेटली करना है जिंदगी में कौन सी
Industries should target us again
इंडस्ट्रीज को टारगेट करना चाहिए अगेन वी
And this means that your family business is now
आर इसमें ये है कि आपका फैमिली बिनेस अभी
is it not us that you have to decide if
है कि नहीं हम दैट यू हैव टू डिसाइड अगर
my family business is it ok or not
मेरा फैमिली बिजनेस है ठीक है या नहीं है
so i will answer first if its a family business
सो आई विल आंसर फर्स्ट अगर फैमिली बिजनेस
so first of all i would check that
है तो मैं सबसे पहले यह देखूंगा कि
What are the things that make me
कौन-कौन सी चीजें हैं जिसकी वजह से मैं
I will be disrupted. This is definitely a disruptor
डिसरप्ट होऊंगा। यह तो श्योर है डिसरप्ट
Will be done. i.e. self awareness
होना ही है। यानी कि सेल्फ अवेयरनेस
related to the weaknesses to the weaknesses and the
रिलेटेड टू वीकनेसेस टू द वीकनेसेस एंड द
rate of change of technology we let you know
रेट ऑफ चेंज ऑफ टेक्नोलॉजी हम यू नो लेट्स
say let's say today yesterday i somebody had come
से लेट्स से टुडे यस्टरडे आई समबडी हैड कम
Home and they are into they are big travel
होम एंड दे आर इंटू दे आर बिग ट्रेवल
Agents. I said friend in today's time
एजेंट्स। मैंने कहा यार आज के जमाने में
There is also a travel agent. It is said bro
ट्रेवल एजेंट भी होता है। कहते है भैया
There is medical tourism. he doesn't trust
मेडिकल टूरिज्म है। वो नहीं ट्रस्ट कर
I can do it online. so you get my
सकता ऑनलाइन वाले को। सो यू गेट माय
Point. I am saying that my business
पॉइंट। मैं कह रहा हूं कि मेरा जो बिजनेस
in that I would see that the AI,
है उसमें मैं यह देखूंगा कि एआई,
Technology, Digitization and New
टेक्नोलॉजी, डिजिटाइजेशन एंड न्यू
Trends How It Will Disrupt My Business
ट्रेंड्स हाउ इट विल डिसरप्ट माय बिनेस
and i will invest that money to hedge my
एंड आई विल इन्वेस्ट दैट मनी टू हैेज माय
Risk. We are you getting the points? If
रिस्क। हम आर यू गेटिंग द पॉइंट्स? अगर
I have a jewelry store or we are bhaiya
मेरा ज्वेलरी स्टोर है या हम तो भैया
Our designs are such that people stand in line to get them
हमारे डिज़ ऐसे हैं लोग लाइन लगा के लेके
I don't want to do it online sir
जाते हैं मुझे नहीं ऑनलाइन करना हम तो सर
If you don't want to do it today you will have to do it tomorrow people will come
आज नहीं करना कल तो करना पड़ेगा लोग आ ही
We are no more Blinkit at all
नहीं रहे हम ब्लिंकिट ने तो बिल्कुल ही
finished after i see it on the table
खत्म कर दिया आफ्टर आई सी ऑन द टेबल इट
has happened in my house when the sauce ran out
हैज़ हैपेंड इन माय हाउस सॉस खत्म हुई तो
The pakoras were served and the sauce was ready in no time
पकोड़े सर्व हो गए और सॉस उतनी देर में आ
I am gone but here so this is one
गई हम लेकिन जी हमारे यहां सो दिस इज़ वन
now suppose i'm starting out a fresh
नाउ सपोज़ आई एम स्टार्टिंग आउट अ फ्रेश
diff different case right its none of my business
डिफर डिफरेंट केस राइट मेरा कोई बिज़नेस
Not there. I am a youngster. I do something
नहीं है। मैं यंगस्टर हूं। मैं कुछ करना
I want. I will say this
चाहता हूं। मैं यह बोलूंगा
First it has to start with inside you
फर्स्ट इट हैज़ टू स्टार्ट विद आपके अंदर
What is the capability? It is written in our Gita
क्या कैपेबिलिटी है? हमारी गीता में लिखा
It has happened. Is it okay? fear of another's religion
हुआ है। ठीक है ना? दूसरे का धर्म भय
It generates. Follow your own religion. it
उत्पन्न करता है। अपने स्वधर्म पे चलो। यह
Dharma is not religion. It means your nature. We
धर्म रिलजन नहीं है। इट मींस योर नेचर। हम
God has given every person a gift
हर एक इंसान को भगवान ने कोई गिफ्ट दिया
Is. I gave you a gift. it was manifested
है। आपको गिफ्ट दिया। वो मैनिफेस्ट हुआ
You. Right? It doesn't happen to anybody
आप। राइट? किसी का नहीं होता है
Manifest. so important is what you
मैनिफेस्ट। सो इंपॉर्टेंट यह है आप क्या
Can you contribute? suppose i am saying
कंट्रीब्यूट कर सकते हो? सपोज आई एम सेइंग
Biotech and biological related issues are a big deal
बायोटेक और बायोलॉजिकल रिलेटेड इज़ अ बिग
Business Opportunity Like Anti Aging in a
बिज़नेस ओपोरर्चुनिटी लाइक एंटी एजिंग इन अ
few years it's already happening but when
फ्यू इयर्स इट्स ऑलरेडी हैपनिंग बट व्हेन
I talk to my friends you know I don't even know
आई टॉक टू माई फ्रेंड्स यू नो आई डोंट इवन
no weather we will die at 150 or what is
नो वेदर वी विल डाई एट 150 ऑर व्हाट इज़
Going to happen. So bio is an area. AI
गोइंग टू हैपन। सो बायो इज़ एन एरिया। एआई
It is definitely an area. you know process
इज़ डेफिनेटली एन एरिया। यू नो प्रोसेस
Digitization is another area. so these are some
डिजिटाइजेशन इज़ अनदर एरिया। सो दीज़ आर सम
of the emerging areas how ever it
ऑफ द इमर्जिंग एरियाज हाउ एवर हाउ एवर इट
has got nothing to do with just potential
हैज़ गॉट नथिंग टू डू विद जस्ट पोटेंशियल
it has to match with what you bring to the
इट हैज़ टू मैच विद व्हाट यू ब्रिंग टू द
table are you getting my point
टेबल आर यू गेटिंग माय पॉइंट मेरा
There is no interest in AIA brother
इंटरेस्ट ही नहीं है एआईए में भाई
Why should I go there, I don't have a bio
मैं काहे जाऊं उधर मेरे को नहीं है बायो
I am interested in what potential I will do
में इंटरेस्ट तो पोटेंशियल क्या करेगा मैं
I'm a good chef so I'll go eat
अच्छा शेफ हूं तो मैं खाने में जाऊंगा अरे
My food is getting disrupted, brother
खाना तो डिसररप्ट हो रहा है भाई वो मेरा
It is a gift na hum it is my gift which God
गिफ्ट है ना हम इट इज माय गिफ्ट व्हिच गॉड
has given to me which I need to nurture are
हैज़ गिवन टू मी व्हिच आई नीड टू न्चर आर
you are getting this gift i think a great
यू गेटिंग दिस गिफ्ट आई थिंक अ ग्रेट
Practice is a reflection of your own life
प्रैक्टिस इज अगर आपकी खुद की लाइफ की एक
There's a timeline and you're somewhere
टाइमलाइन रही है और आप कहीं ना कहीं
You've arrived and now have seed capital
पहुंचे हो और आपके पास अब सीड कैपिटल है
If you want to start a business then at that point
आपको बिज़नेस स्टार्ट करना है तो उस पॉइंट
Life experiences whatever happened before
के पहले जो भी हुआ है लाइफ एक्सपीरियंसेस
skill sets, courses done, studies etc.
स्किल सेट्स कोर्सेज डन स्टडीज वगैरह उन
Scan everything and ask yourself:
सारी चीजों को स्कैन करो और खुद से पूछो
what did I find most interesting then
कि मुझे सबसे इंटरेस्टिंग क्या लगा फिर
Ask me whether I am interested in this
पूछो कि इसी इंटरेस्ट को लेकर क्या मैं
Create a monetizable product or service
कोई मोनेटाइजेबल प्रोडक्ट या सर्विस बना
can I or not? Absolutely. and if the answer
सकता हूं या नहीं? बिल्कुल। एंड इफ द आंसर
yes begin. But there wouldn't be a triangle in it
यस बिगिन। बट इसमें ना एक ट्रायंगल होता
Is. Just interest is not enough. One
है। सिर्फ इंटरेस्ट इनफ नहीं होता। एक
There is interest. There is a potential
इंटरेस्ट होता है। एक पोटेंशियल होता है
And there is a skill set. the potential of the
और एक स्किल सेट होता है। पोटेंशियल ऑफ़ द
Industry of that person. Ok. I am good
इंडस्ट्री ऑफ दैट पर्सन। ओके। मैं अच्छा
I will not sing today.
आज गाता नहीं हूं।
But I love singing. so my
लेकिन मुझे गाने का शौक है। तो मेरा
I am interested. I don’t have the skill set.
इंटरेस्ट है। मेरे पास स्किल सेट नहीं है।
I have the potential. Some guru said
मेरे पास पोटेंशियल है। किसी गुरु ने बोला
that he will become a good singer. but today it's out of tune
कि अच्छा गायक बनेगा। लेकिन आज बेसुरा
He sings. All three have to match and then
गाता है। ऑल थ्री हैव टू मैच एंड देन
Monetization has to come. so i am the answer to this
मोनेटाइजेशन हैज़ टू कम। सो इसका आंसर मैं
I am giving it. Your question is very simple. Brother
दे रहा हूं। आपका सवाल बड़ा सिंपल है। भाई
What business should I do? I am saying that this is
क्या बिनेस करूं? मैं ये बोल रहा हूं जो
You said that business locus of control has
आपने बोला दैट बिजनेस लोकस ऑफ कंट्रोल हैज़
To be with you. which I read from the Gita
टू बी विद इन यू। जो मैंने गीता का
Gave an example. Not this is Trudy. We
एग्जांपल दिया। नॉट ये ट्रडी है। हम
The trend has got nothing to do if it doesn't
ट्रेंड हैज़ गॉट नथिंग टू डू इफ इट इज डज
Does not resonate with you. it has to be an
नॉट रेजोनेट विद यू। इट हैज़ टू बी एन
Infatuation.
इनफचुएशन।
You have to be 24 by saying in love with it. And
यू हैव टू बी 24 बाय से इन लव विद इट। और
If that idea hasn't occurred to you, brother.
अगर वो आईडिया आपको नहीं आया है ना तो भाई
Get your job done quietly. we like i attended
चुपचाप नौकरी कर लो। हम लाइक आई अटेंडेड
You know a book talk by some author. You Know. So
यू नो अ बुक टॉक बाय सम ऑथर। यू नो। सो
this guy was asking this question that sir
दिस गाय वाज़ आस्किंग दिस क्वेश्चन कि सर
I want to do business, but I don't understand
मैं बिज़नेस तो करना चाहता हूं पर मुझे समझ
I am unable to understand what to do. So he said
नहीं आ रहा मैं क्या करूं। तो उसने कहा
Son, get a job. Sir what is this answer?
बेटा नौकरी करो। सर यह क्या जवाब हुआ?
When a son falls in love with a girl, he says
कहता है बेटा जब लड़की से प्यार होता है
no the girl is in love with the boy
ना या लड़की को लड़के से प्यार होता है
Don't take advice. I can't live for you
एडवाइस नहीं लेते। मैं जी नहीं सकता तेरे
No matter how much the world opposes me, I will live
बिना दुनिया कितना भी अपोज करे आई विल लिव
With you. It is live in today's time. Our
विद यू। आज के टाइम में लिव है। हमारे
There is a wedding on time. That idea didn't come
टाइम में शादी है। वो आईडिया ही नहीं आया
You should wait brother.
आपको तो वेट कर लो भाई यार।
It won't happen with trend. hum it is a wrong
ट्रेंड से नहीं होगा। हम इट इज अ रॉन्ग
Approach to start with. let me twist a
अप्रोच टू स्टार्ट विद। लेट मी ट्विस्ट अ
Question. So the big business stories would have been
क्वेश्चन। तो जो बड़े बिजनेस स्टोरीज होते
are just the beginning of those stories
हैं उन कहानियों के जस्ट शुरुआत से पहले
What happens? Ok. how know? how do you
क्या होता है? ओके। कैसे पता? हाउ डू यू
sniff out that yes this will be a good
स्निफ आउट कि हां दिस विल बी अ गुड
Business? So look, this is a very good question.
बिज़नेस? सो देखो ये बड़ा अच्छा सवाल है
Yours. Do you know what has happened many times?
आपका। कई बार पता है क्या हुआ है?
It is accidental.
एक्सीडेंटल है।
which have become big businesses many times
जो बड़े-बड़े बिज़नेस बने हैं ना कई बार तो
Just a stroke of luck or accidental.
जस्ट स्ट्रोक ऑफ लक या एक्सीडेंटल है।
Look, you are calling it accidental. my mind
देखो आप एक्सीडेंटल कह रहे हो। मेरे दिमाग
I feel that this is the result of friction. Ok?
में आई फील ये घिसाई का नतीजा है। ठीक है?
That can also be true. Yes. means that which
दैट कैन आल्सो बी ट्रू। यस। मतलब कि जो
I got it and started from somewhere
मिला उसी में स्टार्ट कर दिया एंड कहीं से
began. Just started trading. As
शुरू किया। ट्रेडिंग ही शुरू कर दी। जैसे
You said get ready brother, I got three for ₹2
आपने बोला रेडी चल भाई ₹2 की मिली तीन में
If I sold it or got three for two then it was too much.
बेची या दो की मिली तीन तो ज्यादा हो गया।
Sold it for Rs. 2.25. So I started from there.
सवा दो में बेची। सो वहां से शुरू किया।
So the answer to your question is look at the
सो आंसर टू योर क्वेश्चन इज़ लुक एट द
Trends and Look at What You Bring to the
ट्रेंड्स एंड लुक एट व्हाट यू ब्रिंग टू द
Table. his match
टेबल। उसका मैच
end interest
एंड इंटरेस्ट
Capability or skill set and potential
कैपेबिलिटी या स्किल सेट एंड पोटेंशियल
Its match and monetization then make a
इसका मैच एंड मोनेटाइजेशन देन मेक अ
Business plan. Got it. of the next chapter
बिज़नेस प्लान। गॉट इट। अगले चैप्टर की
Before I begin I would like to say that
शुरुआत करने से पहले मैं यह कहना चाहूंगा
that I thought we would talk about something relevant
कि आई थॉट वी विल टॉक अबाउट रेलेवेंट
Industries in the following chapter that these
इंडस्ट्रीज इन द फॉलोइंग चैप्टर कि ये जो
these are boring businesses sir which are the
बोरिंग बिनेसेस होते हैं सर व्हिच आर द
Actual Boring Businesses Where High
एक्चुअल बोरिंग बिज़नेसेस जहां हाई
There is potential. But because you said all this
पोटेंशियल है। पर क्योंकि आपने ये सब कहा
About finding your own rhythm before you
अबाउट फाइंडिंग योर ओन रिदमम बिफोर यू
Find the Business You Want to Do. A
फाइंड द बिज़नेस यू मेंट टू डू। अ उसी
Let's talk about finding rhythm.
रिदमम फाइंडिंग के बारे में बात करते हैं।
So in the next chapter we are going to talk
इसलिए अगले चैप्टर में वी आर गोइंग टू टॉक
About Personal Systems That Age 22 to Assume
अबाउट पर्सनल सिस्टम्स कि ऐज 22 से मान लो
What should be done till 30? Let's Map
30 तक भी क्या-क्या करना चाहिए? लेट्स मैप
That's through some points. so let's begin
दैट आउट थ्रू सम पॉइंट्स। सो लेट्स बिगिन
The New Chapter. So what to do from 22 to 30
द न्यू चैप्टर। सो 22 टू 30 से क्या करना
Needed? yes if you want to do a job we
चाहिए? जी अगर आप जॉब करना चाहते हो हम
Again whatever we are discussing is job
अगेन हम जो भी डिस्कशन कर रहे हैं जॉब
Versus Business. Right? Yes yes. If you job
वर्सेस बिनेस। राइट? जी जी। अगर आप जॉब
Do you want to be successful in this country?
करना चाहते हो इस देश में कामयाब होने के
For this, one will have to crack a competition. Any
लिए एक कंपटीशन तो क्रैक करना पड़ेगा। कोई
Do one after 12th, IIT
भी एक कर लो 12वीं के बाद कर लो, आईआईटी
do it, do medical, do it after graduation
कर लो, मेडिकल कर लो, ग्रेजुएशन के बाद कर
Take. You know you get my point. so you have to
लो। यू नो यू गेट माय पॉइंट। सो यू हैव टू
From cracking UPSC, from CA to U
क्रैक यूपीएससी से लेके, सीए से लेके यू
Have to crack one competition to do well in a
हैव टू क्रैक वन कॉम्पटीशन टू डू वेल इन अ
Job. Like a competitive exam.
जॉब। लाइक अ कॉम्पिटिटिव एग्जाम।
Competitive exam. it can be anyone
कॉम्पिटिटिव एग्जाम। इट कैन बी एनी
Competitive. I am saying it could be for a
कॉम्पिटिटिव। आई एम सेइंग इट कुड बी फॉर अ
Job and n Education. I suppose you crack
जॉब और एन एजुकेशन। हम सपोज यू क्रैक
IIT, u crack IM and u crack CA and
आईआईटी, यू कैक आईएम और यू क्रैक सीए और
you crack medical and architecture and there
यू क्रैक मेडिकल और आर्किटेक्चर और देयर
so many other things the nift there is
सो मेनी अदर थिंग्स दे निफ्ट देयर इज़
NID THERE IS LAW. At first, only
एनआईडी देयर इज़ लॉ। पहले तो सिर्फ
The engineer was a doctor. There are many. One
इंजीनियर डॉक्टर था। बहुत सारे हैं। एक
I will have to crack the exam brother. and steve
एग्जाम तो क्रैक करना पड़ेगा भाई। और स्टीव
The story of jobs and college dropouts
जॉब्स एंड कॉलेज ड्रॉप आउट वाली जो कहानी
Right, delete it. This is the most ruined
है ना उसको मिटा दो। ये सबसे जो बर्बाद
These are kids who drop out of college
हुए हैं बच्चे ये जो कॉलेज ड्रॉप आउट
it's syndrome again you're taking an
सिंड्रोम है ना अगेन यू आर टेकिंग एन
Outlier exception s the rule.
आउटलाइयर एक्सेप्शन एस द रूल।
An outlier and exception cannot be the
एन आउटलाइयर एंड एक्सेप्शन कैन नॉट बी द
Rule brother. Or so that's my first point.
रूल भाई। या सो दैट इज माय फर्स्ट पॉइंट।
Get your education base right. have this much muscle
गेट योर एजुकेशन बेस राइट। हैव दिस मच मसल
power that even if I don't do business
पावर कि अगर मैं बिजनेस नहीं भी करूं आई
Will live a lifestyle as good and as near as possible
विल लिव अ लाइफस्टाइल एज गुड और नियरली एज
Good as a middle scale businessman. Dude I
गुड एज अ मिडिल स्केल बिज़नेसमैन। यार मैं
I would also like to say one small thing. please 32
भी एक छोटी सी चीज कहना चाहूंगा। प्लीज 32
A Fairly Young As A Business Owner. I have this
अ फेयरली यंग एस अ बिज़नेस ओनर। मैंने ये
I noticed that teammates who had education
नोटिस किया है कि जिन टीममेट्स ने एजुकेशन
Haven't completed vs. teammates
कंप्लीट नहीं करी है वर्सेस जिन टीममेट्स
has completed education it is always the
ने एजुकेशन कंप्लीट करी है इट्स ऑलवेज द
once I completed the education which was done by grinding and
वंस हु कंप्लीटेड दी एजुकेशन जो घिसाई और
We can do more. they don't let go of the
ज्यादा कर सकते हैं। दे डोंट लेट गो ऑफ द
Ball When the Ball Becomes Difficult to Because
बॉल व्हेन द बॉल बिकम्स डिफिकल्ट टू बिकॉज़
They had the religion power. Yes. that one
दे हैड द रेिलियंस पावर। हां। वो एक
Education builds resilience
रेज़िलियंस बिल्ड हो जाता है एजुकेशन
By completing it. choose a course you enjoy but
कंप्लीट करने से। चूज़ अ कोर्स यू एंजॉय बट
Get it complete. don't be in the zone of
गेट इट कंप्लीट। डोंट बी इन द ज़ोन ऑफ़
Dropping out. That's my personal opinion.
ड्रॉपिंग आउट। दैट्स माय पर्सनल ओपिनियन।
Very Rarely Drop Out Success Stories
बहुत रेयरली ड्रॉप आउट सक्सेस स्टोरीज
They happen in India. Even as a young person,
होते हैं भारत में। इवन एज अ यंग पर्सन,
I am very against this concept of
आई एम वेरी अगेंस्ट दिस कॉन्सेप्ट ऑफ़
Dropping out. And my risk appetite
ड्रॉपिंग आउट। एंड मेरी रिस्क एपिटाइट
It is very big. Still, I am saying this.
बहुत बड़ी है। फिर भी मैं ये कह रहा हूं।
Based on what we have seen over the last 10
बेस्ड ऑन व्हाट वी हैव सीन ओवर द लास्ट 10
Years. Now please go answer. Ok? So
इयर्स। नाउ प्लीज गो आंसर। ठीक है? सो
First thing is, you are doing a job. consider yourself worthy of this
फर्स्ट इज़ जॉब कर रहे हो। अपने को इस लायक
Make sure you earn enough money. so that you have a
बनाओ कि यू अर्न एनफ मनी। सो दैट यू हैव अ
Decent lifestyle. almost as good as a
डिसेंट लाइफस्टाइल। ऑलमोस्ट एज गुड एज अ
Middle scale business. I'm not a big
मिडिल स्केल बिज़ने। आई एम नॉट अ बिग
Industrist. Seconds, get down to business.
इंडस्ट्रिस्ट। सेकंड आ जाओ बिज़नेस में।
If you want to do business then first you should
अगर आपको बिजनेस करना है तो पहले यू शुड
first know what i want to do which has
फर्स्ट नो व्हाट आई वांट टू डू व्हिच हैज़
The Potential and Make a Product Market
द पोटेंशियल एंड मेक अ प्रोडक्ट मार्केट
Fit Hum There is a science behind the product
फिट हम देयर इज़ अ साइंस बिहाइंड प्रोडक्ट
Market Fit Right Product Market Fit
मार्केट फिट राइट प्रोडक्ट मार्केट फिट
You will do a feasibility study and create cash flow
करोगे फिजिबिलिटी स्टडी बनाओगे कैश फ्लो
You will do the analysis and make an investment plan
एनालिसिस करोगे इन्वेस्टमेंट प्लान बनाओगे
and while you're working you know what you make
एंड व्हाइल यू आर वर्किंग यू नो यू मेक
that's the plan and if you have a family and
दैट प्लान एंड इफ यू हैव अ फैमिली और
Somebody to Support You or You Can Raise Funds
समबडी टू सपोर्ट यू और यू कैन रेज फंड्स
from the market you know either way that
फ्रॉम द मार्केट यू नो आइदर वे दैट
Equity Venture Cap Make a Proposal and Then
इक्विटी वेंचर कैप मेक अ प्रपोजल एंड देन
Jump into it. we so this is the very very
जंप इनू इट। हम सो दिस इज द वेरी वेरी
Simple way to navigate it for that job and
सिंपल वे टू नेविगेट इट दैट जॉब के लिए और
A concrete business plan for your business
बिनेस के लिए एक कंक्रीट बिज़नेस प्लान
Should be. we are ok you are business oriented
होना चाहिए। हम ओके आपने बिजनेस ओरिएंटेड
Personal guidelines are given from 22 to 30.
पर्सनल गाइडलाइंस दी है फ्रॉम 22 टू 30।
I would like to give you some human trade guidelines
मैं कुछ-कुछ ह्यूमन ट्रेड गाइडलाइंस देना
I would like to A first of all five days of jam
चाहूंगा। अ फर्स्ट ऑफ़ ऑल पांच दिन जम के
Do the rubbing. If possible, six days a week. A
घिसाई करो। हो सके तो छ दिन इन अ वीक। अ
Your own breaks, manage your own mind
खुद के ब्रेक्स, खुद के दिमाग को मैनेज
do it. Manage your own burnouts
करो। खुद के बर्न आउट्स को मैनेज करो
etc. but at the same time be very knowledgeable
वगैरह। बट एट द सेम टाइम बी वेरी नॉलेज
Seeing in this face. If it is not known that
सीकिंग इन दिस फेस। अगर यह पता नहीं कि
Which business should I enter or not?
कौन से बिज़नेस में घुसना चाहिए या बिज़नेस
Listen to the podcast to see how it is done. End
कैसे करते हैं तो पॉडकास्ट सुनो। एंड
Find secondhand mentors. and Charap Mentors
सेकंडली मेंटर्स ढूंढ लो। और चारप मेंटर्स
Should be. just to learn, just to learn
होने चाहिए। जस्ट टू लर्न, जस्ट टू लर्न
About how the world works. and then ask
अबाउट हाउ द वर्ल्ड वर्क्स। एंड देन आस्क
The Write Questions. If only that was done
द राइट क्वेश्चंस। अगर बस इतना ही कर लिया
And if the same mentors saw that this
और अगर वही मेंटर्स ने देखा कि यार यह
kid works hard that's half the battle one
बच्चा मेहनत करता है दैट्स हाफ द बैटल वन
Because then they will guide you in detail that he
बिकॉज़ देन दे विल गाइड यू इन डिटेल दैट हे
you can start something like this a lot
यू कैन स्टार्ट समथिंग लाइक दिस अ बहुतों
How to start agency business nowadays
की शुरुआत ना आजकल एजेंसी बिज़नेस
Freelancing business is a service business
फ्रीलांसिंग बिज़नेस सर्विस बिज़नेस से होती
and i think that's fine you learn the
है एंड आई थिंक दैट्स फाइन यू लर्न द
Basics you learn how to play the game then
बेसिक्स यू लर्न हाउ टू प्ले द गेम फिर
After that, after a certain point, you will learn by yourself.
उसके बाद एक पॉइंट के बाद खुद से आप सीख
Log through your own network through your own
लोगे थ्रू योर ओन नेटवर्क थ्रू योर ओन
This product is also good for business associates
बिज़नेस एसोसिएट्स कि अच्छा ये प्रोडक्ट भी
We can start I think this is so much
स्टार्ट कर सकते हैं आई थिंक ये इतना इतना
You have said an important thing. maybe the people
इंपॉर्टेंट चीज आपने बोली है। शायद लोगों
Doesn't even know the meaning of mentor. and i can
को मेंटर का मतलब ही नहीं पता। एंड आई कैन
tell you ranvir people of me as you know who
टेल यू रणवीर पीपल ऑफ़ माय एज यू नो हु
The sorts of corporate lives we live are more
सॉर्ट ऑफ़ लिव्ड द कॉर्पोरेट लाइफ आर मोर
Then happy to give there time. we this is the
देन हैप्पी टू गिव देर टाइम। हम दिस इज द
The Only Way We Can Give Back to Society How Much
ओनली वे वी कैन गिव बैक टू सोसाइटी हाउ मच
We have got it. hmm so finding mentors is a big deal
वी हैव गॉट। हम्म सो मेंटर्स ढूंढना बहुत
It is necessary. It will take hard work. and important thing
जरूरी है। मेहनत लगेगी। और इंपॉर्टेंट चीज
This is someone who has never done business with you
ये है जिसने कभी बिज़नेस नहीं किया उससे आप
Get business advice. and who ever got a job
बिज़नेस एडवाइस ले लो। और जिसने कभी नौकरी
You did not do that, you are taking job advice from him
नहीं करी उससे आप नौकरी की एडवाइस ले रहे
yes. So, the problem is within you. Pick the Right
हो। तो आपके अंदर प्रॉब्लम है। पिक द राइट
Mentor. you get my point or you go to surgery
मेंटर। यू गेट माय पॉइंट या आप सर्जरी
If you are not going to get it done by an engineer then right
इंजीनियर से तो नहीं कराओगे ना तो राइट
Grab a mentor and go proactively
मेंटर पकड़ो ना और प्रोएक्टिवली जाओ एंड
people will be happy to give time ok
पीपल विल बी हैप्पी टू गिव टाइम ओके
Moving On To Chapter Four Let's Talk About
मूविंग ऑन टू चैप्टर फोर लेट्स टॉक अबाउट
Relevant Industries as stated in India
रेलेवेंट इंडस्ट्रीज जैसे कि भारत में कहा
It is said that boring businesses make the most
जाता है कि बोरिंग बिज़नेसेस मेक द मोस्ट
Money because this is a bit of a family business
मनी क्योंकि ये थोड़ा सा एक फैमिली बिज़नेस
It is special. Right?
स्पेशल है। राइट?
I have noticed that family businesses are in
आई हैव नोटिस कि फैमिली बिनेसेस इन्हीं
Flourish in boring domains. Fair
बोरिंग डोमेनस में फ्लोरिश करते हैं। फेयर
Two is absolutely fine. So boring India
टू से बिल्कुल ठीक है। तो भारत के बोरिंग
What are the business sectors? Look, tell me this
बिजनेस सेक्टर्स कौन से हैं? देखो ये बताओ
Let's start from the beginning and talk about today.
पहले से चलते हैं और आज की बात करते हैं।
Sure, the sectors which are booming today
श्योर आज की तारीख में जो सेक्टर्स बूम कर
have been. Let's say if we go a little bit earlier
रहे हैं। लेट्स से अगर हम थोड़ा सा पहले
If we go then it will be much easier. Auto Auto
चलें तो इट विल बी मच ईज़ियर। ऑटो ऑटो
components related if you look at the way the
कंपोनेंट्स रिलेटेड अगर आप देखो द वे द
Companies have become multi-billion dollar
कंपनीज़ हैव बिकम मल्टी बिलियन डॉलर
Enterprises I mean before liberalisation
एंटरप्राइजेस आई मीन बिफोर लिबरलाइजेशन
you know what kind of cars we had in this
यू नो व्हाट काइंड ऑफ़ कार्स वी हैड इन दिस
country right so one is anything to do with
कंट्री राइट सो वन इज़ एनीथिंग टू डू विद
Manufacturing with in manufacturing
मैन्युफैक्चरिंग विद इन मैन्युफैक्चरिंग
Auto Kind of Almost Like a Torch Bearer
ऑटो काइंड ऑफ़ ऑलमोस्ट लाइक अ टॉर्च बियरर
you know because liberalization happened in 91
यू नो बिकॉज़ 91 में लिबरलाइजेशन हुआ उसके
Later in 93, 94, 95, Honda, General Motors, all these
बाद 93 94 95 में Honda जनरल मोटर्स इन सब
Applied for it. At that time, people who auto
ने अप्लाई किया। उस समय जो लोग ऑटो
The way they became components
कंपोनेंट्स में आ गए दे रोट द वे बिकम
Multi Billion
मल्टी बिलियन
Dollar Enterprises. this is a paradigm i
डॉलर एंटरप्राइजेस। दिस इज अ पैराडाइम आई
M Giving. Now he is not there today. Because we
एम गिविंग। नाउ आज वो नहीं है। बिकॉज़ वी
R Moving Towards EV. Today Auto Components
आर मूविंग टुवर्ड्स ईवी। आज ऑटो कंपोनेंट
You don't have to put any money in it at all.
में बिल्कुल भी नहीं डालना है पैसा।
Components will not be saved. the engine is going
बचेंगे नहीं कंपोनेंट्स। इंजन ही जा रहा
Is. Hum there is no IC engine. now what
है। हम देयर इज़ नो आईसी इंजन। नाउ व्हाट
Is the way renewable energy.
इज द वे रिन्यूएबल एनर्जी।
Anything to do with renewable energy is a
एनीथिंग टू डू विद रिन्यूएबल एनर्जी इज अ
Sector to be in and get associated with any
सेक्टर टू बी इन एंड गेट एसोसिएटेड एनी वि
way right that is one area i will say
वे राइट दैट इज़ वन एरिया आई विल से
definitely look at okay it could be wind it
डेफिनेटली लुक एट ओके इट कुड बी विंड इट
could be solar you know it could be hydro so
कुड बी सोलर यू नो इट कुड बी हाइड्रो सो
Renewable energy is a variant to anything
रिन्यूएबल एनर्जी इज़ अ वेरीेंट टू एनीथिंग
And everything to do with ESG
एंड एवरीथिंग टू डू विद ईएसजी
Environment Environment Sustainability &
एनवायरमेंट एनवायरमेंट सस्टेनेबिलिटी एंड
Governance ESG G related anything you
गवर्नेंस ईएसजी जी रिलेटेड कुछ भी आप
You will because ESG is no longer a choice.
करोगे क्योंकि अब ईएसजी चॉइस नहीं है।
There are mandates that if I have goods from you
देयर आर मैंडेट्स कि अगर मेरे को आपसे माल
If you want to buy then you must have these compliances
खरीदना है तो आपकी यह कंप्लायंसेस होनी
Needed So ESG related is a very big deal
चाहिए। सो ईएसजी रिलेटेड इज अ वेरी बिग
business which if somebody can crack the court
बिनेस व्हिच इफ समबडी कैन क्रैक द कोर्ट
Can make multi billion dollars. We are seconds
कैन मेक मल्टी बिलियन डॉलर्स। हम सेकंड
third is you know related to again it's a
थर्ड इज़ यू नो रिलेटेड टू अगेन इट्स अ
Kind of an offshoot of ESG safety. First
काइंड ऑफ़ एन ऑफशूट ऑफ ईएसजी सेफ्टी। पहले
We didn't think that much. Wearing gloves,
हम इतना नहीं सोचते थे। ग्लव्स पहने हैं,
I am wearing a helmet. this employee safety, worker
हेलमेट पहनी है। दिस एंप्लई सेफ्टी, वर्कर
Safety has become a big industry and a
सेफ्टी हैज़ बिकम अ बिग इंडस्ट्री एंड अ
Big Business to Sensitize Specially
बिग बिज़नेस टू सेंसिटाइज स्पेशली
MSMEs. Where everything happens. Minimum Wages
एमएसएमईस। जहां सब चलता है। मिनिमम वेजेस
Even though I am not giving it, it is still going on. I Mean
नहीं दे रहा हूं तब भी चल रहा है। आई मीन
you know i have heard there are so many
यू नो आई हैव हर्ड देयर आर सो मेनी
Factories. Their sources of competition
फैक्ट्रीज़। उनके सोर्स ऑफ़ कंपेटिटिव
The advantage is that he is not paying minimum wages
एडवांटेज ये है कि मिनिमम वेज नहीं दे रहा
Am. Imagine. So safety. Next I Will
हूं। इमेजिन। सो सेफ्टी। नेक्स्ट आई विल
say is anything and everything to do with
से इज एनीथिंग एंड एवरीथिंग टू डू विद
Artificial Intelligence and Digitization.
आर्टिफिशियल इंटेलिजेंस और डिजिटाइजेशन।
And last is anything and everything to do
एंड लास्ट इज एनीथिंग एंड एवरीथिंग टू डू
With Bio and Pharmacy. Bio means bio
विद बायो और फार्मेसी। बायो मतलब बायो
Means the new developments that are taking place in
मींस जो नए-नए डेवलपमेंट्स हो रही हैं इन
The field of biology like anti-aging is
द फील्ड ऑफ बायोलॉजी लाइक एंटी एजिंग इज
One right disease is another one health related
वन राइट डिजीज इज़ अनदर वन हेल्थ रिलेटेड
Stuff is another one. so much of research is
स्टफ इज़ अनदर वन। सो लॉट ऑफ़ रिसर्च इज़
Happening at the Frontiers
हैपनिंग एट द फ्रंटियर्स
Intersection of Bio with Even Physics. You
इंटरसेक्शन ऑफ़ बायो विद इवन फिजिक्स। यू
no so i think there is a lot of development
नो सो आई थिंक देयर इज लॉट ऑफ डेवलपमेंट
Happening there that is an area and pharma
हैपनिंग देयर दैट इज एन एरिया एंड फार्मा
is there again something which i feel is continuing
इज अगेन समथिंग व्हिच आई फील इज कंटिन्यू
it will evolve there might be some disruption
इट विल इवॉल्व देयर माइट बी सम डिसररप्शन
But it's going to be there for a long time
बट इट्स गोइंग टू बी देयर फॉर अ लॉन्ग
time so the four five sectors are which i
टाइम सो दी फोर फाइव सेक्टर्स आर व्हिच आई
feel you know the end of course the last one i should
फील यू नो एंड ऑफ कोर्स लास्ट वन आई शुड
Ad Which is an offshoot of What I Said
ऐड व्हिच इज़ एन ऑफशूट ऑफ व्हाट आई सेड
Renewable Energy I Wood Say Anything
रिन्यूएबल एनर्जी आई वुड से एनीथिंग
Related to with energy because kiss will run
रिलेटेड टू विद एनर्जी क्योंकि चलेगी किस
on which one will we go and on which one is it okay
किस पे हम चलेगी किस पे ठीक है तो
Traditionally it is manufacturing
ट्रेडिशनली इट इज़ मैन्युफैक्चरिंग
Traditionally it has been manufactured but
ट्रेडिशनली इट हैज़ बीन मैन्युफैक्चरिंग बट
I'm saying manufacturing is back again
आई एम सेइंग मैन्युफैक्चरिंग इज़ अगेन
boring but any of these areas also will
बोरिंग बट एनी ऑफ़ दीज़ एरियाज आल्सो विल
Gel Well With This Generation
जेल वेल विद दिस जनरेशन
write it will not be as boring but it
राइट इट विल वोंट बी एज बोरिंग बट इट
also has a lot of potential got it. So
आल्सो हैज़ अ लॉट ऑफ़ पोटेंशियल गॉट इट। सो
Study these sectors and invest
इन सेक्टर्स को स्टडी करें, इन्वेस्ट करें
and get in through the easiest and the lowest
एंड गेट इन थ्रू द इजीिएस्ट एंड द लोएस्ट
Denomination Route in Terms of Investment
डिनॉमिनेशन रूट इन टर्म्स ऑफ इन्वेस्टमेंट
end risk. Ok? talking about this
एंड रिस्क। ओके? इसी के बारे में बात करते
Are. Let's go deeper. Ok? two additional questions
हैं। लेट्स गो डीपर। ओके? दो एडिशनल सवाल
Is. The first question is that these five-six
है। पहला सवाल है कि इन पांच-छह
How to bring profitability in industries?
इंडस्ट्रीज में प्रॉफिटेबिलिटी कैसे लाएं?
I think that's the main question. anyone should
आई थिंक दैट्स द मेन क्वेश्चन। एनीवन शुड
ask themself before thinking about
आस्क देमसेल्व बिफोर थिंकिंग अबाउट
Starting business. The second question is the game
स्टार्टिंग बिज़नेस। दूसरा सवाल है गेम
plan because not all these sectors
प्लान क्योंकि यह सारे सेक्टर्स ना थोड़े
I seem larger than life as a 22 year old
लार्जर देन लाइफ लगते हैं कि एज अ 22 ईयर
How do I suddenly install a solar panel in an old graduate?
ओल्ड ग्रेजुएट मैं सडनली सोलर पैनल कैसे
How do I understand this, look I have seen it
बनाता है ये कैसे समझूं देखो आई हैव सीन
many people who started with solar
मेनी पीपल हु स्टार्टेड विद सोलर के
Started with installation, now solar
इंस्टॉलेशन वाले से शुरू किया अब सोलर
I want to install the panel in your home
पैनल मुझे आपके घर में इंस्टॉल करना है
Do I need a plant? I am buying one
क्या मुझे प्लांट चाहिए मैं तो खरीद रहा
am I importing it from China or
हूं ना इंपोर्ट कर रहा हूं चाइना से या
Dada bought it locally, he is coming from outside.
लोकली खरीदा दादा तो बाहर से आ रहा है।
Ok? I am a contractor. Then
ठीक है? मैं तो एक कॉन्ट्रैक्टर हूं। फिर
What did that guy see? where does this item come from
उस बंदे ने क्या देखा? यह माल कहां से आ
Used to be? so he started as a contractor
रहा है? सो ही स्टार्टेड एज अ कॉन्ट्रक्टर
Just An Installation Guy At Homes. Then
जस्ट एन इंस्टॉलेशन गाय एट होम्स। फिर
What did he do? If friend comes from home
उसने क्या किया? यार घर से आया तो
Factory required. We don't think so
फैक्ट्री की जरूरत है। हम तो सोचते नहीं
At home but in the plant if my ₹1
घर में लेकिन प्लांट में अगर मेरा ₹1 पर
The units were left and then he entered the plants.
यूनिट बचे फिर वो प्लांट्स में घुस गया।
Then he started taking on bigger contracts
फिर उसने बड़े कॉन्ट्रैक्ट उठाने शुरू
Do. Then what did he say? Yaar Main Panels
करे। फिर उसने क्या बोला? यार मैं पैनल्स
Should I start making it or trading?
ही बनाने शुरू कर देता हूं या ट्रेडिंग
Karani then started manufacturing again. Now
करनी फिर मैन्युफैक्चरिंग शुरू कर दी। नाउ
He has become very big. you understand?
ही हैज़ बिकम वेरी बिग। यू अंडरस्टैंड?
The contract is almost zero investment
ऑलमोस्ट जीरो इन्वेस्टमेंट है कॉन्ट्रैक्ट
Raise. So I am saying, go inside. I
उठाना। तो ये मैं कह रहा हूं कि घुसो। आई
I'm not saying you know you can become a renewal
एम नॉट सेइंग यू नो यू कैन बिकम अ रिन्यू
You know renewable energy and you can become you
यू नो रिन्यू एनर्जी और यू कैन बिकम अ यू
No start up a gigawatt of solar energy
नो स्टार्ट अप अ गीगावाट एनर्जी का सोलर
Plant. It will take time to reach there. But
प्लांट। वहां पहुंचने में टाइम लगेगा। बट
Enter the area. When you enter the solar panel
एरिया में तो घुसो। जब आप घुसे सोलर पैनल
You started walking on that path, you got a thousand
में आप उस रास्ते पर चलने लगे आपको हजार
Things came to light, all ecosystems came to light
चीजें पता चली सब इकोसिस्टम पता चला
Who is the supplier, who is the buyer and who is purchasing it
सप्लायर कौन है बायर कौन है उसके की बाइंग
What are the factors then you can start with
फैक्टर्स क्या है देन यू कैन स्टार्टली
start to scale up when you get my point
स्टार्ट टू स्केल अप यू गेट माय पॉइंट जब
Let's take your YouTube example.
जैसे आपका YouTube वाला एग्जांपल लेते हैं
like when you started how much would you have
जैसे आपने जब शुरू किया हाउ मच यू वुड हैव
Learn and relearn but if you were working in
लर्न एंड रीलर्न बट इफ यू वर वर्किंग इन
In some other fields I don't know these news
सम अदर फील्ड तो ये नए्ससेस नहीं पता पता
moving end may be 10 years back or when
चलती एंड मे बी 10 इयर्स बैक या जब
wherever you started you would never have
व्हेयरवर यू स्टार्टेड यू वुड नेवर हैव
Imagine that I will cover such a journey
इमेजिन कि यार मैं ऐसी जर्नी कवर कर लूंगा
Kya Hum So A Journey Of 1000 Steps
क्या हम सो अ जर्नी ऑफ़ 1000 स्टेप
Starts with the first step right away
स्टार्ट्स विद द फर्स्ट स्टेप राइट अ000
The mile starts with the first step
माइल स्टार्ट्स विथ द फर्स्ट स्टेप वो
have to do it. so to answer your question
करना पड़ेगा। सो टू आंसर योर क्वेश्चन
Start with the minimum investment which
स्टार्ट विद द मिनिमम इन्वेस्टमेंट व्हिच
can even be a contracting and
कैन इवन बी अ कॉन्ट्रैक्टिंग और अ
Trading and then slowly building it up. it
ट्रेडिंग एंड देन स्लोली बिल्ड इट अप। यह
How to start contracting or trading
कॉन्ट्रैक्टिंग या ट्रेडिंग कैसे स्टार्ट
We do? Just ask your friends. brother look
करते हैं? दोस्तों को ही पूछ लो। भाई देख
So I'm starting this. you my
ऐसा है मैं यह शुरू कर रहा हूं। तूने मेरे
Have to give 10 references. solar at home
को 10 रेफरेंसेस देने हैं। घर में सोलर
This is the advantage of the panel. whom shall I tell
पैनल का ये फायदा है। बता मैं किससे
Should I take a meeting? at least this friend of i
मीटिंग करूं? एटलीस्ट दिस फ्रेंड ऑफ़ आई
Mind that's how he started. Brother I
माइंड दैट्स हाउ ही स्टार्टेड। भाई मैं
I am starting a business. did a lot of job
बिज़नेस शुरू कर रहा हूं। जॉब कर ली बहुत
Year. Rajeev, I need 10 references and 10 each
साल। राजीव 10 रेफरेंसेस चाहिए और 10-10
Asked people and educated them. from home
लोगों से पूछा और उनको एजुकेट किया। घर से
Started and then he went to the factory.
शुरू किया एंड देन ही वेंट टू द फैक्ट्री।
So it will happen by your network. as we are
सो इट विल हैपन बाय योर नेटवर्क। हम जैसे
you know marwadi community, gujarati
यू नो मारवाड़ी कम्युनिटी, गुजराती
community, jain community have a lot of
कम्युनिटी, जैन कम्युनिटी हैव अ लॉट ऑफ
Support. so you have to see we are the network
सपोर्ट। सो यू हैव टू सी वि इज द नेटवर्क
you can tap into whoever you ask bro
यू कैन टैप इंटू कि जिससे आप पूछो भाई
If you need help then say come on friend, let's go
हेल्प चाहिए तो कह अरे आ ना यार बोले चले
Friend, stop picking up the phone. This is how it is today
यार फोन उठाना बंद कर दो। ऐसे है आज की
The world is like this. Tell someone your work
दुनिया ऐसी है। आप किसी को काम बताओ आपका
He will stop picking up the phone. You tell someone friend
फोन उठाना छोड़ देगा। आप किसी को बोलो यार
He needs to be trained and given a job.
इसकी ट्रेनिंग लगवानी है, जॉब लगवानी है।
That is the easiest way he will not block you.
दैट इज द इज़िएस्ट वे ही विल नॉट ब्लॉक यू।
But he will start ignoring you. As such
बट ही विल स्टार्ट इग्नोरिंग यू। ऐसा
No network required. so to answer your
नेटवर्क नहीं चाहिए। सो टू आंसर योर
Questions Look at Your Network People Who Want
क्वेश्चन लुक एट योर नेटवर्क पीपल हु वांट
To you to do well seek out support that
टू यू टू डू वेल सीक आउट देर सपोर्ट कि
Boss, I am doing this, tell me how can you help me
बॉस ये कर रहा हूं बताओ मेरी क्या हेल्प
you can easily got it okay i think this is
कर सकते हो इजी गॉट इट ओके आई थिंक दिस इज
a variant point where we should bring up
अ वेरीेंट पॉइंट वेयर वी शुड ब्रिंग अप
supply chain supply chain means what sir ok
सप्लाई चेन सप्लाई चेन मतलब क्या सर ठीक
Please explain it easily, this is a very big business
है आसानी से समझाइए ये बहुत की बिनेस
Career loan is a very important thing, see
करियर की लोन बहुत ही जरूरी चीज है देखो
There are two types of things in the supply chain
सप्लाई चेन में ना दो तरीके की चीजें होती
Inbound and Outbound Supply Chain
है इनबाउंड एंड आउटबाउंड सप्लाई चेन
What is it basically? what does supply chain mean
बेसिकली क्या है? सप्लाई चेन का मतलब क्या
Is? things to make any goods
है? किसी भी माल को बनाने के लिए चीजें
It seems so. to make things happen
लगती हैं। चीजें लगने के लिए चीजों को आना
It happens. Ok? so if I get a product
होता है। ओके? सो मुझे अगर एक प्रोडक्ट
Have to make it. Let's get me a washing machine
बनाना है। लेट्स से मुझे एक वाशिंग मशीन
Have to make it. It has x number of parts.
बनानी है। उसमें x नंबर ऑफ पार्ट्स हैं।
may be those parts are coming from various
मे बी दोज़ पार्ट्स आर कमिंग फ्रॉम वेरियस
Geographies. Right? those geographies can
ज्योग्राफीस। राइट? दोज़ ज्योग्राफीज़ कैन
be with in india can be outside of
बी विद इन इंडिया कैन बी आउटसाइड ऑफ
India. So one is an inbound logistics.
इंडिया। सो वन इज अ इनबाउंड लॉजिस्टिक्स।
Ok? Like a part of me has to come from China.
ओके? जैसे मेरा एक पार्ट चाइना से आना है।
One part has to come from Europe. one part russia
एक पार्ट यूरोप से आना है। एक पार्ट रशिया
Have to come from. Everything of mine is ready. One
से आना है। मेरा सब कुछ रेडी हो गया। एक
My part got stuck. something with china
पार्ट मेरा अटक गया। चाइना के साथ कुछ
The problem started. We are a live example
प्रॉब्लम शुरू हो गई। हम ये लाइव एग्जांपल
Is. Now I am not the kind of person who can use a washing machine
है। अब मैं ऐसा तो नहीं है कि वाशिंग मशीन
Sir, it is not just a roller. take the rest
सर वो सिर्फ रोलर नहीं है। बाकी चीज ले
Go. So it is important to understand this in the supply chain
जाओ। सो सप्लाई चेन में यह समझना जरूरी है
that's all the parts
दैट ऑल दी पार्ट्स
of the entire system from the time that
ऑफ द एंटायर सिस्टम फ्रॉम द टाइम दैट
Placing a parts order is a great help to that supplier.
पार्ट कम्स ऑर्डर देना उस सप्लायर की क्या
Is there capacity? Is that capacity in this timeline?
कैपेसिटी है क्या वो कैपेसिटी इस टाइमलाइन
I will probably meet everyone
में मीट करेगी हो सकता है सबकी
synchronize he is saying sir i
सिंक्रोनाइज करना वो बोल रहा है सर मैं
I will give you the goods, call me again on 10th June
आपको माल दे दूंगा 10 जून को दूसरा बोल
Sir, I will give it on 10th July so what
रहा है मैं सर 10 जुलाई को दूंगा तो क्या
I will make it half and keep it aside, do you understand this point?
मैं आधी बना के रख दूं ये पॉइंट समझ में आ
yes it is in very crude language i understood
रहा है यस बड़ी क्रूड भाषा में मैं समझा
I have been. Over simplified. so this is
रहा हूं। ओवर सिंपलीफाइड। सो दिस इज
Inbound Logistics to Make Something. It
इनबाउंड लॉजिस्टिक्स टू मेक समथिंग। इट
Needs x number of parts. those parts
नीड्स एक्स नंबर ऑफ पार्ट्स। दोज़ पार्ट
should reach at one point in time so that i
शुड रीच एट वन पॉइंट इन टाइम सो दैट आई
Can plan my manufacturing line. This
कैन प्लान माय मैन्युफैक्चरिंग लाइन। दिस
This is part A. then there is outbound
इज पार्ट ए। देन देयर इज़ आउटबाउंड
Logistics.
लॉजिस्टिक्स।
After I have made the goods, I will give it to her
मैंने जब माल बना दिया उसके बाद मैं उसको
I am transporting it. what's in it
ट्रांसपोर्ट कर रहा हूं। उसमें क्या-क्या
Is there a complication? The most important thing is
कॉम्प्लिकेशन है? सबसे इंपॉर्टेंट चीज है
Time of delivery.
टाइम ऑफ डिलीवरी।
Logistics cost. what is the right board
लॉजिस्टिक्स कॉस्ट। व्हाट इज द राइट बोर्ड
to you know should i put it on a truck, should i
टू यू नो शुड आई पुट इट ऑन अ ट्रक, शुड आई
Put it on a you know the trailer? should i send
पुट इट ऑन अ यू नो द ट्रेलर? शुड आई सेंड
Is it by train? should i if it is being
इट बाय ट्रेन? शुड आई इफ इट इज़ बीइंग
Exported which is the nearest port.
एक्सपोर्टेड व्हिच इज द नियरेस्ट पोर्ट।
Should I send it to that port by train or bus?
उस पोर्ट पे मैं ट्रेन से भेजूं या बस से
should I send it? Should I send it by truck or by trailer?
भेजूं? ट्रक से भेजूं, ट्रेलर से भेजूं?
Then transit is a very important thing
देन बहुत इंपॉर्टेंट चीज है ट्रांजिट
Damages. How should the packing be? Fragile
डैमेजेस। पैकिंग कैसी होनी चाहिए? फ्रजाइल
What is it? How fragile is it? The dent will come
है क्या? कितना फ्रजाइल है? डेंट आ जाएगा
What? This is a basic supply chain. But
क्या? यह एक बेसिक सप्लाई चेन है। बट
What does it contain? where is the problem in that
इसमें क्या होता है? दिक्कत इसमें कहां
does it come? as i give you that example chain is
आती है? एज आई गिव यू दैट एग्जांपल चेन इज
Strong as the Weakest Link.
स्ट्रांग एस द वीकेस्ट लिंक।
If even a single part does not arrive on time then
एक भी पार्ट अगर नहीं आया उस टाइम पर तो
Your assembly line will stop. So if
आपकी असेंबली लाइन रुक जाएगी। तो अगर
plant of car or any other car stopped working
प्लांट बंद हो गया कार का या किसी भी
Understand the factory today, two, three or four people
फैक्ट्री का आज समझ लो दो तीन चार लोगों
And I lost my job.
की तो नौकरी गई।
It is like murder.
इट इज लाइक मर्डर।
So that is supply chain management. We Butt I
सो दैट इज सप्लाई चेन मैनेजमेंट। हम बट आई
only explain the part of timing match,
ओनली एक्सप्लेन द पार्ट ऑफ टाइमिंग मैच,
Cost, Quality, Inbound Quality. My
कॉस्ट, क्वालिटी, इनबाउंड क्वालिटी। मेरा
The quality of the product is dependent on
क्वालिटी ऑफ द प्रोडक्ट इज़ डिपेंडेंट ऑन
My inbound quality. how to check that
मेरी इनबाउंड क्वालिटी। वो कैसे चेक कर
had been? What is its mechanism?
रहे हो? उसका क्या मैकेनिज्म है?
How will the rejections happen? this whole piece
रिजेक्शंस कैसे होंगी? दिस होल पीस
Sounds boring. the money is in us
साउंड्स बोरिंग। पैसा इसी में है हम
Because trades are now mine and my circle
क्योंकि ट्रेड अब मेरे एक मेरे हैं सर्कल
me u know de sale construction de sale
में यू नो दे सेल कंस्ट्रक्शन दे सेल
Tiles Now understand them in tiles
टाइल्स अब टाइल्स में उन्होंने समझ लो
1 lakh square feet showroom built ok
1 लाख स्क्वायर फुट का शोरूम बना लिया ठीक
Made in Faridabad with let's
है लेट्स से फरीदाबाद में बना लिया
Now what is their value addition in that
नाउ उसमें उनका क्या वैल्यू एडिशन है वो
Mall in Tiles Showroom in Faridabad
माल मैं टाइल्स फरीदाबाद के शोरूम में
I will see, maybe I will meet the person from Delhi
देखूंगा हो सकता है मैं दिल्ली वाले से
Let me go and negotiate. Butt Manufacturing
जाके नेगोशिएट कर लूं। बट मैन्युफैक्चरिंग
I believe you have that competitive advantage. Are you
में यू हैव दैट कंपेटिटिव एडवांटेज। आर यू
Getting my peace? Trading and You Know the Money
गेटिंग माय पीस? ट्रेडिंग एंड यू नो द मनी
and the margins are always going to be
एंड द मार्जिनस आर ऑलवेज गोइंग टू बी
larger because you have more leverage in
लार्जर बिकॉज़ यू हैव मोर लिवरेज इन
Manufacturing. in trading you are kind
मैन्युफैक्चरिंग। इन ट्रेडिंग यू आर काइंड
Of you know compressed. hmm means trading
ऑफ़ यू नो कंप्रेस्ड। हम्म मतलब ट्रेडिंग
is a good starting point. it's a very
इज अ गुड स्टार्टिंग पॉइंट। इट्स अ वेरी
Good starting point. because less capital
गुड स्टार्टिंग पॉइंट। बिकॉज़ कम कैपिटल
Is. But again, what are you trading? His
है। बट अगेन ट्रेडिंग किस चीज की? उसके
What kind of retail space is required for this? Online Tax
लिए कैसा रिटेल स्पेस चाहिए? ऑनलाइन कर
You can, that's a good thing. but if you have a
सकते हो अच्छी बात है। बट अगर आपको एक
If you want a fancy place then it's not a good
फैंसी जगह चाहिए तो फिर इट्स नॉट अ गुड
Point to start with. like you gov
पॉइंट टू स्टार्ट विद। लाइक यू गव
Example of cloud kitchen vs a fancy one
एग्जांपल ऑफ क्लाउड किचन वर्सेस अ फैंसी
restaurant. Got it. Ok. Summarize a little
रेस्टोरेंट। गॉट इट। ओके। थोड़ा सा समराइज
I would like to do it. basically if it's boring
करना चाहूंगा। बेसिकली अगर ये बोरिंग
If you want to enter business then consider supply chain
बिज़नेसेस में घुसना है तो सप्लाई चेन
Management has to be learnt. Supply Chain
मैनेजमेंट सीखनी ही होगी। सप्लाई चेन
If you want to learn management then my personal advice
मैनेजमेंट सीखनी है तो मेरी पर्सनल एडवाइस
This is to find mentors and learn AI
ये है कि मेंटर्स ढूंढ लो और एआई का
Use it. At least your learning speed
इस्तेमाल करो। एटलीस्ट योर लर्निंग स्पीड
will increase but the fastest way to increase
विल इंक्रीस बट द फास्टेस्ट वे टू इंक्रीस
Learning speed is to apply yourself.
लर्निंग स्पीड इज टू अप्लाई योरसेल्फ।
Absolutely. So you are saying that trading off
बिल्कुल। तो आप कह रहे हो कि ट्रेडिंग ऑफ
a part of the supply chain that identifies
अ पार्ट ऑफ द सप्लाई चेन वो आइडेंटिफाई
Do it and get in there. Absolutely. that's why
करो और वहां घुसो। बिल्कुल। दैट्स व्हाई
You can begin your business career.
यू कैन बिगिन योर बिज़नेस करियर।
Exactly. then what before that part
एक्सक्ट्ली। फिर उस पार्ट के पहले क्या
what comes and what comes after that is good
आता है और बाद में क्या आता है वो अच्छे
Know from. Exactly. and at some point you
से जानो। एक्सैक्टली। एंड एट सम पॉइंट आप
You will learn yourself that yes, I am good at this thing
खुद ये सीख लोगे कि हां मैं इस चीज की
I will be able to do manufacturing. and because of that
मैन्युफैक्चरिंग कर पाऊंगा। और उस वजह से
This is part of the supply chain, this is mine
ये जो सप्लाई चेन का हिस्सा है यह मेरा तो
It just happened. In addition this is the second
अभी हो गया ही। इसके अलावा यह दूसरा
The share will be mine too. Correct. this is
हिस्सा भी मेरा हो जाएगा। करेक्ट। दिस इज
The Basic Game Plan. That is absolutely correct.
द बेसिक गेम प्लान। बिल्कुल ठीक बात है।
Ok. About A & Joe Industries
ओके। अ एंड जो इंडस्ट्रीज के बारे में
You mentioned about the five-six industries.
आपने बताया वो जो पांच छह इंडस्ट्रीज हैं
Same game plan applies across. so see if
सेम गेम प्लान अप्लाई अक्रॉस। सो देखो अगर
You go historically. Yes. We who are traders
आप हिस्टोरिकली चलो। जी। हम जो बनिया
community or the trader community
कम्युनिटी है या जो ट्रेडर कम्युनिटी है
It has been there for 2000 years. Ok? since 2000 years
2000 साल से हैं। ठीक है? 2000 साल से
Trade Lots of Traders Industrialists
ट्रेड बहुत सारे ट्रेडर्स इंडस्ट्रियलिस्ट
How to become it? Are traders just traders?
कैसे बने? क्या ट्रेडर्स ट्रेडर्स ही हैं?
Is it Marwari or Gujarati or Baniya?
क्या मारवाड़ी या गुजराती या बनिया
Are you a trader? they became got inu
ट्रेडर्स हैं? दे बिकम गॉट इनू
manufacturing but they started with
मैन्युफैक्चरिंग बट दे स्टार्टेड विद
Trading. You get my point? Yes. from the bad
ट्रेडिंग। यू गेट माय पॉइंट? यस। बुरे से
What would be bad? The stuff I bought,
बुरा क्या होगा? मैंने जो माल खरीदा है,
What you bought for ₹2 or what you bought for ₹200,
₹2 में जो खरीदा है या ₹200 में खरीदा है,
I will sell it for 180, I will sell it for 160, that much
180 में बेचूंगा, 160 में बेचूंगा, उतना
I will sell only whatever I have. So Backward
ही बेचूंगा ना जो मेरे पास है। सो बैकवर्ड
And then he did forward integration.
एंड फॉरवर्ड इंटीग्रेशन करी फिर उन्होंने।
hmm hmm because they got a foot in the door
हम्म हम्म बिकॉज़ दे गॉट अ फुट इन द डोर
I got my foot in the door, where did you understand the whole system?
फुट इन द डोर मिला पूरा सिस्टम समझा कहां
what is missing but go inside and then
पे क्या चीज कमी है उसमें घुसे और फिर
built it you can't start with the
उसको बिल्ड किया यू कांट स्टार्ट विद द
Elephant right I mean you have to start
एलीफेंट राइट आई मीन यू हैव टू स्टार्ट
Small Understand the Gaps and Then Build
स्मॉल अंडरस्टैंड द गैप्स एंड देन बिल्ड
it up how much time does it take to go
इट अप वक्त कितना लगता है इसमें टू गो
From Being a Trader to a Profitable Trader
फ्रॉम बीइंग अ ट्रेडर अ प्रॉफिटेबल ट्रेडर
To become an industrialist one generation
टू बिकमिंग एन इंडस्ट्रियलिस्ट वन जनरेशन
wow
वाव
wow even today we are saying it will take one generation
वाह आज भी आज भी हम इट विल टेक वन जनरेशन
Meaning that it would take half a generation if one
मतलब कि पौनी जनरेशन तो लग जाएगी अगर एक
I didn't feel complete when I said what it meant
पूरी नहीं लगी व्हेन आई से पूरी इट मींस
30 years of work harsh truth 15 20 years
30 इयर्स ऑफ़ वर्क कठोर सच 15 20 साल
It will not seem so easy that you become a trader today
लगेंगे इतना आसान नहीं है कि आप आज ट्रेडर
And you become completely different because your mentality is completely different
और बन जाओ बिकॉज़ मेंटालिटी पूरी डिफरेंट
Is. The game is completely different. your talking to you
है। गेम पूरी डिफरेंट है। योर टॉकिंग यू
Saying Trader Versus Industry
सेइंग ट्रेडर वर्सेस इंडस्ट्री
A huge game change in manufacturing
मैन्युफैक्चरिंग में बहुत बड़ी गेम चेंज
Is. So you can assume that for 20 years, you know
है। तो 20 साल तो आप मान कर चलो द यू नो
true transition you know it can take that
ट्रू ट्रांजिशन यू नो इट कैन टेक दैट
kind of time it can be done earlier also
काइंड ऑफ़ टाइम इट कैन बी डन अर्लियर आल्सो
But I am saying that
बट मैं ये कह रहा हूं कि
If you don't know the whole game
अगर आपको पूरी गेम नहीं पता तो
If you close your eyes and enter in a hurry
आंखें बंद करके आप जल्दबाजी में घुसोगे तो
Chances of failure will increase
चांसेस ऑफ फेलियर विल इंक्रीस
You can do it exponentially faster but
एक्सप्पोनेंशियली जल्दी कर सकते हो बट
Haste is the devil's work. Nowadays we are not one
जल्दी का काम शैतान का है। हम आजकल ना एक
Slang has become very popular. These
स्लैंग बहुत पॉपुलर बन चुका है। ये
Actually comes from the basketball world.
एक्चुअली बास्केटबॉल वर्ल्ड से आता है।
Like his name is LeBron James. He is very
लाइक उनका नाम है लिब्रॉन जेम्स। वो बहुत
He used to say this. It has now become a slang word
ये कहते थे। अभी ये स्लैंग वर्ड बन चुका
Is. The slang word is generational wealth. We
है। द स्लैंग वर्ड इज जनरेशनल वेल्थ। हम
That means that
यानी कि
Money like a dog.
कुत्ते जैसा पैसा।
But the Truth About Generational Wealth Is 20 Years Old
बट द ट्रुथ अबाउट जनरेशनल वेल्थ इज 20 साल
It seems so. Practically Speaking Minimum
लगते हैं। प्रैक्टिकली स्पीकिंग मिनिमम
Maybe 30 years. He is not ready to do any
शायद 30 साल। वो कोई रेडी नहीं है करने
To. We need it quickly because attention span
को। जल्दी चाहिए हम क्योंकि अटेंशन स्पैन
It isn't there, right? See it in everything
नहीं है ना। देखो वो हर चीज में
Same thing is happening in relationships also. Job
रिलेशनशिप्स में भी तो यही हो रहा है। जॉब
Same thing is happening in me too. means in everything
में भी तो यही हो रहा है। मतलब हर चीज में
it's happening quickly quickly quick
ये हो रहा है कि जल्दबाजी जल्दबाजी क्विक
Quickie Quickie That's Instant Gratification.
क्विक क्विक दैट इंस्टेंट ग्रेटिफिकेशन।
Brother, who will take 15 years? so what bro
भाई 15 साल कौन लगाएगा? तो भाई क्या
will you do it? Get bankrupt. we mean his
करोगे? बैंककरप्ट हो जाओ। हम मतलब उसका
The second option is this. so i wonder if you have
दूसरा ऑप्शन यह है। सो आई वंडर इफ यू हैव
Cracked the Formula. If you are trading a
क्रैक्ड द फार्मूला। अगर ट्रेडिंग अ करना
You learned a little bit better game plan
सीख गए आप और थोड़ा बहुत अच्छा गेम प्लान
Also made a for manufacturing. From
भी बना दिया अ मैन्युफैक्चरिंग के लिए। से
If you're at your five year mark. can you
इफ यू आर एट योर फाइव ईयर मार्क। कैन यू
Raise money to jump to the next level. and you
रेज मनी टू जंप टू द नेक्स्ट लेवल। ओर यू
Can but that also has to be calculated. it see
कैन बट दैट आल्सो टू बी कैलकुलेटेड। इट सी
I am saying this. the money they're giving you
मैं ये बोल रहा हूं। जो पैसा आपको दे रहे
He is taking a bet on you. Hmm. Now
हैं ही इज़ टेकिंग अ बेट ऑन यू। हम्म। नाउ
Many people who become investors, after seeing this guy
कई लोग जो इन्वेस्टर होते हैं बंदा देख के
I also apply it. I have seen like I talk
भी लगा देते हैं। आई हैव सीन लाइक आई टॉक
To these people, friend, what did you see? Business
टू दिस पीपल यार क्या देखा तूने? बिनेस
The plan was rubbish, the guy was on fire
प्लान तो बकवास था यार बंदे में फायर थी
Buddy. That bastard will do something. the plan was rubbish
यार। वो साला कुछ कर लेगा। प्लान बकवास था
The guy was right. We sleep like this too. but however
बंदा सही था। हम सो ये भी है। बट हाउएवर
If You're Wanting to Raise Money You Have to Show
इफ यू आर वांटिंग टू रेज मनी यू हैव टू शो
Some proof of concept. I am your brother
सम प्रूफ ऑफ कांसेप्ट। मैं तुझ पे भाई
Why should I believe it? what am i betting
क्यों विश्वास करूं? व्हाट एम आई बेटिंग
On? Am I betting on your idea? Am I
ऑन? एम आई बेटिंग ऑन योर आईडिया? एम आई
Betting on Your Potential and Am I Betting
बेटिंग ऑन योर पोटेंशियल और एम आई बेटिंग
On your execution capability? Any
ऑन योर एग्जीक्यूशन कैपेबिलिटी? किसी
because i have to secure my money na that
बिकॉज़ आई हैव टू सिक्योर माय मनी ना वो
It is important that you have to answer this question
जरूरी है कि यू हैव टू आंसर दिस क्वेश्चन
In your mind why should somebody invest
इन योर माइंड कि व्हाई शुड समबडी इन्वेस्ट
That's Money on Me and the Biggest Myth Vi
दैट मनी ऑन मी एंड द बिगेस्ट मिथ वि
The youngster's idea was great. The idea of
यंगस्टर आईडिया बड़ा अच्छा था। आईडिया के
There is no money. execution money
कोई पैसे नहीं होते। एग्जीक्यूशन के पैसे
Execution Your Capability Your Team Your
एक्सजीक्यूशन योर कैपेबिलिटी योर टीम योर
fire in the belly bl bl bl the sigma of
फायर इन द बेली ब्ल ब्ल ब्ल द सिग्मा ऑफ़
All that we know in this chapter, haven't you?
ऑल दैट हम पता है इस चैप्टर में ना आपने
Golden nuggets have been given. if someone likes
गोल्डन नगेट्स दिए हैं। लाइक अगर किसी ने
I would have said this at age 22
मुझे ये एट एज 22 कहा होता आई वुड हैव सेड
thank you sir but the truth is of this chapter
थैंक यू सर बट द ट्रुथ इज़ इस चैप्टर के
The chapters that came earlier are more important
पहले जो चैप्टर्स आए थे वो ज्यादा जरूरी
is for the audience to learn to handle
है ऑडियंस के लिए कि लर्न टू हैंडल
Yourself. Learn to handle your finances.
योरसेल्फ। लर्न टू हैंडल योर फाइनेंससेस।
Learn to handle growing in your career.
लर्न टू हैंडल ग्रोइंग इन योर करियर।
So we will move on to the next chapter.
इसलिए वी विल मूव ऑन टू द नेक्स्ट चैप्टर।
Ok? which is also a small case study but at the
ओके? जो छोटी सी केस स्टडी भी है बट एट द
Same time it's mainly for family businesses.
सेम टाइम इट्स मेनली फॉर फैमिली बिनेसेस।
Because this topic has not been covered in this
क्योंकि ये वाला टॉपिक कवर नहीं हुआ है इस
And I feel it's a very different topic on the show.
शो पर एंड आई फील इट्स अ वेरीेंट टॉपिक।
because those who are also freshers who have
क्योंकि जो लोग फ्रेशर्स भी हैं जिन्होंने
I have never even started a business. whose
कभी बिज़नेस स्टार्ट भी नहीं करा है। जिनके
Even families don't have businesses
फैमिलीज़ के भी बिज़नेसेस नहीं है उन्हें भी
You will get the perspective. but this is for
पर्सेक्टिव मिल जाएगा। बट दिस इज फॉर
Families Who Are Trying to Figure Out How to Make
फैमिलीज़ हु आर ट्राइंग टू फिगर हाउ टू मेक
The Businesses Grow Further Pass It On To The
द बिनेसेस ग्रो फर्दर पास इट ऑन टू द
Next generation to scale sure okay a first
नेक्स्ट जनरेशन टू स्केल श्योर ओके अ पहले
Let’s start with a case study
एक केस स्टडी के साथ स्टार्ट करते हैं
Ambani case study loosely you can explain it
अंबानी केस स्टडी लूजली आप यह समझा सकते
what did Dhirubhai Ambani do and then
हो कि धीरूभाई अंबानी ने क्या किया और फिर
Ah what did you say to Mukesh Ambani loosely speaker
अह मुकेश अंबानी को क्या कहा लूजली स्पीकर
And then what did Mukesh Ambani do?
और फिर मुकेश अंबानी ने क्या करा एंड
What is the plan for the third generation. So
व्हाट इज द प्लान फॉर द थर्ड जनरेशन। सो
this is you know obviously based on not my
दिस इज़ यू नो ऑब्वियसली बेस्ड ऑन नॉट माय
First Hand Experience But Whatever I
फर्स्ट हैंड एक्सपीरियंस बट व्हाटएवर आई
have seen heard observed so dhirubhai also
हैव सीन हर्ड ऑब्ज़र्व्ड सो धीरूभाई आल्सो
Started as a trader, we trade
स्टार्टेड एज़ अ ट्रेडर हम ट्रेडिंग करा
Then after that Wright came into manufacturing
फिर उसके बाद मैन्युफैक्चरिंग में आए राइट
Textiles and plastics came into those things
टेक्सटाइल किया प्लास्टिक वो चीजों में आए
then he took a very big risk which is
देन ही टूक अ वेरी बिग रिस्क व्हिच इज़
called jamnagar refinery now let me tell you
कॉल्ड जामनगर रिफाइनरी नाउ लेट मी टेल यू
When the Jamnagar refinery was being set up and
जब जामनगर रिफाइनरी लग रही थी और जो
He created capacity and some of the people
कैपेसिटी उन्होंने बनाई एंड सम ऑफ द पीपल
who work with him at that time i have had
हु वर्क वि हिम एट दैट टाइम आई हैव हैव
work with them and they said
वर्क वि देम एंड दे सेड
I too had told Dhiru Bhai that Sir once
हमने भी बोला था धीरू भाई को कि सर एक बार
Think about it, it's not that big of a risk
सोच लो ये थोड़ा ज्यादा बड़ा रिस्क नहीं
It's okay and this is something I heard
हो गया ओके एंड दिस इज सुनी सुनाई बात
I put this disclaimer on my own
मैंने अपने से इतना मैं डिस्क्लेमर डाल
I am here so he said what will happen
रहा हूं तो उन्होंने बोला कि क्या होगा
No sir, whatever you have done in all these years
नहीं सर मतलब जो भी आपने इतने साल में
I have made it, it will become zero sir, that's all
बनाया है वो जीरो हो जाएगा सर बस इतना ही
No
ना
We will start again, this is Dheeru Bhai I AM
फिर शुरू करेंगे ये है धीरू भाई आई एम
sure he would have secured the family i am
श्योर ही वुड हैव सिक्यर्ड ह फैमिली आई एम
I'm not very sure about that
आई एम आई एम नॉट वेरी श्योर अबाउट दैट
Ranveer because whenever Jamnagar refinery's
रणवीर क्योंकि जब जब जामनगर रिफाइनरी का
jo risk hai somebody has to salute that
जो रिस्क है समबडी हैस टू सैल्यूट दैट
person to take that kind of risk and the
पर्सन टू टेक दैट काइंड ऑफ रिस्क एंड द
People have head in many places it is mentioned panchratna
पीपल ही हैड कई जगह इट इज़ मेंशंड पंचरत्न
you know the really great team he had at least
यू नो द रियली ग्रेट टीम ही हैड एटलीस्ट
one or two people i know because i work with
वन और टू पीपल आई नो बिकॉज़ आई वर्क विथ
them like they are like i would touch their feet
देम लाइक दे आर लाइक आई वुड टच देर फीट
Any time means that it is respect
एनी टाइम मतलब वो रिस्पेक्ट रिगार्ड है
He said we stood correct it. We
उन्होंने कहा कि वी स्टुड करेक्ट इट। हमने
Also tried to stop the hand. he said
भी हाथ रोकने की कोशिश की। उन्होंने कहा
Look friend, I listened to everyone. not like that
यार देखो मैंने सबकी बात सुन ली। ऐसा नहीं
It is that Dhiru Bhai used to ignore that I have
है कि धीरू भाई इग्नोर करते थे कि आई हैव
The Answers. He said, okay tell me what is the risk?
द आंसर्स। कहा अच्छा बताओ क्या रिस्क है?
This is capacity risk. Capex Risk
ये है कैपेसिटी रिस्क है। कैपेक्स रिस्क
Is. Sensitivity analysis. you know this is a
है। सेंसिटिविटी एनालिसिस। यू नो दिस इज अ
the very thing that if I assumed
वेरीेंट थिंग कि अगर मैंने जो अस्यूम किया
This much stuff will be sold. if it is not sold so much
इतना माल बिकेगा। अगर नहीं बिका इतनी
If production does not happen, will there be a loss? These
प्रोडक्शन नहीं हुई तो क्या लॉस होगा? ये
He said this after listening to everything. I heard all
सब उन्होंने सुनने के बाद कहा। आई हर्ड ऑल
Of you with full respect. but we are
ऑफ यू विद फुल रिस्पेक्ट। लेकिन वी आर
Going Ahead as an Entrepreneur This is my
गोइंग अहेड एज एन एंटरप्रेन्योर यह मेरी
There is a call. so you understand and that was the
कॉल है। सो यू अंडरस्टैंड एंड दैट वास द
Game changer for Reliance Jamnagar refinery
गेम चेंजर फॉर Reliance जामनगर रिफाइनरी
has built reliance because the kind of
हैज़ बिल्ट Reliance बिकॉज़ द काइंड ऑफ
Scale Cash Flows Everything It Brings You Know
स्केल कैश फ्लोस एवरीथिंग इट ब्रॉट यू नो
Did everything for Reliance. understand this point
डिड एवरीथिंग फॉर Reliance। यह पॉइंट समझ
I came. now we go to the next what
में आ गया। नाउ वी गो टू द नेक्स्ट व्हाट
I saw when I was working in that company
आई सॉ व्हेन आई वास वर्किंग इन दैट कंपनी
is that which Mukesh bhai inherited
इज दैट जो मुकेश भाई ने इनहेरिट किया
He did that before I left Reliance this
उसको उन्होंने बिफोर आई लेफ्ट Reliance ये
How much did you build and grow but what
कितना बिल्ड एंड ग्रो कर दिया बट व्हाट
what has happened in the last 10-15 years is so
हैज़ हैपेंड इन द लास्ट 10-15 इयर्स इज़ सो
The One Transformation That Reliance Went Through
वन ट्रांसफॉर्मेशन दैट Reliance वेंट थ्रू
This is what we call reincarnation or avatar
जिसको हम बोलते हैं रीइकारनेशन या अवतार
Vaz
वाज़
Dhiru bhai to Mukesh bhai but I think third
धीरू भाई टू मुकेश भाई बट आई थिंक तीसरा
An incarnation has taken place which no one is seeing. like those
अवतार हुआ जो कोई नहीं देख रहा। जैसे उन
Great people whose feet I touch even today
दिग्गज लोगों ने जिनके मैं पांव छू आज भी
I will touch it. He said we stand corrected
छूंगा। उन्होंने बोला वी स्टैंड करेक्टेड
In front of Dhiru Bhai Will. I also stand
इन फ्रंट ऑफ धीरू भाई विल। मैं भी स्टैंड
I am corrected. I am confessing today.
करेक्टेड हूं। मैं आज कनफेस कर रहा हूं।
When he was investing in Jio. End
जब वो Jio की इन्वेस्टमेंट कर रहे थे। एंड
I had some idea how much you were doing. 50000
आई हैड सम आईडिया कितना कर रहे थे। 50000
It became crores. Then Rs 1 lakh on top of that. They
करोड़ हुआ। फिर 1 लाख के उसके ऊपर। वो
I said, brother, the ship will shake, brother.
मैंने कहा भाई शिप हिल जाएगी भाई।
Then you are coming into consumer brands. You
फिर कंज्यूमर ब्रांड्स में आ रहे हो। तुम
So you are the king of B2B, friend. Where to Be
तो बी टू बी के बादशाह हो यार। कहां बी टू
Are you entering B? Where to enter retail
बी में घुस रहे हो? कहां रिटेल में घुस
had been? Where are you getting into telecom?
रहे हो? कहां टेलीकॉम में घुस रहे हो?
I also thought that this is the right
मेरे को भी लगता था यार इज दिस द राइट
Strategy? Because you are great at being to be
स्ट्रेटजी? बिकॉज़ यू आर ग्रेट इन बी टू बी
You are not so good at being a jerk. but what did
यू नॉट सो गुड इन बी टू सी। बट व्हाट डिड
did it happen? what happened? today they are ruling
इट हैप? व्हाट हैपेंड? टुडे दे आर रूलिंग
Even there. so to move from be to be like
इवन देयर। सो टू मूव फ्रॉम बी टू बी जैसे
I said it takes a generation, right, trader?
मैंने बोला एक जनरेशन लगती है ना ट्रेडर
to become a B2B manufacturer
को बनने में मैन्युफैक्चरर एक बी टू बी को
It probably takes one lifetime to go from B to C
बी टू सी बनने में शायद एक लाइफ टाइम में
It cannot happen and maybe it cannot happen
हो भी नहीं सकता और शायद हो ही नहीं सकता
Like Schneider Electric or ABB
जैसे स्नाइडर इलेक्ट्रिक है या एबीबी है
So washing machines will someday come in B2C
तो बी टू सी में कभी आएंगे वाशिंग मशीन
will you make it
बनाएंगे क्या
But Reliance did it and culturally too
बट Reliance ने कर दिखाया एंड कल्चरली भी
A lot has changed now when I go there it is
बहुत चेंज हुआ नाउ व्हेन आई गो देयर इट्स
a different company so imagine a petroleum
अ डिफरेंट कंपनी सो इमेजिन अ पेट्रोलियम
ium company a petrochemicals company gates
ियम कंपनी अ पेट्रोकेमिकल्स कंपनी गेट्स
Innu Consumer Facing Business Gets In The
इनू कंज्यूमर फेसिंग बिनेस गेट्स इन द
The Next Generation Stitches It and Builds
नेक्स्ट जनरेशन स्टिचेस इट एंड बिल्ड्स
It. I mean what could be a better story
इट। आई मीन व्हाट कुड बी अ बेटर स्टोरी
Then that. I think a lot of young people do this
देन दैट। आई थिंक बहुत सारे यंग लोग ये
Believe that Ambani family has a no
मानते हैं कि अंबानी फैमिली का ना एक
Golden hands are such that they can handle anything with their hands
गोल्डन हैंड है कि वो किसी भी चीज को हाथ
If applied it turns into gold. but it's not
लगाए वो सोना बन जाती है। बट इट्स नॉट
Like that. Look at those businesses which don't take off
लाइक दैट। देखो जो बिनेस नहीं टेक ऑफ करते
Are. So Reliance is always in project
हैं। सो Reliance इज़ ऑलवेज इन प्रोजेक्ट
Stage. We used to watch this many times parallelly, friend
स्टेज। पैरेलली कई बार हम ये देखते थे यार
Which team is this? What are they doing?
ये कौन सी टीम है? ये क्या कर रहे हैं?
There are many projects when 100 people are sitting together
100 लोग बैठे हुए तो बहुत सारे प्रोजेक्ट
They keep studying and many don't even do that.
स्टडी करते रहते हैं और कई वो नहीं भी ल्च
Do. but I would also think that this is
करते। बट आई आई वुड आल्सो थिंक दैट ये जो
The Golden Hand Theory Seems to Be Right
गोल्डन हैंड वाली थ्योरी सीम्स टू बी राइट
Because it would be hard to find a business
बिकॉज़ इट वुड बी हार्ड टू फाइंड अ बिज़नेस
In which they field. We But At Reliance Core
इन व्हिच दे फील्ड। हम बट एट Reliance कोर
Something is going right mentally.
कुछ तो मेंटालिटी वाइज़ सही जा रहा है।
Culturally, Mentality Wise, A Strategy
कल्चरली, मेंटालिटी वाइज़, अ स्ट्रेटजी
Wise. So what is that core? So look at the core I
वाइज़। तो वो कोर क्या है? सो देखो कोर मैं
I can only tell you my own experience
अपना एक एक्सपीरियंस ही आपको बता सकता हूं
Because I also mean limited visibility
क्योंकि मैं भी मतलब लिमिटेड विजिबिलिटी
I was in a product line when I first started
था एक प्रोडक्ट लाइन में था जब मैंने पहली
I did the presentation and I went on a Honda
प्रेजेंटेशन करी और मैं Honda से गया था
So brother MAC, there is some tension when
तो भाई एमएसी थोड़ी तो टशन होती है तो जब
I did the first one and this is to show you the mentality
मैंने पहली एंड दिस टू शो यू द मेंटालिटी
I made great preparations for my first presentation and one
पहली प्रेजेंटेशन बड़ी तैयारी करी एंड वन
of the Executive Directors relating to
ऑफ द एग्जीक्यूटिव डायरेक्टर्स रिलेटेड टू
Mukesh bhai Sheetal Miswani was there
मुकेश भाई शीतल मिसवानी वास देयर
My bosses were big people,
बड़े-बड़े लोग थे मेरे को मेरे बॉस ने
He said if you do it then I am Chotu Ram you know
बोला तुम करो तो मैं छोटू राम यू नो
He is a DGM level guy. they are all to
डीजीएम लेवल का बंदा है। दे आर ऑल तो
I started the presentation. the first or
मैंने प्रेजेंटेशन शुरू करी। पहली या
It was on the second slide. He said, son, sit down.
दूसरी स्लाइड पे था। कहा बेटा बैठ जाओ।
I said no sir, no no sit down.
मैंने नहीं सर कहता नहीं नहीं बैठ जाओ।
Rajiv, why did you ask these three questions?
तीन सवाल पूछे राजीव ये आपने किस लिए
made? I said Sir, who is related to Petroleum
बनाया? मैंने कहा सर पेट्रोलियम के जो
We want to open petrol pumps, its channel
हमें पेट्रोल पंप्स खोलने हैं उसकी चैनल
There is a strategy. Ok. so we companies have you
स्ट्रेटजी है। ओके। सो वि कंपनीज़ हैव यू
Benchmarked? I am BPCL this December. No
बेंचमार्क्ड? मैं बीपीसीएल दिस दिस। नहीं
no no we are not talking about India
नहीं नहीं इंडिया की हम बात ही नहीं कर
have been. Which global company did you choose?
रहे हैं। ग्लोबल कौन सी कंपनी आपने
Have you seen it in petroleum? I said global
पेट्रोलियम में देखी है? मैंने कहा ग्लोबल
So I did not see it. good but you
तो मैंने देखी नहीं। अच्छा पर आपको
I don't want to look at petroleum. You have 71
पेट्रोलियम तो देखनी नहीं है। आपने 71
Store Dekha which is the best franchise
स्टोर देखा व्हिच इज द बेस्ट फ्रेंचाइज
Model in the world? 71 McDonald's did you
मॉडल इन द वर्ल्ड? 71 McDonald's डड यू
Study Duncan Donuts
स्टडी डंकन डोनट्स
We will start with a global scale
दे स्टार्ट विद ग्लोबल स्केल हम ये दिस
was a because i have worked in Honda which
वाज़ अ बिकॉज़ आई हैव वर्क्ड इन Honda व्हिच
is a multinational but the thinking is what
इज़ अ मल्टीीनेशनल बट द थिंकिंग तो वो क्या
Happened? My third presentation was discussed
हुआ? बातें हुई मेरी प्रेजेंटेशन तीसरी
did not go to the slide. and i learn my lesson
स्लाइड पे नहीं गई। एंड आई लर्न माय लेसन
that Gupta ji you should improve yourself if you come here
कि गुप्ता जी सुधर जाओ अगर यहां पर
If you want to survive then one thing is to think
सर्वाइव करना है तो सो वन थिंग इज दे थिंक
Global but there is a difference between
ग्लोबल बट देयर इज अ डिफरेंस बिटवीन
Thinking Global: Many people think global, but I
थिंकिंग ग्लोबल बहुत लोग सोचते हैं बट आई
Call That Sabse Baagh and Sheikh Chilli Ke Khwab
कॉल दैट सब्स बाग एंड शेख चिल्ली के ख्वाब
They also make it happen that's the one difference.
दे आल्सो मेक इट हैपन दैट्स द वन डिफरेंस।
so fire you know that fire in the belly that go
सो फायर यू नो दैट फायर इन द बेली दैट गो
Getter Attitude Having the Teams in Place
गेटर एटीट्यूड हैविंग द टीम्स इन प्लेस
Having the monitoring mechanisms in place
हैविंग द मॉनिटरिंग मैकेनिज्म्स इन प्लेस
Having the Resources in Place People in
हैविंग द रिसोर्सेज इन प्लेस पीपल इन
place and they are way ahead of time when I
प्लेस एंड दे आर वे अहेड ऑफ़ टाइम व्हेन आई
when i joy them i mean everything was
व्हेन आई जॉइ देम आई मीन एवरीथिंग वाज़
Online in 2002 means I don't have prescriptions
ऑनलाइन इन 2002 मतलब मैं पर्चियां नहीं
I had to make a book of leaves in 2002 so I did a book
बनानी थी लीव्स की 2002 में तो मैं एक
He used to make leave slips in a multinational company
मल्टीीनेशनल में लीव की पर्चियां बनाता था
or go out to the factory to sleep
या बाहर जाने के लिए फैक्ट्री के लिए सो
They have adopted technology for so long
दे हैड अडॉप्टेड टेक्नोलॉजी जी सो लॉन्ग
We can only see the glitter outside.
हमारे को सिर्फ बाहर की चकाचौंध दिखती है।
But what goes in is that we don't see. So
बट जो अंदर जाता है दैट वी डोंट सी। सो
This is the mentality. Think Global But Make
दिस इज़ द मेंटालिटी। थिंक ग्लोबल बट मेक
It happens. We and what will it take to make
इट हैपन। हम एंड व्हाट विल इट टेक टू मेक
can it happen? We
इट हैपन? हम
Ok. Now the same case from a practical point of view
ओके। अभी एक प्रैक्टिकल नजरिए से सेम केस
Let us analyse the study. for first
स्टडी को एनालाइज करते हैं। फॉर फर्स्ट
Generation Entrepreneurs Like Me. Mukesh
जनरेशन एंटरप्रेन्यर्स लाइक मी। मुकेश
Ambani is like God for us. that wow
अंबानी हमारे लिए भगवान की तरह है। कि वाओ
What a business story. but honestly we
व्हाट अ बिज़नेस स्टोरी। बट ऑनेस्टली वी
Can only aspire to be Dhirubhai Ambani.
कैन ओनली अस्पायर टू बी धीरूभाई अंबानी।
Is there truth in the statement? Absolutely
इज देयर ट्रुथ इन द स्टेटमेंट? बिल्कुल
Ok. no you can only aspire to be
ठीक है। नो यू कैन ओनली अस्पायर टू बी
Dheeru bhai. because when you start you
धीरू भाई। क्योंकि आपको स्टार्ट तो आप
The advantage that Mukesh Bhai got will be available to you too
मुकेश भाई को जो एडवांटेज मिली वो आपको
Not there. ok and in order to become a
नहीं है। ओके एंड इन ऑर्डर टू बिकम अ
The Potential Dhirubhai Ambani We Need Too
पोटेंशियल धीरूभाई अंबानी वी नीड टू
Master Everything We Have Spoken About Till
मास्टर एवरीथिंग वी हैव स्पोकन अबाउट टिल
This Point in the Podcast. Absolutely. Correct.
दिस पॉइंट इन द पॉडकास्ट। बिलकुल। करेक्ट।
Now let's talk about the second generation
अभी ये सेकंड जनरेशन के बारे में बात करते
Are. So there are two questions. The first question is that
हैं। तो दो सवाल हैं। पहला सवाल यह है कि
What do you think Dhirubhai Ambani said about Mukesh Ambani?
व्हाट डू यू थिंक धीरूभा अंबानी ने मुकेश
What did others teach Ambani on a core level?
अंबानी को क्या सिखाया ऑन अ कोर लेवल अदर
Then the technicalities?
देन द टेक्निकिटीज?
The second question is that in a 2020
दूसरा सवाल यह है कि एक 2020 के
keeping the context in mind
कॉन्टेक्स्ट को ध्यान में रखकर
If a family run business is to be taken to the next generation
अगर एक फैमिली रन बिजनेस को अगले जनरेशन
What to keep in mind when training a
को ट्रेन करना तो दिमाग में क्या रखना
Needed?
चाहिए?
So I have to only guess. so what do i think
सो आई हैव टू ओनली गेस। सो मुझे क्या लगता
That Dhiru Bhai Ji needs to be taught something
है कि धीरू भाई जी को कुछ सिखाने की जरूरत
It might not have been there. s i always say children
नहीं पड़ी होगी। एस आई ऑलवेज से चिल्ड्रन
Learn by watching the parents. so i think
लर्न बाय वाचिंग द पेरेंट्स। सो आई थिंक
Value systems that are go-getters for hard work
वैल्यू सिस्टम्स जो हैं मेहनत के गो गेटर
And if you have decided about it then you have to do it.
एटीट्यूड के और अगर सोच लिया तो करना है।
i think this is what would have been
आई थिंक दिस इज व्हाट वुड हैव बीन
definitely transmitted not merely through the
डेफिनेटली ट्रांसमिटेड नॉट मेयरली थ्रू द
DNA and through the blood but by living in the
डीएनए और थ्रू द ब्लड बट बाय लिविंग इन द
Same house and working in the same company. So
सेम हाउस एंड वर्किंग इन द सेम कंपनी। सो
Working Hard Having a Gotter Attitude and
वर्किंग हार्ड हैविंग अ गोटर एटीट्यूड एंड
whatever you set out to do don't leave your
व्हाटएवर यू सेट आउट टू डू डोंट लीव योर
College in Between.
कॉलेज इन बिटवीन।
If you have picked it up then you have to do something boss
उठा लिया है ना तो करना तो है बॉस कुछ भी
Let that reliability power focus on the
हो जाए दैट रेिलियंस पावर फोकस ऑन द
Controllables and Cuts Off the Noise Exactly
कंट्रोलबल्स एंड कट ऑफ द नॉइस एक्सक्टली
so i think this spirit of work hard
सो आई थिंक दिस स्पिरिट ऑफ वर्क हार्ड
Global Thinking Think Big Think Really Big
ग्लोबल थिंकिंग थिंक बिग थिंक रियली बिग
Think Global because I think one of Reliance
थिंक ग्लोबल बिकॉज़ आई थिंक Reliance का एक
There is an unspoken strategy. Any we business
अनस्पोकन स्ट्रेटजी है। कोई भी हम बिज़नेस
We have to be number one in India
करेंगे इंडिया में वी हैव टू बी नंबर वन
And top three in the world. it's very
एंड टॉप थ्री इन द वर्ल्ड। इट्स वेरी
clear. Number one in India, top three in
क्लियर। इंडिया में नंबर वन, टॉप थ्री इन
The World. So that is the thinking of many people
द वर्ल्ड। सो वो सोच है कितनों की ऐसी सोच
we god these are the learnings that dhirubhai
हम गॉड दीज़ आर द लर्निंग्स दैट धीरूभा
Ambani Possibly Passed On To Mukesh Ambani
अंबानी पॉसिबबली पास्ड ऑन टू मुकेश अंबानी
or i have heard something similar in most
या आई हैव हर्ड समथिंग सिमिलर इन मोस्ट
Conversations that have had around this topic
कन्वर्सेशन दैट हैव हैड अराउंड दिस टॉपिक
Now!
अभी
I would like to ask you that a 2020
मैं आपसे यह पूछना चाहूंगा कि एक 2020
keeping the context in mind
कॉन्टेक्स्ट को ध्यान में रखकर
What a business owner teaches his kids
एक बिजनेस ओनर अपने बच्चों को क्या सिखा
so that's the second generation goes way
सकता है सो दैट द सेकंड जनरेशन गोज़ वे
Beyond the first generation. Ok. So
बियों बियों्ड द फर्स्ट जनरेशन। ओके। सो
it's very crude but I think that
इट्स वेरी क्रूड बट मैं ये सोचता हूं कि
which is our mind, body and habits
जो हमारी माइंड, बॉडी और हैबिट्स है ना ये
There is a lot of need to correct this generation a little.
इस जनरेशन को थोड़ी ठीक करने की बहुत
There is need. so i give a simple example
जरूरत है। सो मैं एग्जांपल सिंपल देता हूं
that I haven't seen at least in my life
कि मैंने नहीं देखा एटलीस्ट अपनी लाइफ
in time that any person can do 40 hours or 45
टाइम में कि कोई भी बंदा 40 आवर्स या 45
Hours may be available in the next generation. Address
आवर्स हो सकता है अब आगे की जनरेशन। पता
will it work after 20 years or any 20 hours or 15 or
चलेगा 20 साल बाद कि कोई 20 घंटा या 15 या
Can one be successful by working for 20 hours?
20 घंटे करके सक्सेसफुल हो सकता है क्या?
so the first thing is that
सो फर्स्ट थिंग इज दैट
you have to have a body
यू हैव टू हैव अ बॉडी
which can get out of the house at 8:00 am
व्हिच कैन गेट आउट ऑफ द हाउस एट 8:00 am
and get into the house at 8:00 p.m. End
एंड गेट इंटू द हाउस एट 8:00 पी.m. एंड
it's like 12 hours including commute and
इट्स लाइक 12 आवर्स इंक्लूडिंग कम्यूट एंड
You should be okay with it. hmm because those 12
यू शुड बी ओके विद इट। हम्म क्योंकि उन 12
in hours just because of the environment
घंटों में आप एनवायरमेंट की वजह से ही
You will learn a lot. Exactly outside
बहुत कुछ सीख लोगे। एक्सैक्टली बाहर तो
You will go from home, it is commute time. so one is that
जाओगे घर से कम्यूट टाइम है। सो वन इज कि
Second, this is the get rich quick theory
दूसरा यह जो गेट रिच क्विक वाली थ्यरीज है
no I think whatever is teaching you or
ना आई थिंक जो भी सिखा रहा है आपको या
as many people i think that should be really
जितने सारे लोग आई थिंक दैट शुड बी रियली
Thrown out the window. The third thing is this
थ्रोन आउट ऑफ द विंडो। थर्ड थिंग यह है
If I am a family business owner. we are
अगर मैं फैमिली बिज़नेस ओनर हूं। वी आर
Talking of second gem. I think as a father
टॉकिंग ऑफ़ सेकंड जेम। आई थिंक एज अ फादर
I will carefully assess that this is my child
आई विल केयरफुली असेस कि यह जो मेरा बच्चा
Hey again what did I say? interest,
है अगेन मैंने क्या बोला? इंटरेस्ट,
Capability and Potential. if these three
कैपेबिलिटी एंड पोटेंशियल। यह तीनों अगर
If my child is sitting in a triangle, then
ट्रायंगल में मेरे इसके बैठ रहे हैं, तो
how do I fit that into this business and
मैं इसको इस बिज़नेस में कैसे फिट करूं और
How do I train him? but if I think
इसको कैसे ट्रेन करूं। बट अगर मुझे लगता
is that he is not going to be able to
है दैट ही इज़ नॉट बी गोइंग टू बी एबल टू
Succeed and fit into my shoes and I am that
सक्सीड और फिट इंटू माय शूज एंड आई एम दैट
Business owner then I will create another system
बिज़नेस ओनर देन आई विल क्रिएट अनदर सिस्टम
End process. So that the business continues,
एंड प्रोसेस। सो दैट द बिजनेस कंटिन्यूस,
The Life Style Continues and This Person
द लाइफ स्टाइल कंटिन्यूस एंड दिस पर्सन
does something align with his interest,
डस समथिंग वि अलाइन विद ह इंटरेस्ट,
capability and potential which is one way today
कैपेबिलिटी एंड पोटेंशियल जो आज वन वे
traffic is that if you are not in this business
ट्रैफिक है कि अगर आप इस बिजनेस में नहीं
If it comes you can't do anything. But even if
आए तो आप कुछ नहीं कर सकते। बट वो भी अगर
Even if you want to do hard work, mentoring,
करना है तो भी हार्ड वर्क, मेंटरिंग,
Ecosystem, relationships, all this will have to be done.
इकोसिस्टम, रिलेशनशिप ये सब करनी पड़ेगी।
so i think as the next gen as a second
सो आई थिंक एज अ नेक्स्ट जन एज अ सेकंड
Generation Owner and First Generation Passing to the
जनरेशन ओनर और फर्स्ट जनरेशन पासिंग टू द
next jan what i will do i would do is
नेक्स्ट जन व्हाट आई विल डू आई वुड डू इज
I would tell them it's absolutely fine to
आई वुड टेल देम इट्स अब्सोलुटली फाइन टू
Be out and about for 12 hours in a day
बी आउट एंड अबाउट फॉर 12 आवर्स इन अ डे हम
I am working hard because I don't want to die
डोंट से मैं बड़ी मेहनत कर रहा हूं मैं मर
There is no need to curse Gaya. you should
गया क्या कोसने की जरूरत नहीं है। यू शुड
Be Grateful That You Have So Many Hours of Work
बी ग्रेटफुल कि आपके पास इतने घंटे का काम
Is. Hmm, the day when I will sit idle
है। हम्म हम खाली बैठोगे ना जिस दिन उस
The day will come when you will understand what happens. Being
दिन समझ में आएगा कि क्या होता है। बीइंग
Busy is a privilege is a privilege
बिजी इज अ प्रिविलेज इज अ प्रिविलेज ये
It is necessary. and you know your understanding
जरूरी है। एंड यू नो अंडरस्टैंडिंग योर
interest this thing and also
इंटरेस्ट दिस थिंग एंड आल्सो
understanding your weaknesses that this is
अंडरस्टैंडिंग योर वीकनेसेस कि दिस इज़
what I can do and this is what I can't
व्हाट आई कैन डू एंड दिस इज़ व्हाट आई कांट
Doo. i think these are the few things i would
डू। आई थिंक दीज़ आर द फ्यू थिंग्स आई वुड
Like to know transfer to the next
लाइक टू यू नो ट्रांसफर टू द नेक्स्ट
Generation. but as the owner as the custodian of the
जनरेशन। बट एज़ द ओनर एज़ द कस्टोडियन ऑफ़ द
Business which I have set up.
बिज़नेस व्हिच आई हैव सेट अप।
I will ensure that I am putting the best
आई विल इंश्योर दैट आई एम पुटिंग द बेस्ट
person out there not my son not my daughter
पर्सन आउट देयर नॉट माय सन नॉट माय डॉटर
If that person is not the best suited person
इफ दैट पर्सन इज नॉट द बेस्ट सूटेड पर्सन
For the interest of the business we get you the
फॉर द इंटरेस्ट ऑफ द बिनेस हम यू गेट द
Point Yes
पॉइंट यस
Now you are basically saying that the child's
अब बेसिकली ये कह रहे हो कि बच्चे की
Recognize the personality if personality
पर्सनालिटी को पहचानो अगर पर्सनालिटी
if it is not suitable then rather take care of yourself
सूटेड नहीं है तो रादर टेक केयर ऑफ योर
Business not your child yah. and figure it out
बिज़नेस नॉट योर चाइल्ड याह। एंड फिगर आउट
How to take care of child's future.
हाउ टू टेक केयर ऑफ़ चाइल्ड फ्यूचर।
Absolutely. The person whose upbringing is different,
बिल्कुल। जिस बंदे की अपब्रिंगिंग अलग है,
The guy for whom everything is different, why are you
जिस बंदे का सब कुछ अलग है, व्हाई आर यू
Trying to convert him into your image?
ट्राइंग टू कन्वर्ट हिम इंटू योर इमेज?
God has made each individual in him
गॉड हैज़ मेड ईच इंडिविजुअल इन ह इन
Different image. Right? So, I am saying this
डिफरेंट इमेज। राइट? सो, मैं यह कह रहा
I am here to take this business forward
हूं कि मेरे इस बिजनेस को आगे चलाने के
What should my child be like? Right?
लिए मेरा बच्चा कैसा होना चाहिए? राइट?
To be smart, to be clever, you know, to be savvy,
चतुर होना, शाना होना, यू नो सैवी होना,
I will do all this by being a little political. And
थोड़ा पॉलिटिकल होना ये सब मैं करूंगा। और
If I feel, Bhaiya, we cannot do this
अगर मुझे लगता है भैया ना हो पाई हम इसके
If that's the case then I will professionalize the company
बस की ना है तो मैं कंपनी को प्रोफेशनलाइज
I will do it but he won't be sad my friend
कर दूंगा हम बट उदास नहीं होगा यार ये
What God, what a donkey you created such a thing
क्या भगवान क्या गधा पैदा किया ये ऐसी
Language is business, is a donkey born from it?
भाषा होती है बिनेस से क्या गधा पैदा हुआ
Maybe my wife also heard the sound
है हो सकता है मेरी वाइफ को भी चार सुना
Give me what a bastard you have brought out, what is all this
दे क्या तूने कपूत निकाला है ये सब क्या
these are useless things, may be he is meant to
बेकार की बातें हैं मे बी ही इज़ मेंट टू
do something else than i will not have further
डू समथिंग एल्स हम देन आई विल नॉट हैव फदर
quarrel with that issue but I will
क्वरल विथ दैट इशू बट आई आई विल
Professionalize the Company Put True Structures
प्रोफेशनलाइज द कंपनी पुट सच स्ट्रक्चर्स
that the business of these places should also continue
इन प्लेस कि बिजनेस भी चलता रहे वो भी
keep doing it. Last time today a lot
करता रहे। लास्ट आज के टाइम में बहुत
There are huge options. Sell ​​the company friend
बड़ी-बड़ी ऑप्शंस हैं। बेच दो यार कंपनी
To.
को।
You have a company worth Rs 250 crore or Rs 500 crore.
आपकी 250 करोड़ या 500 करोड़ की कंपनी है।
Ok? Your EBITDA from LETS is 10%.
ठीक है? लेट्स से आपका एबिटा 10% का है।
EBITDA is in a very bad state at 15%.
बड़ी मरी गिरी हालत में 15% का एबिटा है।
Ok? So how much is it? 75 crores
ठीक है? तो कितना हो गया? 75 करोड़ हो
Went. There must be some valuation. you sell off
गया। कुछ तो वैल्यू्यूएशन होगी। आप सेल ऑफ
Do it to the company. Create wealth and give it away
कर दो कंपनी को। वेल्थ क्रिएट करके दे दो
To the children. Slowly after taking out IPO
बच्चों को। आईपीओ निकाल के धीरे-धीरे
Unlock your wealth. So why are we in the same
वेल्थ अनलॉक कर लो। मतलब क्यों हम उसी में
We are stuck in our own labyrinth,
ही फंसे हुए हैं अपने चक्रव्यूह में कि
My son will take care of it. there are ways to
मेरा बेटा ही संभालेगा। देयर आर वेज़ टू
Unlock that Wealth and Create the Well Being
अनलॉक दैट वेल्थ एंड क्रिएट द वेल बीइंग
For the future generations. but the dispute is in
फॉर द फ्यूचर जनरेशंस। बट द डिस्प्यूट इन
our mind is family for the business or is
आवर माइंड इज़ इज़ फैमिली फॉर द बिनेस या इज
Business for the Family. we are there for purpose
बिनेस फॉर द फैमिली। हम ये वहां पे पर्पस
The needle gets stuck in it. Wow.
में जाके अटक जाती है सुई। वाओ।
Because there is no clarity in this itself.
हम क्योंकि इसी में खुद क्लेरिटी नहीं है।
Why do you want to do business now? friend of the kids
क्यों करना है अभी बिजनेस? यार बच्चों की
Life style should be good. Ok? So
लाइफ स्टाइल अच्छी होनी चाहिए। ठीक है? तो
Unlock his wealth. sell it to him
उसकी वेल्थ अनलॉक कर लो। बेच दो उसको
Make a system. Yes, if business is morant
सिस्टम बना दो। हां, अगर बिज़नेस इज़ मोरेंट
then family, then another structure was added to it
देन फैमिली, तो उसमें दूसरा स्ट्रक्चर लगा
Two. That's the only way out. Hmm. but why
दो। दैट्स द ओनली वे आउट। हम्म। बट व्हाई
It's Just Quarreling and Fighting It's Not
इट जस्ट क्वरलिंग एंड फाइटिंग इट्स नॉट
Going to happen. Understood and Absorb
गोइंग टू हैपन। अंडरस्टुड एंड अब्सॉर्ब
everything you said so but that's why it's not
एवरीथिंग यू सेड सो बट इसी वजह से ना इट्स
Shocking to me that there are many such people in our country
शॉकिंग टू मी कि हमारे देश में ऐसे बहुत
all are business families which have gone
सारी बिनेस फैमिलीज़ हैं व्हिच हैव गॉन
Beyond Gen Two Gen Three Gen Three and the
बिय्ड जेन टू जेन थ्री जेन थ्री एंड द
Ambanis Themselves Are Gen Three Right Now
अंबानीज़ देमसेल्व्स आर जेन थ्री राइट नाउ
I don't know what's gone right now. I know
आई डोंट नो व्हाट्स गॉन राइट देर। आई नो
We have addressed this in the past. butt so i
वी हैव एड्रेस दिस इन द पास्ट। बट तो मैं
Let me answer this. Latest Survey Shows
इसका जवाब देता हूं। लेटेस्ट सर्वे शोज़
and i'm not surprised the number could be
एंड आई एम नॉट सरप्राइज़्ड द नंबर कुड बी
Peacock. 50% off the next does not want to join
मोर। 50% ऑफ द नेक्स्ट डजंट वांट टू ज्वॉइ
The Family Business.
द फैमिली बिजनेस।
But according to me it might be 70 or 80
बट मेरे हिसाब से इट माइट बी 70 और 80 बट
Survey says 50. Why? I have family
सर्वे 50 बताता है। क्यों? मुझे फैमिली
The benefits that you are getting from the business
बिज़नेस से जो बेनिफिट मिल रहे हैं वो तो
I want it but I don't want to die. What is the reason
चाहिए बट मुझे मरना नहीं है। क्या कारण है
His? There are two reasons. Boring Business End
उसका? दो कारण है। बोरिंग बिजनेस एंड
Somebody breathing down my neck. That means that
समबडी ब्रीथिंग डाउन माय नेक। यानी कि
Father. Papa Uncle Uncle Grandfather Elder Cousin Elder
पापा। पापा चाचा ताऊ दादा एल्डर कजन एल्डर
Sibling the list is endless
सिबलिंग द लिस्ट इज एंडलेस
Brother, minimum what I have seen is very few like this
भाई मिनिमम मैंने जो देखा बहुत कम ऐसी
there will be families that are somewhat of the same size that
फैमिलीज होंगी जो थोड़े एक साइज के हैं कि
It's father and son, there must be uncle
फादर और बेटा है चाचा ताऊ जरूर होंगे
Because the brothers of the grandfather were different
क्योंकि ग्रैंडफादर के जो भाई थे वो अलग
If there are four people then the minimum number of uncles will be
हो गए चार जने तो मिनिमम होंगे चाचा ताऊ
cousin and that is fine and if there is a sibling then let
कजन और वो ठीक है और अगर सिबलिंग है सो दे
don't want to breathe people down
डोंट वांट टू ब्रीथिंग पीपल ब्रीथिंग डाउन
The Neck
द नेक
second and this was you know some recent one
सेकंड एंड दिस वास यू नो सम रिसेंटली वन
of the person who enrolled in our course told
ऑफ द पर्सन हु एनरोल्ड इन आवर कोर्स टोल्ड
I say sir if you will teach me then
मी कहता है सर मेरे को आप पढ़ाओगे तो
I don’t want to do the family business
फैमिली बिज़नेस मुझे करना ही नहीं है मैं
Why do you say sir there is no break in life
क्यों कहता है सर ब्रेक ही नहीं है लाइफ
Why do I say anything sir my mind is cooked
में कुछ मैं क्यों कहता है सर दिमाग पक
Those things happen in the morning as well as in the afternoon
जाता है सुबह भी वो बातें दोपहर में भी
They didn’t let me do anything even in the evening
शाम को भी करने देना नहीं इन्होंने कुछ
I want my sir to be like this
मुझे तो मैं तो चाहता हूं कि मेरी सर ऐसा
Make me do the course so that I can get a job
मुझे कोर्स कराओ मेरी नौकरी लग जाए सो द
the issue is a money is an accept
इशू इज अ मनीज इज एन एक्सेप्ट
The business was interesting enough to match with the
द बिनेस वाज़ इंटरेस्टिंग इनफ इट मैच वि द
Kids But 50% Off The Kids Don't Want To Run
किड्स बट 50% ऑफ़ द किड्स डोंट वांट टू रन
The Family Business. now how do we solve that
द फैमिली बिज़नेस। नाउ हाउ डू वी सॉल्व दैट
problem and imagine what would be that
प्रॉब्लम एंड इमेजिन व्हाट विल बी दैट
Number? There are 6.3 crore MSMEs in this
नंबर? देयर आर 6.3 करोड़ एमएसएमईस इन दिस
Country. Ok? I think that's the number. Now
कंट्री। ओके? आई थिंक दैट्स द नंबर। नाउ
What will happen? their children cannot drive
व्हाट विल हैपन? उनके बच्चे तो चलाना नहीं
Want. Are they lying outside or their life
चाहते। वो तो बाहर पड़े हैं या उनकी लाइफ
Is. that's the problem this country needs to
है। दैट्स द प्रॉब्लम दिस कंट्री नीड्स टू
Solv. So what will happen to these businesses? Close
सॉल्व। तो क्या होगा इन बिनेसेस का? बंद
will it happen or the wealth will be unlocked or sold
हो जाएंगे या वेल्थ अनलॉक हो जाएगी या बिक
Will go. Whatever can be sold will be sold. which is not
जाएंगे। जो बिक सकेगा बिक जाएगा। जो नहीं
It can be sold, he will run it as long as he can.
बिक सकेगा जब तक वो चला सकता है चलाएगा।
That's what so happens. I remember when I
दैट्स व्हाट सो हैपन। मुझे याद है जब मैं
I was 22 years old and when I was with my friends
22 साल का था और जब मैं मेरे दोस्तों की
I used to watch lives. Where the friend is someone's family
लाइव्स देखता था। जहां यार किसी का फैमिली
This is business. i thought to myself that wow what
बिज़नेस है। आई थॉट टू मसेल्फ कि वाओ व्हाट
A platform. you know i wish i had that
अ प्लेटफार्म। यू नो आई विश आई हैड दैट
Platform. i could grow it into something
प्लेटफार्म। आई कुड ग्रो इट इनू समथिंग
Hughes.
ह्यूज।
but then again as I grow older I get this
बट देन अगेन एज आई ग्रू ओल्डर मैं यह
I want to know that friend you can't always do it completely
जानना हूं कि यार यू कांट ऑलवेज कंप्लीटली
Empathize with people you don't know what
एम्प्थाइज विथ पीपल यू डोंट नो व्हाट्स
What's actually happening behind closed doors
एक्चुअली हैपनिंग बिहाइंड क्लोज डोर्स वो
Isn't it true that I am crazy in love with my pain
है ना एरी मैं तो प्रेम दीवानी मेरा दर्द
I don't know of any other one, I will give you an example
ना जाने कोई एक और आपको एग्जांपल देता हूं
a guy from a top b school ok son of a
अ गाय फ्रॉम अ टॉप बी स्कूल ओके सन ऑफ अ
Big Industrialist
बिग इंडस्ट्रियलिस्ट
he is crying okay recently i met this
वो रो रहा है ठीक है रिसेंटली आई मेट दिस
Cow he was literally crying says sir
गाय ही वास लिटरली क्राइंग कहता सर सबसे
A man committed a big mistake in his life, he is the only son
बड़ी जिंदगी की भूल एक करी इकलौता बेटा है
That the school also came on top in the family business
कि फैमिली बिजनेस में आ गया टॉप भी स्कूल
was in a dying state, as much as the head
से था मरी गिरी हालत में सर जितना भी
If I got breath I would have come
मिलता सांस तो आती
If I could breathe, I would tell you how am I today
सांस तो आती कहता आज मेरी क्या हालत है
my piercers they are getting multi
मेरे जो पियर्स हैं दे आर गेटिंग मल्टी
Crore salary because he is from a top b
करोड़ सैलरी बिकॉज़ ही हैज़ फ्रॉम अ टॉप बी
Graduated from school 15-16 years ago
स्कूल 15 16 इयर्स पहले ग्रेजुएट किया
He says, Sir, no one is worth even Rs.1 lakh per year to me.
कहता है सर मुझे ₹ लाख भी साल के कोई नहीं
I will give it because I have never done a job
देगा क्योंकि मैंने कभी जॉब ही नहीं करी
Is. so this is the issue that is happening that the
है। सो दिस इज द इशू दैट इज हैपनिंग दैट द
the next gen is feeling suffocated
नेक्स्ट जन इज फीलिंग सफोकेटेड
And it's not about boring. boring is a
एंड इट्स नॉट अबाउट बोरिंग। बोरिंग इज अ
Ellebaab and a Proxy for Over Bearing
एलेबाब और अ प्रोक्सी फॉर ओवर बियरिंग
Seniors in the Family.
सीनियर्स इन द फैमिली।
Because they are not allowing them to have autonomy. Lala
बिकॉज़ दे आर नॉट अलाउंग देम ऑटोनोमी। लाला
Lala
लाला
because we
हम क्योंकि
My word is my rule
मेरा वचन ही शासन है
And my rule will prevail but maybe this Lala
और मेरा ही शासन चलेगा बट शायद ये लाला
the problem is unsolvable too you are right to
प्रॉब्लम अनसॉल्वेबल भी है यू आर राइट टू
a great extent can't solve that lala
अ ग्रेट एक्सटेंट कांट सॉल्व दैट लाला
Look at the problem, I will tell you where it is
प्रॉब्लम देखो मैं बताऊं कि कहां
It is unsolvable where it is not
अनसॉल्वेबल है कहां नहीं है
If Lala you started this with Tata
अगर एक लाला आपने टाटा से शुरू किया था ये
Discussion
डिस्कशन
If I come on the custodian ship by ownership
मालकियत से अगर मैं कस्टोडियन शिप पे आ
Should I go? Let's take a simple example. First
जाऊं। लेट्स टेक अ सिंपल एग्जांपल। पहले
So I should have known that I would die.
तो मुझे यह पता होना चाहिए कि मैं मरूंगा।
Maybe I will die. I don't know maybe
मैं तो मरूंगा ना शायद। पता नहीं शायद
Lala might not have died if it seemed so. These
लाला शायद नहीं मरते होंगे जो लगे। ये
They are immortal. So
इमोर्टल होते हैं। तो
What do I think about these?
मेरे मेरा इनके बारे में क्या विचार है?
You did not ask, I am telling you that their
आपने पूछा नहीं मैं बता रहा हूं कि इनकी
What is thinking? that sometimes it is dharmasya
सोच क्या है? कि यदा यदा ही धर्मस्य
Guilty Bhavati Bharatam. There is nothing like that
ग्लानी भवती भारतम। ऐसी कुछ है ना कि
This is God's incarnation, we are but because of
भगवान का यह अवतार है हम बट बिकॉज़ ऑफ
humility they are calling themselves s
ह्यूमिलिटी दे आर कॉलिंग देमसेल्फ एस
King. I don't like to say God but
किंग। अच्छा नहीं लगता भगवान बोलना लेकिन
I know that I am God. Sir you
मुझे पता है कि मैं भगवान हूं। सर तुम्हें
You should know that I am God. this god
पता होना चाहिए भगवान हूं। दिस गॉड
complex
कॉम्प्लेक्स
is the problem and this is the reason they become
इज द प्रॉब्लम एंड दिस इज द रीज़ दे बिकम
so overbearing but maturity of them are
सो ओवरबियरिंग बट मैच्योरिटी ऑफ़ देम आर
Like this. but there are examples wit
लाइक दिस। बट आर देर एग्जांपल्स वि आर
Different? yes there are why not there are
डिफरेंट? यस देयर आर व्हाई नॉट देयर आर
Example Sunil Bharti Mittal Harsh
एग्जांपल सुनील भारती मित्तल हर्ष
Mariwala Rahul Bajaj All Of Them Have Groom
मारीवाला राहुल बजाज ऑल ऑफ़ देम हैव ग्रूम
there airs anand mahra you know kumar mangalam
देयर एयर्स आनंद मह्रा यू नो कुमार मंगलम
Birla Godrej Family: Is it Overbearing?
बिरला गोदरेज फैमिली क्या वो ओवरबेरिंग
Parents are their children, look at Azim Prem
पेरेंट्स हैं उनके बच्चे देखो अजीम प्रेम
yes how well are their children doing shiva
जी हाउ वेल आर देयर चिल्ड्रन डूइंग शिव
Nadar Roshni Nadar is doing a fabulous job
नादर रोशनी नादर इस डूइंग अ फैबुलस जॉब
How many examples are there in which we can say
कितने एग्जांपल्स है जिसमें हम कह सकते
that parents are not overbearing they have
हैं कि पेरेंट्स वर नॉट ओवरबियरिंग दे हैड
Give me a retirement date when I will die
अ रिटायरमेंट डेट दे न्यू कि मैं मरूंगा
Brother, I don't know when I will die, when will death come
भाई और पता नहीं कब मरूंगा मौत कब आएगी
If you don't know then groom the kids because
नहीं पता तो बच्चों को ग्रूम करो क्योंकि
I use bicycle stand for hand holding
मैं हाथ पकड़ने के लिए साइकिल का स्टैंड
But the thing
पकड़ने के लिए नहीं खड़ा होऊंगा बट द थिंग
is the people who think they are immortal
इज द पीपल हु थिंक दे आर इमोर्टल
and who thinks that the universe goes around
एंड हु थिंक दैट द यूनिवर्स गोज़ अराउंड
them and if they are not there then that is what happens
देम एंड इफ दे आर नॉट देयर वो होता है ना
An example that
एक एग्जांपल कि
I am carrying the globe on my body. Doz R
ग्लोब अपने इस पे कैरी कर रहा हूं। दोज़ आर
The People and You Know I Always Say This They Should
द पीपल एंड यू नो आई ऑलवेज से दिस दे शुड
Be very clear in their head. to the children
बी वेरी क्लियर इन देयर हेड। बच्चों को
Let me breathe friend. if you are so over
यार सांस लेने दो। अगर आप इतने ओवर
Be careful somebody needs to tell them. End
बियरिंग हो समबडी नीड्स टू टेल देम। एंड
I think the kids should figure it out
आई थिंक बच्चों को ही फिगर आउट कर लेना
Needed Study hard and get an MBA or
चाहिए। पढ़ाईवढ़ाई करके एमबीए करो या
Do engineering. Get a job. Papa I am coming
इंजीनियरिंग करो। नौकरी कर लो। पापा मैं आ
I have been in business. I am coming. next year
रहा हूं बिज़नेस में। आ रहा हूं। अगले साल
I am coming. I am coming next year. and when
आ रहा हूं। अगले साल आ रहा हूं। एंड व्हेन
your father that over bearing father is no lager
योर फादर दैट ओवर बियरिंग फादर इज नो लगर
Having the health and this thing then you come in
हैविंग द हेल्थ और दिस थिंग देन यू कम इन
this is a very important part of this whole
दिस इज वेरी इंपॉर्टेंट पार्ट ऑफ दिस होल
Story That
स्टोरी दैट
We need to understand the needs of this
वी नीड टू अंडरस्टैंड द नीड्स ऑफ़ दिस
generation also they can't take so much of
जनरेशन आल्सो दे कैन नॉट टेक सो मच ऑफ़
crap they want autonomy they want to live
क्रैप दे वांट ऑटोनोमी दे वांट टू लिव
their life they need some independence and above
देयर लाइफ दे नीड सम इंडिपेंडेंस एंड अबोव
All they need respect and they need
ऑल दे नीड़ रेस्पेक्ट एंड दे नीड़
Significance
सिग्निफिकेंस
He wants to create something. Meni
वो कुछ क्रिएट करना चाहते हैं। मेनी
Business Owners Kids Have Been Telling Me That
बिजनेस ओनर्स किड्स हैव बीन टेलिंग मी कि
Sir, I only wish to do something
सर मेरी एक ही इच्छा है कि मैं कुछ कर
show that I respect myself
दिखाऊं जिससे मैं अपने को रिस्पेक्ट कर
I may find that I just didn't inherit the you know
पाऊं कि मैंने सिर्फ यू नो इनहेरिट नहीं
Did. this is the issue that needs to be
किया। दिस इज द इशू दैट नीड्स टू बी
Solved. we know you and this is our effort you
सॉल्वड। हम यू नो एंड दिस इज़ आवर एफर्ट यू
No in this program that this problem
नो इन दिस प्रोग्राम कि इस प्रॉब्लम को
How to solve this?
किस कैसे सॉल्व करें।
Rajeev sir, I wish I could keep you here and do business
राजीव सर काश मैं आपको यहीं रखकर बिजनेस
I can take coaching for the rest of my life
कोचिंग ले सकूं फॉर द रेस्ट ऑफ माय लाइफ
but unfortunately we are out of time all i
बट अनफॉर्चुनेटली वी आउट ऑफ टाइम ऑल आई
want to say at this point is fun
वांट टू से एट दिस पॉइंट इज मजा आ गया
It was a very crisp value adding podcast
बहुत ही क्रिस्प वैल्यू ऐडिंग पॉडकास्ट था
These
ये
I taught myself business from Stanford
मैंने खुद बिज़नेस सीखा था एक स्टैनफोर्ड
From the series of lectures by Why Combinator
सीरीज ऑफ लेक्चर्स से व्हाई कॉम्बिनेटर ने
upload some lectures the it was called
कुछ लेक्चर्स अपलोड करे थे इट वास कॉल्ड
how to start a startup
हाउ टू स्टार्ट अ स्टार्टअप
But whatever has been discussed in this podcast today,
बट आज जो इस पडकास्ट में बातें हुई है,
It's much more practical than that series. So
इट्स मच मोर प्रैक्टिकल देन दैट सीरीज। सो
Happy to hear this Ranveer. I just hope that
हैप्पी टू हियर दिस रणवीर। आई जस्ट होप कि
The audience should understand what kind of gold is lying there
ऑडियंस समझे कि किस तरह का सोना पड़ा हुआ
It's in this podcast. Let them seek it out.
है इस पॉडकास्ट में। लेट देम सीक इट आउट।
So thank you sir. Appreciate your time,
तो थैंक यू सर। अप्रिशिएट योर टाइम,
Unappreciated. Thank you so much. and hope you
अप्रिशिएट। थैंक यू सो मच। एंड होप यू
Enjoyed it us. Yes, I enjoyed it a lot.
एंजॉयड इट अस। यस, आई एन्जॉयड इट अ लॉट।
Thank you. See you very soon. Thank you sir.
थैंक यू। सी यू वैरी सून। थैंक यू सर।
Thank you. Bye. So friends, this was today.
थैंक यू। बाय। सो दोस्तों, यह था आज का
Episode. When this episode was recorded
एपिसोड। जब ये एपिसोड रिकॉर्ड हुआ मेरी
The thought was that friend we should cut it and we should
थॉट ये थी कि यार शुड वी कट इट और शुड वी
Leave it deep as it is long lasting podcast
लीव इट डीप एज इट इज लंबा पडकास्ट रहना
Or do you want some condensed podcast but friend
चाहिए या थोड़ा सा कंडेंस पडकास्ट बट यार
Rajeev Gupta sir is so respected
राजीव गुप्ता सर इतने ज्यादा रिस्पेक्टेड
is because of his own career track record
है खुद के करियर ट्रैक रिकॉर्ड की वजह से
Given because of his own teaching skills
खुद के टीचिंग स्किल्स की वजह से दी
The obvious answer was leave it as it is
ऑब्वियस आंसर वास लीव इट एज इट इज दिस इज
Golden Advice This is the Kind of Advice
गोल्डन एडवाइस दिस इज द काइंड ऑफ़ एडवाइस
I wish I had it at the start of my own
आई विश आई हैड एट द स्टार्ट ऑफ माय ओन
Business Career Friends Rajeev Sir's Social
बिज़नेस करियर दोस्तों राजीव सर के सोशल
We will link the handles below. remember this
हैंडल्स हम नीचे लिंक कर देंगे। याद रखिए
If you are a second generation or third generation
अगर आप एक सेकंड जनरेशन या थर्ड जनरेशन
entrepreneur or if you're a second or
एंटरप्रेन्योर हो या अगर आप एक सेकंड या
Be the third generation of a business family. This
थर्ड जनरेशन ऑफ अ बिजनेस फैमिली हो। दिस
is one of the most important episode you will ever watch in
इज़ वन ऑफ़ द मोस्टेंट एपिसोड यू एवर वाच इन
Your life. so i will link rajeev saras
योर लाइफ। इसलिए आई विल लिंक राजीव सरस
Post Graduate Program at Masters
पोस्ट ग्रेजुएट प्रोग्राम एट मास्टर्स
Union down below as well. make sure you
यूनियन डाउन बिलो एज वेल। मेक श्योर यू
Check it out. couldn't point you towards a
चेक इट आउट। कुडंट पॉइंट यू टुवर्ड्स अ
Better Business Coach When It Comes to This
बेटर बिजनेस कोच व्हेन इट कम्स टू दिस
Specific Business Game Plan of Scaling a
स्पेसिफिक बिजनेस गेम प्लान ऑफ स्केलिंग अ
Family business. tell me this podcast
फैमिली बिज़नेस। बताइए यह वाला पॉडकास्ट
How was it? especially those of you who
कैसा लगा? एस्पेशली आप में से जो
Aspiring entrepreneurs, I ask you
एस्पायरिंग एंटरप्रेन्यर्स हैं, मैं आपसे
I want to know if you
यह जानना चाहूंगा कि आई वांट टू नो इफ यू
Gain value from this one and I want to
गेन वैल्यू फ्रॉम दिस वन एंड आई वांट टू
Know how we can improve this kind of
नो हाउ वी कैन इंप्रूव दिस काइंड ऑफ़
Business Conversations Even Further. Our
बिज़नेस कन्वर्सेशंस इवन फर्दर। हमारी
the intent is that too long too much
इंटेंशन यह है कि बहुत लंबे बहुत ज्यादा
We record and present deep podcasts
डीप पडकास्ट हम रिकॉर्ड करके पेश करें
in front of you through your feedback and through your
आपके सामने थ्रू योर फीडबैक एंड थ्रू योर
Inputs. Lots of love to you. thank you for
इनपुट्स। लॉट्स ऑफ लव टू यू। थैंक यू फॉर
Listening to TRS.
लिसनिंग टू टीआरएस।
yes
हो
[music]
[संगीत]